<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Bpm4Struts - HowTo (3)</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Controllers">
            <p>
                Modeling activity graphs allows you to clearly express the way your application flows from one
                state into another. This already helps a great deal in the code generation process, but all this
                effort would only make sense when you ould be able to actually insert your own code fragments
                into this process. UML elegantly allows this.
            </p>
            <p>
                Per use-case you will need to model a class in which you will put all the operations that can be
                called from within that use-case's activity.
            </p>
            <p>
                You will need to associate this class to the use-case somehow, the cartridge can't just guess which
                cartridge it corresponds to. Therefore we have two options, depending on the maturity of the UML
                tool you are using:
                <ul>
                    <li>Assign this class as the context of the activity graph (MagicDraw supports this),
                        this is a standard UML feature that, unfortunately, is often overlooked by CASE tools vendors.
                    </li>
                    <li>Add a tagged value to the controller, pointing to the use-case, like this:
                        <code>@andromda.struts.controller.usecase=My UseCase</code> (the value is the name
                        of the use-case).
                    </li>
                </ul>
                Either one of these options will do, we recommend using the former because that way you won't need
                to update the tagged value whenever you decide to change the name of the use-case (which can be a pain).
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="resources/howto/org/andromda/test/controllers.jpg"/>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                Now that we know how to define custom code operations we need to learn how
                to call them from within your activity graph, <a href="howto4.html">read on</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
