<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="joel@lighthouse-pmg.com">Joel Kozikowski</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - A bird's eye view</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="A Bird’s Eye view of AndroMDA">
            <p>By Joel Kozikowski</p>
            <p>
                <em>The purpose of this document is to give a high level view of the entire AndroMDA system so you can
                    quickly get up to speed in using it.  It is intended to be used by an experienced developer (but new
                    to AndroMDA) as a road map to find their way around all of the components. It does not go into
                    detail on any one aspect of the system.  Instead, it identifies common how does that work type
                    questions, and then points you to material for further study. A basic understanding of UML is
                    assumed. If you are completely new to UML, you may want to try one of the numerous books on the
                    subject before tackling AndroMDA. A good crash course on UML can be found here:
                    <a href="http://bdn.borland.com/article/0,1410,31863,00.html">
                        http://bdn.borland.com/article/0,1410,31863,00.html</a>
                </em>
            </p>
            <subsection name="System overview">
                <p>AndroMDA is a code generation tool that takes a UML model as input and generates source code as
                    output.  Using a series of template files (which you can customize if you wish), AndroMDA can
                    produce source code from a UML model in any programming language.  Default templates exist to
                    generate Java code (and in particular J2EE code).</p>
                <p>There are two primary components used in the AndroMDA system:
                    <ol>
                        <li>The AndroMDA code generation engine.</li>
                        <li>Apache’s Maven project builder and management system.</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>
                <p>The AndroMDA code generator is actually a generic code generation engine. The engine is a platform
                    that hosts code modules (called cartridges) that do the actual code generation.  An AndroMDA
                    cartridge is a collection of source code template files and Java helper classes (called Metafacades)
                    packaged into a .JAR file.  There are a variety of pre-existing cartridges that you can plug in to
                    the engine to generate code a particular way.  The pre-existing cartridges all generate Java source
                    code for various popular Open Source libraries (such as Spring, Hibernate, and J2EE). The engine is
                    not limited to these however.  You can write your own cartridges, and (at least in theory) generate
                    code from UML for any programming language.</p>
                <p>An excellent explanation/demonstration of AndroMDA’s capabilities can be found in the HowTo guide
                    explaining how to model using the Spring Cartridge.  There, you can see examples of a UML model, and
                    the resulting Java source code (very valuable to study).  For more details, see
                    <a href="../andromda-spring-cartridge/howto1.html">the Spring howto documentation</a>.
                </p>
                <p>Maven is actually an optional component.  The AndroMDA engine could be called directly from the
                    command line, from within an IDE, or from a build script (such as from within Ant).  However, a
                    series of Maven plug-ins already exist to greatly simplify the process of using AndroMDA. Unless you
                    are trying to integrate AndroMDA into a pre-existing project, using Maven is highly recommended.  It
                    is the normal way of accessing AndroMDA services.</p>
                <p>If you are unfamiliar with Maven, learning it first (at least at the conceptual level) is highly
                    recommended.  A good overview article of what Maven is and what it is capable of can be found here:
                    <a href="http://www.devx.com/java/Article/17204">http://www.devx.com/java/Article/17204</a>
                </p>
                <p>For a complete list of articles you can use to familiarize yourself with Maven, see
                    <a href="http://maven.apache.org/reference/articles.html">Maven articles</a>.
                </p>
                <p>For instructions on how to install the necessary components to get AndroMDA up and running see
                    <a href="../starting.html">Getting started</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Project development cycle">
                <p>The following is a typical AndroMDA project’s development cycle (for Java). Details for each step
                    follow this section.</p>
                <ol>
                    <li>Create a new project directory using the command
                        <b>maven andromdapp:generate</b>
                        (which calls a maven plug-in known as the maven app generator plug-in). 
                    </li>
                    <li>Configure the generated project to fit your specific needs</li>
                    <li>Use MagicDraw to edit the file
                        <b>&lt;
                            <i>projectDir</i>
                            &gt;/mda/src/uml/&lt;
                            <i>projectName</i>
                            &gt;Model.xmi
                        </b>
                        . This file is where you save your UML model.
                    </li>
                    <li>Generate code by issuing one of the following commands from your project’s root directory:</li>
                    <ol>
                        <li>
                            <b>maven mda</b>
                            (re)generates source code from the model
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <b>maven install</b>
                            (re)generates source code, including the database schema files, then builds all source
                            modules.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <b>maven create-schema</b>
                            installs the SQL DDL to your database if you are using AndroMDA to generate your persistence
                            layer (such as with Hibernate and/or Spring).  This command assumes the DDL file has already
                            been created (using
                            <b>maven install</b>
                            )
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                    <li>Hand code any methods requiring manual implementation in the source files found in
                        <b>&lt;
                            <i>projectDir</i>
                            &gt;/core/src/java
                        </b>
                        .
                    </li>
                    <li>Compile and test your code</li>
                    <li>As your project evolves, make refinements
                        <i>first</i>
                        to the UML model by re-starting the process from step 3 above.
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>A complete list of Maven goals for your project that you may want to use for step #4 above can be
                    found in the file
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;/readme.txt
                    </b>
                    (which is created by the app generator).
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Creating a new project">
                <p>To create a new project, first change to the desired PARENT directory of your soon to be created
                    project directory, and issue the
                    <b>maven andromdapp:generate</b>
                    command.  When asked for a project ID use a short name (without any spaces) that will represent the
                    sub-directory’s name.  For example, if in the
                    <b>\myProjects</b>
                    directory you generate a project with the ID myDemo, your project’s root directory will be
                    <b>/myProjects/myDemo</b>.
                </p>
                <p>For more information, see
                    <a href="../starting.html#My_first_AndroMDA_project">My first AndroMDA project</a> as well as
                    <a href="../maven-andromdapp-plugin/index.html">the andromdapp plugin</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Project Directory Structure">
                <p>The most significant sub-directories in the project structure created by the Maven app generation
                    plug-in are as follows:</p>
                <p>
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;/mda/src
                    </b>
                </p>
                <p>Where the UML model file is located.</p>
                <p>
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;/mda/conf
                    </b>
                </p>
                <p>Where the AndroMDA engine configuration file is located.</p>
                <p>
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;/core/target
                    </b>
                </p>
                <p>Where the code generator places most of the resulting files.  The SQL schema files are found in this
                    directory. Java source files are found in the
                    <b>src/</b>
                    sub-directory. You may view this code for study, but
                    <i>do not</i>
                    make any modifications to it, as it will be overwritten on subsequent runs of the code generator.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <b>&lt;projectDir&gt;/core/src</b>
                </p>
                <p>Source files that require manual implementation go here.  Files in this directory will NOT be
                    overwritten on subsequent runs of the code generator.</p>
                <p>For a complete description of project sub-directories, see the file
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;/readme.txt
                    </b>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="AndroMDA configuration">
                <p>The AndroMDA engine is ultimately driven by the configuration information found in the file
                    <b>andromda.xml</b>
                    .  If using a project generated by the Maven app generator plug-in, this file is located in the
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;/mda/conf
                    </b>
                    sub-directory. This file contains, among other things, the name of the UML model file to be used by
                    the engine, as well as configuration settings for the various AndroMDA Cartridges used by your
                    project (these settings are segregated from each other in sections called namespaces).
                </p>
                <p>For general information about the configuration information found in
                    <b>andromda.xml</b>, see <a href="../configuration.html">the configuration page</a>
                </p>
                <p>For information about cartridge specific configuration options, first go to the
                    <a href="../andromda-cartridges/index.html">AndroMDA Cartridge page</a>
                    , select the desired cartridge from the Available Cartridges menu on the left, then select the
                    Namespace option under the Documentation menu.
                </p>
                <p>If you used the Maven app generator (and subsequently use Maven to actually
                    <i>build</i>
                    your project), many of the configuration values found in
                    <b>andromda.xml</b>
                    are actually delegated up to Maven build properties.
                </p>
                <p>The file
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;project.properties
                    </b>
                    contains Maven properties that are passed down to
                    <b>andromda.xml</b>
                    (and other parts of the build scripts) that are project wide settings (regardless of which developer
                    is currently building the system, and which version is being built).  These include things such as
                    JDBC configuration settings, which database dialect you want Hibernate to use (e.g. Hypersonic,
                    mySQL, etc.).
                </p>
                <p>The file
                    <b>
                        <i>&lt;projectDir&gt;build.properties</i>
                    </b>
                    contains Maven properties that are specific to the version being built.
                </p>
                <p>Maven build properties can also be overridden on a workstation (and/or developer) by workstation
                    basis.  For more information about Maven build properties in general, see
                    <a href="http://maven.apache.org/reference/properties.html">
                        http://maven.apache.org/reference/properties.html</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Creating your UML Model">
                <p>In theory, AndroMDA can use the output of any UML modeling tool as its starting point for code
                    generation, provided the UML modeling tool can output to the Object Management Group’s industry
                    standard XML Metadata Interchange (XMI) file format (see
                    <a href="http://www.omg.org/technology/documents/formal/xmi.htm">
                        http://www.omg.org/technology/documents/formal/xmi.htm</a>).
                </p>
                <p>In <i>practice</i>
                    , you will save yourself a LOT of headache if you simply use MagicDraw as your UML tool (a free
                    community edition is available at
                    <a href="http://www.magicdraw.com/">http://www.magicdraw.com</a>
                    ).  All of the developers on the AndroMDA team use MagicDraw.  All of the testing of the Cartridges
                    is based on MagicDraw files.  And frankly, there seem to be some assumptions made in the AndroMDA
                    code that are based on MagicDraw (and its capabilities). For all intents and purposes, AndroMDA only
                    works with MagicDraw.
                </p>
                <p>AndroMDA code generation is driven by UML
                    <i>stereotypes</i>
                    .  In a nutshell, the engine traverses your UML model, looking for classes tagged with a specific
                    stereotype.  If it finds a stereotype it recognizes, the appropriate cartridge is called to generate
                    code for that class. Which stereotypes are recognized depend on the AndroMDA Cartridge(s) being
                    used. Stereotype recognition is case sensitive.
                </p>
                <p>A key concept in the Model Driven Architecture methodology is the idea of the developer first
                    creating a
                    <i>Platform Independent Model</i>
                    (the PIM) of the system.  By Platform Independent, that means a model devoid of any platform
                    <i>specific</i>
                    items (such as a class’s attribute defined using a Java data type like java.lang.String).  Many UML
                    tools are
                    <i>designed</i>
                    to generate Java code, so they use Java data types by default when modeling (violating the PIM
                    concept). AndroMDA expects UML models to contain
                    <i>generic</i>
                    data types (specifically, UML data types).
                </p>
                <p>To simplify modeling (insuring the proper UML data types and stereotypes are used), the AndroMDA UML
                    Profile has been developed which can (and really
                    <i>must</i>
                    ) be included as part of your model. The profile is named
                    <b>
                        <i>andromda-profile-XXX.xml.zip</i>
                    </b>
                    (where XXX is the version of AndroMDA you are using).  The profile contains all of the UML data
                    types, stereotypes, and tagged values that are known to work with AndroMDA and all of its
                    Cartridges.  Any new UML model should begin by importing this file into your project (with
                    MagicDraw, this is done by using the File_Use Profile/Module menu option). See the
                    <a href="../faq.html#profile-import">Frequently Asked Questions</a>
                    for more information.
                </p>
                <p>If your project was generated using the Maven app generation plug-in, the pre-created project model
                    file
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;/mda/src/uml/&lt;
                        <i>projectName</i>
                        &gt;Model.xmi
                    </b>
                    will already have included this profile.
                </p>
                <p>The profile file itself can be found in the AndroMDA source distribution in the
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>sourceDir</i>
                        &gt;/etc/profile/target
                    </b>
                    sub-directory.  Frequently, when opening a UML file with MagicDraw, it will ask for you to specify
                    the location of this file.  Copying the profile file from the AndroMDA source dir to MagicDraw’s
                    profile directory (
                    <b>/Program Files/Magic Draw UML/profiles</b>
                    on a Windows XP installation) will allow MagicDraw to find the profile file on its own.
                </p>
                <p>For general information on AndroMDA modeling, see
                    <a href="../modeling.html">Modeling in AndroMDA</a>
                </p>
                <p>For a tutorial on creating models that work with the Spring cartridge (the most popular AndroMDA
                    plug-in), see
                    <a href="../andromda-spring-cartridge/howto.html">the AndroMDA Spring cartridge howto</a>
                </p>
                <p>For information about cartridge specific stereotypes and tagged values, first go to
                    <a href="../andromda-cartridges/index.html">the AndroMDA
                    Cartridge page</a>, select the desired cartridge from the Available
                    Cartridges menu on the left, and then select the
                    Profile option on the left hand menu.
                </p>
                <p>For more information on the Model Driven Architecture methodology in general, see
                    <a href="http://www.omg.org/mda/">http://www.omg.org/mda/</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="How AndroMDA generates code">
                <p>The following describes the process used by the AndroMDA engine to generate code.  Details of each
                    step follow this section.</p>
                <ol>
                    <li>All of the cartridges that the project requires are loaded by the engine.</li>
                    <li>The engine then parses the UML model’s XMI file, creating an object tree of the model for use by
                        the engine and the cartridge templates.  In addition to the main object tree, helper classes
                        (called Metafacades) are created to simplify the work of the cartridge templates.</li>
                    <li>The engine traverses the object tree, looking for classes tagged with stereotypes it
                        recognizes</li>
                    <li>For each class located, the appropriate cartridge template(s) are identified and dispatched to
                        generate code.  Multiple source code files may be generated for each tagged class in the model:
                        more than one template in a given cartridge may generate code for any given class; more than one
                        cartridge may generate code for any given class. The default templates for a cartridge may be
                        used, or a customized version may be used, depending on your configuration.</li>
                    <li>Step #4 is repeated for every class in the model.</li>
                </ol>
                <h3>Loading the Cartridges to use</h3>
                <p>When the AndroMDA engine is started, it first loads and activates the cartridges it will use.  For a
                    particular cartridge to be used, the cartridge .JAR file must:</p>

                <ol>
                    <li>Be in the Java  CLASSPATH of the AndroMDA engine</li>
                    <li>Be activated by referencing its namespace in the
                        <b>andromda.xml</b>
                        configuration file.
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>To put the cartridge in the CLASSPATH of the engine if using the Maven plug-in, modify the
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;/mda/project.xml
                    </b>
                    file and add a &lt;dependency&gt; for the cartridge to the &lt;dependencies&gt; section.  For more
                    information, see Using a cartridge at
                    <a href="../andromda-cartridges/index.html">the cartridges index page</a>
                </p>
                <p>If using the Maven plug-in, the
                    <b>andromda.xml</b>
                    configuration file is located in the
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>projectDir</i>
                        &gt;/mda/conf
                    </b>
                    directory.  This file contains one or more &lt;namespace&gt; tags to activate the cartridge(s).
                </p>
                <p>For more information on configuring a cartridge’s namespace, see
                    <a href="../configuration.html#namespace">configuring AndroMDA namespaces</a>
                </p>
                <h3>Loading the UML model</h3>
                <p>Just as there is a standardized object model to represent a parsed XML file (The Document Object
                    Model) and popular Java implementations of the DOM API (such as Apache’s Xerces), so is there a
                    standardized object model for the metadata stored in a UML model.  The standardized object model
                    that represents UML metadata is called The Meta Object Facility (the MOF – see
                    <a href="http://www.omg.org/mof">http://www.omg.org/mof</a>
                    ).  One Java implementation of this API is Netbeans’ MDR (MetaData Repository – see
                    <a href="http://mdr.netbeans.org/">http://mdr.netbeans.org/</a>
                    ).  The AndroMDA engine uses the Netbeans MDR to load the UML model into memory.
                </p>
                <p>The act of generating code from the UML model requires some computation not easily handled by the
                    simple scripting capabilities found in the template engine used by AndroMDA.  Things such as
                    traversing the MDR looking for relationships among classes, testing for certain conditions in the
                    model, formulating identifier names and package names based on attributes found in the UML model –
                    these all require computation handled easier in Java code.  To simplify the source code templates,
                    the Facade design pattern is used to create helper classes that shield the complexities of the MDR
                    from the template.  These helper classes are called Metafacades (for meta data facades).  Each
                    cartridge used by the AndroMDA engine usually contains its own set of Metafacades to aid in platform
                    specific code generation.  It is the engine’s responsibility to instantiate these Metafacades for
                    use by the source code templates.</p>
                <p>For more information about Metafacades, see
                    <a href="../andromda-metafacades/index.html">the metafacades documentation</a>
                </p>
                <h3>Matching Stereotypes to Cartridges</h3>
                <p>After initializing, the AndroMDA engine traverses the UML model, looking for classes marked with a
                    specific stereotype.  When it finds a stereotype it recognizes (or more specifically, a stereotype
                    that a cartridge is known to recognize), the appropriate cartridge(s) is called to generate the
                    code.</p>
                <p>A cartridge is actually a .JAR file.  In this .JAR file there is (amongst other things), a file named
                    <b>/META-INF/andromda/cartridge.xml</b>
                    .  This file is called the Cartridge Descriptor. Inside the Cartridge Descriptor, there are
                    <span>&lt;template&gt;</span>
                    tags that specify the code generation templates available from the Cartridge.  Inside each
                    <span>&lt;template&gt;</span>
                    tag is a
                    <span>&lt;modelElements&gt;</span>
                    tag. This
                    <span>&lt;modelElements&gt;</span>
                    node will contain one or more
                    <span>&lt;modelElement&gt;</span>
                    nodes.  Each
                    <span>&lt;modelElement&gt;</span>
                    is used to specify (among other things) the stereotype the template maps to.  This specification is
                    done in one of two ways:
                </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>directly via an attribute of the
                        <span>&lt;modelElement&gt;</span>
                        tag named stereotype.  The value of the stereotype attribute specifies the stereotype the
                        template maps to.
                    </li>
                    <li>indirectly via a
                        <span>&lt;type&gt;
                        </span>
                        inner node.  The
                        <span>&lt;type&gt;</span>
                        node specifies the name of the Metafacade class the template uses. The Metafacade’s definition,
                        in turn, contains a definition of the stereotype the Metafacade maps to. The Metafacade’s
                        definition is found in the Metafacade Descriptor – a file in the cartridge .JAR file named
                        <b>/META-INF/andromda-metafacades.xml</b>
                        .  The Metafacade Descriptor contains
                        <span>&lt;metafacade&gt;</span>
                        tags for each metafacade used by the cartridge.  Each
                        <span>&lt;metafacade&gt;</span>
                        tag in turn contains a
                        <span>&lt;stereotype&gt;</span>
                        tag which defines the name of the stereotype the metafacade maps to.
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>For more information on the Cartridge Descriptor, see The Cartridge Descriptor at
                    <a href="../andromda-cartridges/index.html">the cartridge index page</a>
                    .
                </p>
                <p>For more information on the Metafacade Descriptor, see
                    <a href="../andromda-metafacades/configuring.html">configuring metafacades</a>
                </p>
                <h3>Generating code from templates</h3>
                <p>Once the AndroMDA engine has identified a class from the UML model and matched it to a cartridge, the
                    appropriate templates are called to generate code.</p>
                <p>By default, AndroMDA uses the Apache Software Foundation’s Velocity template engine to generate
                    code.  Mechanisms exist to allow other template engines to be used, but in practice, Velocity does
                    most of the work.  If you are unfamiliar with Velocity, see
                    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/docs/user-guide.html#What%20is%20Velocity?">
                        http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/docs/user-guide.html#What%20is%20Velocity?</a>
                    for a good overview.
                </p>
                <p>To see all of the templates available from a particular cartridge, examine the contents of the
                    cartridge’s Cartridge Descriptor file (
                    <b>/META-INF/andromda/cartridge.xml)</b>
                    .  This file can be found in one of two places:
                </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>inside of the cartridge .JAR file itself</li>
                    <li>if it is part of the default AndroMDA source distribution, in the
                        <b>/src/META-INF/andromda</b>
                        sub-directory of the cartridge’s source directory (
                        <b>&lt;
                            <i>androMDASourceDir</i>
                            &gt;/cartridges/&lt;
                            <i>nameOfCartridge</i>
                            &gt;
                        </b>
                        )
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>Each template available for use in the cartridge is defined in a
                    <span>&lt;template&gt;</span>
                    node inside the Cartridge Descriptor.  The
                    <span>&lt;template&gt;</span>
                    node contains several pieces of important information:
                </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>The path attribute specifies the complete path (inside of the cartridge .JAR file) to the
                        template file</li>
                    <li>The outlet attribute specifies (indirectly) the sub-directory where the source file will be
                        written to.  An outlet is a conceptual name assigned to a sub-directory. It is actually the name
                        of a property found in the cartridge’s namespace in the
                        <b>andromda.xml</b>
                        configuration file.  For example, an outlet named config-files would mean there is a namespace
                        property named config-files in
                        <b>andromda.xml</b>
                        that specifies the sub-directory where all configuration files are to be written to.
                    </li>
                    <li>The overwrite attribute specifies whether or not the template will overwrite pre-existing source
                        files on subsequent runs of the code generator.  In general, source code that requires hand
                        modification will have the overwrite attribute set to false and will have a different outlet
                        than code that does not require hand modification.</li>
                    <li>The
                        <span>&lt;modelElements&gt;</span>
                        tag defines the Metafacade used by the template.  The variable attribute of the
                        <span>&lt;modelElements&gt;</span>
                        tag defines the name of the instance variable to be used by the template.  That template
                        variable will be an instance of the specified Metafacade.
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>The
                    <span>&lt;modelElements&gt;</span>
                    tag of a
                    <span>&lt;template&gt;</span>
                    definition contains a
                    <span>&lt;modelElement&gt;</span>
                    tag, which may in turn contain a
                    <span>&lt;type&gt;</span>
                    tag.  The
                    <span>&lt;type&gt;</span>
                    tag specifies the Metafacade class that the template will use.  The
                    <span>&lt;type&gt;</span>
                    tag may optionally contain
                    <span>&lt;property&gt;</span>
                    tags.  These
                    <span>&lt;property&gt;</span>
                    tags are used for conditional code generation.  If a value is specified for a property, that
                    property
                    <i>must</i>
                    match that value for template code to be saved to disk.  If the
                    <span>&lt;property&gt;</span>
                    tag does not contain a value, then that property simply must be defined.  The property might be a
                    namespace property defined in the
                    <b>andromda.xml</b>
                    config file (to allow for the code generation to be defined at configuration time).  The property
                    may instead be a property set by the template after it has run.  This allows the template itself to
                    determine if code should be generated at run-time.
                </p>
                <p>For more information on how cartridges work in general, see
                    <a href="../andromda-cartridges/index.html">the cartridge index page</a>
                </p>
                <p>The Velocity Template Language reference guide can be found here
                    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/docs/vtl-reference-guide.html">
                        http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/docs/vtl-reference-guide.html</a>
                </p>
                <p>For more details on the Velocity template engine in general, see
                    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/index.html">
                        http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/index.html</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Customizing code generation">
                <p>There are several ways to customize the code generation process. </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>Override a template from a pre-existing cartridge with a custom version</li>
                    <li>Customize the entire cartridge, re-compiling the .JAR file</li>
                    <li>Write your own cartridge from scratch.</li>
                </ol>
                <h3>Overriding a cartridge’s default template(s)</h3>
                <p>The simplest way to customize code generation is to slightly modify or simply re-write one or two
                    templates in an existing cartridge.  Assuming a particular cartridge does mostly what you are
                    looking for, but you need to change or extend its functionality, you can instruct the AndroMDA
                    engine to use your template rather than the one from the cartridge’s .JAR file.</p>
                <ol>
                    <li>locate the
                        <i>original</i>
                        template file you wish to modify.  These files can be found in the
                        <b>/templates</b>
                        sub-directory of the cartridge’s .JAR file. If you have the AndroMDA source distribution
                        installed on your machine, you can also find them in the
                        <b>/src/templates</b>
                        sub-directory of the of the cartridge’s source directory (
                        <b>&lt;
                            <i>androMDASourceDir</i>
                            &gt;/cartridges/&lt;
                            <i>nameOfCartridge</i>
                            &gt;
                        </b>
                        ).
                    </li>
                    <li>Copy the desired files to your project directory.  If your project conforms to the standard
                        project structure using the Maven plug-ins, the best place to put your copy is in the
                        <b>/mda/src</b>
                        directory of your project (such as
                        <b>&lt;
                            <i>projectDir</i>
                            &gt;/mda/src/customTemplates
                        </b>
                        /).  Since you may override templates from more than one cartridge, it is also a good idea to
                        further segregate each cartridge into its own sub-directory.  Finally, it is important you honor
                        the template structure found in the cartridge.  So, to override the hibernate.hbm.xml.vsl
                        template for version 3, place a copy of that file in the sub-directory
                        <b>&lt;
                            <i>projectDir</i>
                            &gt;mda/src/customTemplates/andromda-hibernate/templates/hibernate3
                        </b>
                        .
                    </li>
                    <li>In the cartridge’s
                        <span>&lt;namespace&gt;</span>
                        entry in the
                        <b>andromda.xml</b>
                        configuration file, specify a mergeLocation property. For our example Hibernate template
                        overwrite, we would make the following addition in the andromda.xml file:
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <source language="xml">
<![CDATA[
<namespace name="hibernate">
   …
   <properties>
      …
      <property name="mergeLocation">${maven.src.dir}/customTemplates/andromda-hibernate</property>
      …
   </properties>
   …
</namespace>
]]>
                </source>
                <p>When you specify a mergeLocation property, the AndroMDA engine will first look in your mergeLocation
                    directory when looking for a particular template file.  If it does not find it, it will fall back on
                    the cartridge’s .JAR file.</p>
                <p>See Overriding cartridge resources at
                    <a href="../andromda-cartridges/index.html#mergeLocation">overriding cartridge resources</a>
                    for more details.
                </p>
                <h3>Customizing existing cartridges</h3>
                <p>The standard cartridges that come with AndroMDA can be modified and extended if you need more control
                    than a simple template override can provide. The source directory for a cartridge comes with the
                    AndroMDA source distribution.  The cartridge’s root directory is
                    <b>&lt;
                        <i>androMDASourceDir</i>
                        &gt;/cartridges/&lt;
                        <i>nameOfCartridge</i>
                        &gt;
                    </b>
                    . All the source files are located under that directory.  From the cartridge root directory, the
                    command
                    <b>maven install</b>
                    will re-build and re-package the cartridge.
                </p>
                <p>For more details on developing cartridges, see
                    <a href="../andromda-cartridges/developing.html">developing cartridges</a>
                </p>
                <h3>Writing cartridges from scratch</h3>
                <p>Entire cartridges can also be developed.  The most difficult aspect of cartridge development is the
                    probable need for custom Metafacades.  The good news is that AndroMDA can be used to develop
                    metafacades.  You can model your metafacade with MagicDraw, then have AndroMDA generate the
                    metafacade code.</p>
                <p>For more details on developing metafacades, see
                    <a href="../andromda-metafacades/developing.html">developing metafacades</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
