<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="tfmorris@tigris.org">Tom Morris</author>
        <title>Create Timecard Entity using ArgoUML</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Create Timecard Entity using ArgoUML">
            <p>
                This page provides directions to create the Timecard entity using ArgoUML along with
                its associations to the Person entity. The model is shown below for your reference.
            </p>

            <p>
                <div align="center">
                    <img src="../../../images/argouml/TimecardEntity.png"/>
                </div>
            </p>

            <p>
              <ol>
                <li>In the TimeTracker model open the Domain Objects diagram. This diagram already
                contains the <code>Person</code> class.</li>

                <li>Now add the <code>Timecard</code> class to the diagram and set its stereotype
                to Entity.</li>

                <li>Next we need to add the <code>status</code> attribute to <code>Timecard</code>.
                However note that <code>status</code> is of type <code>TimecardStatus</code> which
                is an enumeration. We must define <code>TimecardStatus</code> first. So create a
                class called <code>TimecardStatus</code>. Give it a stereotype of
                <code>Enumeration</code>. Add four attributes to it representing the
                enumeration values. We give each attribute an initial value which is
                a string with its name in uppercase (ie DRAFT, SUBMITTED, APPROVED, and REJECTED)
                These values can't be entered directly on the diagram, so type them
                into the Initial Value field on the property panel for each attribute.
                Now that we have defined <code>TimecardStatus</code>, we
                can add the <code>status</code> attribute to <code>Timecard</code> as shown above.</li>

                <li>Next add the <code>begDate</code> and <code>comments</code> attributes to <code>Timecard</code>.</li>

                <li>Now we must add the association between <code>Timecard</code> and <code>Person</code>.
                To do this, use the Association tool in the toolbar (5th icon from the left). Click on the
                the downward pointing triangle just to its right to activate the pulldown menu and select
                the directional association tool with the arrowhead in place of the default straight line
                (bidirectional) tool.  Click on the
                <code>Timecard</code> class, drag your mouse to the <code>Person</code> class and release the
                mouse. A new association will be created.</li>

                <li>Right-click on the <code>Timecard</code> end and uncheck Navigable. This will make the
                association one-way from <code>Timecard</code> to <code>Person</code>.</li>

                <li>Right-click on the <code>Timecard</code> end of the association and select
                Multiplicity -&gt; 0..*.  We'll leave the other end at the default multiplicity of 1.</li>

                <li>Double click just below the <code>Person</code> end of the association and
                type the name <code>submitter</code>. The
                <code>Timecard</code> end does not have to be named because it is not navigable.
                This completes the submitter association from <code>Timecard</code> to <code>Person</code>.</li>

                <li>Similarly add an <code>approver</code> association from <code>Timecard</code> to
                <code>Person</code>. Move the associations up or down as appropriate so they do not overlap
                each other.</li>

                <li>Make sure your class diagram matches the one shown above.</li>

                <li>Save the model by selecting File > Save Project.</li>
              </ol>
            </p>

            <p>
              We are now ready to generate code for <code>Timecard</code>. Please go back to the main
              tutorial page and continue from where you left off.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
