<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="naresh@andromda.org">Naresh Bhatia</author>
        <title>AndroMDA.NET - Getting Started</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Getting started with AndroMDA.NET">
            <p>
                Understanding new tools and technologies can be a daunting task. AndroMDA
                is no exception. This tutorial serves as a gentle introduction to the power
                of AndroMDA. We will show you step-by-step how to set up your development
                environment and build your first .NET application. Instead of mechanically
                going through a series of steps, we will focus on ideas and concepts behind
                what we are doing. Armed with this knowledge you will be well positioned to
                take on real world challenges. Please set aside half a day of quality
                uninterrupted time to learn AndroMDA as there is lot to learn. Then brew a
                good cup of coffee and immerse yourself in the wonderful world of Model
                Driven Architecture.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Prepare the development environment">
            <p>
                What follows is a step-by-step guide to set up your development environment
                for AndroMDA. We assume that you are working on a Windows platform.
            </p>

            <subsection name="Install SQL Server">
                <p>
                    Install SQL Server 2000 or SQL Server 2005. You should be able to use
                    other databases by configuring NHibernate appropriately. However for the
                    purpose of this tutorial we will assume SQL Server.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install Visual Studio">
                <p>
                    Install Visual Studio 2005. During the installation proces, do not use the
                    default option of installing SQL Server Express Edition. You have already
                    installed SQL Server in the previous step. Also note that AndroMDA.NET
                    currently supports generation of C# only, other .NET languages are not
                    supported.
                </p>
                
                <p> 
                    You may be able to use AndroMDA with Visual Studio 2003 (and .NET 1.1)
                    but you will have to do bunch of configuration manually. In comparison,
                    Visual Studio 2005 is a much more productive environment and if you
                    have any flexibility switch over to this version as quickly as you
                    possibly can!
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install Java">
                <p>
                    Install J2SE Development Kit 5.0 (JDK 5.0) from
                    <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/download.jsp" target="_blank">here</a>.
                    This is the preferred version of the JDK for AndroMDA.NET. We also support
                    JDK version 1.4. If you prefer this version, you can download it from
                    <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/download.html" target="_blank">here</a>.
                </p>

                <p>
                    Make sure that the <code>JAVA_HOME</code> environment variable is pointing to
                    the directory where you installed the JDK. It is possible you have this
                    variable set already, but just to make sure here's how to check.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ol>
                        <li>
                            Go to the control panel and double-click on <code>System</code>.
                            If you are a Windows XP user it's possible you have to open
                            <code>Performance and Maintenance</code> before you will see
                            the <code>System</code> icon.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Go to the <code>Advanced</code> tab and click on
                            <code>Environment Variables</code>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Make sure you have set the <code>JAVA_HOME</code> variable set
                            and it is pointing to the directory where you installed the JDK.
                            If not, add/edit the variable and set it to the correct value,
                            e.g. C:\Program Files\Java\jdk1.5.0. You may add the variable
                            to the list of user variables or system variables.
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install Maven">
                <p>
                    <a href="http://maven.apache.org/" target="_blank">Maven</a> is a
                    software project management and comprehension tool. Based on the
                    concept of a project object model (POM), Maven can manage a project's
                    build, reporting and documentation from a central piece of information.
                    We will now install Maven and configure it to download dependencies
                    from the AndroMDA server whenever it needs to.
                    <ol>
                        <li>
                            Download Maven 1.0.2 from this site:
                            <a href="http://maven.apache.org/start/download.html" target="_blank">
                            http://maven.apache.org/start/download.html</a>. Note that later
                            versions of Maven are not yet supported by AndroMDA.NET.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Install the downloaded binary. (We will assume you installed it in
                            <code>C:\Program Files\Apache Software Foundation\Maven 1.0.2</code>)
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            If the installation would complain that the JAVA_HOME environment
                            is not set then make sure you have correctly set it and close
                            Windows Explorer or <a href="http://www.ghisler.com" target="_blank">
                            Total Commander</a>, whatever it is you are using and start it again.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Go to your <code>home</code> directory. (If your login is
                            <code>foo</code> this means here:
                            <code>C:\Documents and Settings\foo</code>)
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Create a file there, called <code>build.properties</code> and
                            add the following line in there. This line instructs Maven to
                            look for artifacts at the AndroMDA site in addition to the ibiblio site.<br/>
<code>maven.repo.remote=http://www.ibiblio.org/maven,http://team.andromda.org/maven</code><br/>
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Setup Environment variables">
                <p>
                    We have seen earlier how to set environment variables such as
                    <code>JAVA_HOME</code>, it is strongly recommended to set the
                    following variables before continuing. We repeat <code>JAVA_HOME</code>
                    here just for completeness.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property</th>
                            <th>Value</th>
                            <th>Required?</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>JAVA_HOME</td>
                            <td>Java installation directory, e.g. <code>C:\Program Files\Java\jdk1.5.0</code></td>
                            <td>Yes</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>MAVEN_HOME</td>
                            <td>Maven installation directory, e.g.
                                <code>C:\Program Files\Apache Software Foundation\Maven 1.0.2</code>
                                (this may have already been set by the Maven installer)</td>
                            <td>Yes</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>MAVEN_OPTS</td>
                            <td>Parameters to pass to the Java VM when running Maven. Set this
                                value to: <code>-XX:MaxPermSize=128m -Xmx512m</code>
                                (required to build the AndroMDA contrib project)</td>
                            <td>Yes</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>PATH</td>
                            <td>This makes sure the system will search for console commands in
                                the directories listed here. If this property already exists you
                                should simply add <code>%JAVA_HOME%\bin;%MAVEN_HOME%\bin</code>
                            </td>
                            <td>Yes</td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install AndroMDA C# Application plugin">
                <p>
                    Next we will download and install the AndroMDA C# Application plugin
                    to the MAVEN_HOME\plugins directory. This plugin allows creation of
                    C# starter applications that use AndroMDA. This is the only AndroMDA
                    artifact that we will install explicitly. All other artifacts, such
                    as AndroMDA cartridges, will be automatically downloaded by the
                    Maven scripts generated by the plugin.
                </p>

                <p>
                    To install the C# Application plugin open a Command Prompt and
                    Execute the following command. Make sure you get a "BUILD SUCCESSFUL"
                    message at the end of the command output.
                </p>

                <p><code>maven plugin:download -DgroupId=andromda -DartifactId=maven-andromdacsapp-plugin -Dversion=1.0-SNAPSHOT</code></p>

                <p>
                    Notice that you will now have <code>maven-andromdacsapp-plugin-1.0-SNAPSHOT.jar</code>
                    installed at MAVEN_HOME\plugins
                    (<code>C:\Program Files\Apache Software Foundation\Maven 1.0.2\plugins</code>
                    for this example).
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install a UML tool">
                <p>
                    Install a tool that will allow you to model your applications in UML and
                    export these models into a format that AndroMDA can understand. AndroMDA
                    currently supports UML 1.4 and XMI 1.2. Please follow one of the links
                    below to install the UML tool of your choice. (As of this writing only
                    one tool is supported. We invite UML tool vendors and open-source projects
                    to test their tools with AndroMDA and supply installation instructions for
                    inclusion in this section.)
                </p>

                <p>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/magicdraw/install.html" target="_blank">MagicDraw 9.5</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="My first AndroMDA application">
            <p>
                Now that the development environment is ready to go, it is time to build our first AndroMDA
                application. We will design and implement a simple TimeTracker application that allows users
                to enter timecards. Note that a completed version of this application is available under the
                samples directory. Please feel free to refer to it while going through this tutorial.
            </p>

            <p>
                The diagram below shows four key components of the TimeTracker application and their relationships.
                We will create a Visual Studio project for each of these components. What follows is a high-level
                description of each component.
                <p>
                    <div align="center">
                        <img src="images/TimeTrackerComponents.gif"/>
                    </div>
                </p>
                    <ol>
                        <li><strong>TimeTrackerCommon</strong> is a class library that contains classes common to
                        multiple tiers, for example value objects and enumerations.</li>

                        <li><strong>TimeTrackerCore</strong> is a class library that packages the entities and the
                        data access layer for the TimeTracker application. A key design principle
                        used throughout AndroMDA recommends that entities should reside only in the middle-tier of an
                        application, i.e. in the data-access layer and/or in the services layer. Specifically, the
                        front-end and other applications should not have direct access to entities. Instead
                        should be converted to value objects before transfer to/from other tiers. This approach
                        has several advantages. First of all the data passed to other tiers can be massaged to
                        present a view that is more useful or efficient compared to passing entities in their
                        entirety. Sometimes you may want to limit what gets passed to other tiers based on the
                        access rights of the requesting user. For example you may want to return an EmployeeVO
                        object as the return value of a web service call which has the salary field stripped out.
                        The second benefit of this approach is that it allows the middle-tier to act as a gatekeeper
                        of data that can be merged into entities without compromising their integrity. The middle-tier
                        can perform business validations and check for sanity of incoming data. Finally, this
                        approach also helps in controlling what exactly gets serialized when passing information
                        between tiers. As you know, entities can be interconnected to form complex networks.
                        Automatic serialization of these networks could result in transfer of more then necessary
                        set of entities across the wire. In addition, some transport layers have restrictions
                        on how entities can be serialized. For example, in case of web services it is easier to
                        represent data in tree structures compared to networks. Also web services do not understand
                        C# collections. Collections have to be converted into arrays before passing them back and
                        forth. This translation is easily facilitated by the use of value objects.</li>

                        <li><strong>TimeTrackerConsole</strong> is an administrative console application that allows
                        creation and display of various entities used in the TimeTracker application. It demonstrates
                        how to use the entities and data access layer provided by the <code>TimeTrackerCore</code>
                        library.</li>

                        <li><strong>SchemaExport</strong> is another administrative application that generates DDL from
                        the entities defined in the <code>TimeTrackerCore</code> library. This DDL can be used to
                        create tables that will store the TimeTracker entities. SchemaExport also has the
                        capability to directly create the tables in a database.</li>
                    </ol>
            </p>

            <p>
                In this section we will perform the one-time set up that is necessary to start any AndroMDA
                application. Subsequent sections will describe the iterative development process that follows
                this initial set up. So roll up your sleeves and let's get started!
            </p>

            <subsection name="Create a Visual Studio Solution">
                <p>
                    We start by creating a blank Visual Studio solution and populating it with the projects
                    that make up the TimeTracker application.
                    <ol>
                        <li>Start Visual Studio 2005.</li>
                        <li>Select File > New > Project...</li>
                        <li>Under Project types (left panel) select Other Project Types > Visual Studio Solutions</li>
                        <li>Under Templates (right panel) choose Blank Solution.</li>
                        <li>In the Name field below, enter <code>TimeTracker</code> as the name of the solution.</li>
                        <li>In the Location field, enter a directory where you want to create the solution.
                            We will assume the location to be C:\.</li>
                        <li>Now click OK. A blank solution will be created at C:\TimeTracker.</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                    Follow the steps below to add a project called TimeTrackerCommon to our solution. As mentioned
                    earlier, this project will generate a class library containing classes common to multiple tiers.
                    <ol>
                        <li>In Solution Explorer, right-click on the TimeTracker solution and
                            select Add > New Project....</li>
                        <li>Under Project types (left panel) select Visual C# > Windows</li>
                        <li>Under Templates (right panel) choose Class Library.</li>
                        <li>In the Name field below, enter <code>TimeTrackerCommon</code>
                            as the name of the project.</li>
                        <li>Make sure the Location field contains the name of the solution directory.
                            In this example, the location should be C:\TimeTracker.</li>
                        <li>Now click OK. A class library project will be created at
                            C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerCommon.</li>
                        <li>Delete the automatically generated class file called Class1.cs.</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                    Follow the steps below to add a project called TimeTrackerCore to our solution. This project will
                    generate a class library containing the entities and the data access layer for the
                    TimeTracker application.
                    <ol>
                        <li>In Solution Explorer, right-click on the TimeTracker solution and
                            select Add > New Project....</li>
                        <li>Under Project types (left panel) select Visual C# > Windows</li>
                        <li>Under Templates (right panel) choose Class Library.</li>
                        <li>In the Name field below, enter <code>TimeTrackerCore</code>
                            as the name of the project.</li>
                        <li>Make sure the Location field contains the name of the solution directory.
                            In this example, the location should be C:\TimeTracker.</li>
                        <li>Now click OK. A class library project will be created at
                            C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerCore.</li>
                        <li>Delete the automatically generated class file called Class1.cs.</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                    Follow the steps below to add a project called TimeTrackerConsole to our solution.
                    This project will generate a console application that allows creation and display
                    of various entities used by TimeTracker.
                    <ol>
                        <li>In Solution Explorer, right-click on the TimeTracker solution and
                            select Add > New Project....</li>
                        <li>Under Project types (left panel) select Visual C# > Windows</li>
                        <li>Under Templates (right panel) choose Console Application.</li>
                        <li>In the Name field below, enter <code>TimeTrackerConsole</code>
                            as the name of the project.</li>
                        <li>Make sure the Location field contains the name of the solution directory.
                            In this example, the location should be C:\TimeTracker.</li>
                        <li>Now click OK. A console application project will be created at
                            C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerConsole.</li>
                        <li>In Solution Explorer, right-click on the TimeTrackerConsole project and
                            select Add > New Item....</li>
                        <li>Select the template called Application Configuration File.</li>
                        <li>Make sure the Name field contains the name App.config and click Add.
                            A new App.config file will be added to the project.</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                    Follow the steps below to add a project called SchemaExport to our solution.
                    This project will generate a console application that allows DDL generation from
                    the entities defined in the <code>TimeTrackerCore</code> library.
                    <ol>
                        <li>In Solution Explorer, right-click on the TimeTracker solution and
                            select Add > New Project....</li>
                        <li>Under Project types (left panel) select Visual C# > Windows</li>
                        <li>Under Templates (right panel) choose Console Application.</li>
                        <li>In the Name field below, enter <code>SchemaExport</code>
                            as the name of the project.</li>
                        <li>Make sure the Location field contains the name of the solution directory.
                            In this example, the location should be C:\TimeTracker.</li>
                        <li>Now click OK. A console application project will be created at
                            C:\TimeTracker\SchemaExport.</li>
                        <li>In Solution Explorer, right-click on the SchemaExport project and
                            select Add > New Item....</li>
                        <li>Select the template called Application Configuration File.</li>
                        <li>Make sure the Name field contains the name App.config and click Add.
                            A new App.config file will be added to the project.</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                    Now save the Visual Studio Solution by selecting File > Save All. Exit Visual Studio
                    by selecting File > Exit. At this point the preliminary set up of our Visual Studio solution
                    is complete.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Create Maven scripts for code generation">
                <p>
                    Let us turn our attention to the one-time setup required for code generation from
                    AndroMDA. This procedure will add Maven build scripts, an empty UML model and a Lib
                    directory to the TimeTracker solution. The Maven scripts will be used to generate code
                    from our UML model. So let's get started.
                    <ol>
                        <li>Open a Command Prompt and change directory to the parent directory of the
                            TimeTracker solution. In this example, that would be the C:\ directory.</li>
                        <li>Now execute the following command to generate Maven scripts in the
                            TimeTracker solution. Answer the questions exactly as shown in the output that follows.
                            You are allowed to enter your own name in response to the first question :-).
                            <p>
                                <code>maven andromdacsapp:generate</code>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <pre class="console">
 __  __
|  \/  |__ _Apache__ ___
| |\/| / _` \ V / -_) ' \  ~ intelligent projects ~
|_|  |_\__,_|\_/\___|_||_|  v. 1.0.2

Please enter your first and last name (e.g. Louis Coude):
Naresh Bhatia
Please enter the name of your C# application (e.g. Time Tracker):
Time Tracker
Please enter a version for your application (e.g. 1.0-SNAPSHOT):
1.0-SNAPSHOT
Would you like to create an ASP.NET web site? (enter 'yes' or 'no'):
no
build:start:

andromdacsapp:init:

andromdacsapp:generate:
    [echo] +------------------------------------------------------------------+
    [echo] |   G E N E R A T I N G   A n d r o M D A   C#   S O L U T I O N   |
    [echo] +------------------------------------------------------------------+
andromdacsapp:init:

andromdacsapp:generate-mda-project:
    [mkdir] Created dir: C:\TimeTracker\mda\src\uml
    [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\TimeTracker\mda\src\uml
    [zip] Building zip: C:\TimeTracker\mda\src\uml\TimeTrackerModel.xml.zip
    [delete] Deleting: C:\TimeTracker\mda\src\uml\TimeTrackerModel.xml
    [mkdir] Created dir: C:\TimeTracker\mda\conf
    [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\TimeTracker\mda

andromdacsapp:init:

andromdacsapp:generate-common-project:
andromdacsapp:generate-project:

    [mkdir] Created dir: C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerCommon\src
    [mkdir] Created dir: C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerCommon\target

andromdacsapp:init:

andromdacsapp:generate-core-project:
andromdacsapp:generate-project:

    [mkdir] Created dir: C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerCore\src
    [mkdir] Created dir: C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerCore\target

andromdacsapp:init:

andromdacsapp:generate-schema-export-project:
    [copy] Copying 2 files to C:\TimeTracker\SchemaExport

andromdacsapp:init:

andromdacsapp:generate-lib-directory:
    [mkdir] Created dir: C:\TimeTracker\Lib
    [copy] Copying 11 files to C:\TimeTracker\Lib

    [echo]
    [echo] ***  New C# solution generated in 'C:\\TimeTracker'  ***
    [echo]
BUILD SUCCESSFUL
Total time: 51 seconds
Finished at: Sat Nov 12 17:06:50 EST 2005
                </pre>

                <p>
                    Examine the various folders and files created by the <code>andromdacsapp</code> plugin. You
                    will notice files called <code>project.xml</code>, <code>maven.xml</code> and
                    <code>project.properties</code> at various levels in the TimeTracker solutions. These
                    files represent Maven projects, scripts and properties. You will also notice a <code>mda</code>
                    folder which contains an empty UML model under <code>mda\src\uml</code>. Finally you will see a
                    <code>Lib</code> folder containing dlls to be used by the generated code. Most dlls belong to
                    the <a href="http://wiki.nhibernate.org/display/NH/Home" target="_blank">NHibernate library</a>
                    which is used for object persistence. In addition you will find the following dlls:

                    <ul>
                        <li><code>NHibernate.Support.dll</code>: used to manage NHibernate sessions</li>
                        <li><code>NHibernate.Nullables2.dll</code>: used to store .NET 2.0 Nullable types using NHibernate</li>
                        <li><code>log4net.dll</code>: used for general purpose logging</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Create a database">
                <p>
                    Create a new database in your SQL Server instance using SQL Server Enterprise Manager
                    and name it TimeTracker. You may use an existing database, just be sure to replace the name
                    TimeTracker with the name of your database later in the tutorial.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <p>
                Congratulations! You have now completed the one-time setup for TimeTracker. We are now
                ready to start modeling!
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="First Iteration - Implement key TimeTracker classes">
            <p>
                In this section we will implement four key entities of the TimeTracker application - Person, Timecard,
                TimeAllocation and Task. In addition we will implement two supporting classes - TimecardStatus and
                Quantity. TimecardStatus is an enumeration and Quantity is an embedded value inside the Person entity.
                The diagram below shows these classes and their relationships.
            </p>

            <p>
                <div align="center">
                    <img src="images/TimeTrackerEntities.gif"/>
                </div>
            </p>

            <p>
                Note the level of detail in this diagram. Every detail has some meaning - none of the content is
                "fluff". For example we use stereotypes to indicate the "flavor" of each class - Entity vs.
                Enumeration vs. EmbeddedValue. Stereotypes tell AndroMDA the pattern of code to generate for
                each class. More specifically, stereotypes determine which AndroMDA templates get triggered
                to generate code. Similarly the various decorations you see on associations have very specific
                meanings. It is this level of preciseness that enables AndroMDA to generate major portions of
                your application - this is truly what Model Driven Architecture is! Here are some of the
                advantages of this approach:

                <ol>
                    <li>The model provides a common language for business users and developers.
                        It describe business requirements precisely and succinctly.</li>
                    <li>Developers can focus on implementing higher level business logic rather than doing
                        mundane tasks such as writing repetitive code to implement the data access layer.</li>
                    <li>Developers can be more responsive to changing business needs. Relatively large changes
                        to the business model can be handled more easily, because AndroMDA is there to help
                        you generate major portions of these changes.</li>
                    <li>The quality of your application will undoubtedly be superior because you are now
                        generating tested and proven patterns instead of writing one-of-a-kind code.
                        Possibility of human error is minimized. In addition, your focus will shift from
                        writing custom code for each situation to discovering commonalities and patterns that
                        can be coded into templates.</li>
                    <li>Models always represent the current state of the system, not just an outdated piece
                        of documentation. When you are done with your system, the model truly represents
                        the system "as-delivered" - there is no need to go back and retrofit the "documentation"
                        to match what was implemented. AndroMDA indeed makes the model a first-class system
                        artifact as is source code.</li>
                </ol>
            </p>

            <p>
                Now that you are fully bought into the idea of Model Driven Architecture :-), let's get started
                with the TimeTracker model shown above.
            </p>

            <subsection name="Create TimeTracker Model">
                <p>
                    As part of the setup procedure performed earlier, AndroMDA had created an empty UML model
                    in the TimeTracker solution. We will now start populating this model. Please follow one
                    of the links below to edit the TimeTracker model with the UML tool of your choice. (There
                    is only one choice at the time of this writing.)
                </p>
                
                <p>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/magicdraw/create-time-tracker-model.html" target="_blank">MagicDraw</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Generate code and build the application">
                <p> Follow the steps below to generate code.
                    <ol>
                        <li>Open a Command Prompt and change your directory to <code>C:\TimeTracker</code>.</li>
                        <li>Execute the command <code>maven</code> and boom, there you have it - code for all the
                            classes in your model is generated! (Make sure you get a <code>BUILD SUCCESSFUL</code>
                            message when the Maven script finishes execution.)</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                    Notice that code is generated in the following folders.
                    <ol>
                        <li><strong>C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerCommon\target\TimeTracker\Domain:</strong>
                            This folder contains only one file, <code>TimecardStatus.cs</code>, representing
                            the enumeration <code>TimecardStatus</code>.</li>
                        <li><strong>C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerCore\target\TimeTracker\Domain:</strong>
                            This folder contains the majority of generated files representing entities,
                            embedded values, data access objects and NHibernate mappings. In addition
                            it contains a file called <code>DaoFactory.cs</code> which is used to get
                            instances of the DAOs.</li>
                        <li><strong>C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerCore\src\TimeTracker\Domain:</strong>
                            This folder contains several files with <code>Impl</code> suffix. These files
                            are intended for modification by the developer.</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                    Note that code produced in <code>target</code> folders should never be modified by hand.
                    It will be deleted completely before regeneration in the next iteration. It is also
                    a best practice not to check this code into your source repository. Instead let your
                    build script generate this code on the fly. On the other hand, code generated in the
                    <code>src</code> directory is intended for modification by the developer. AndroMDA will
                    never overwrite code in these directories. It is generated one-time only.
                </p>

                <p>
                    Now that you understand the code that has been generated, it is time to compile it.
                    In order to avoid adding each individual file to our solution we will perform a neat
                    trick to make our job easier. We will edit the <code>TimeTrackerCommon</code> and
                    <code>TimeTrackerCore</code> projects so they will compile any C# file in a specified
                    folder. Follow the steps below to implement this trick.
                    <ol>
                        <li>Open <code>TimeTrackerCommon.csproj</code> in a text editor.</li>
                        <li>
                            Search for the following ItemGroup:
                            <source language="xml"><![CDATA[
<ItemGroup>
  <Compile Include="Properties\AssemblyInfo.cs" />
</ItemGroup>]]>
                            </source>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Modify the ItemGroup as follows to compile all C# files in the <code>target</code> directory:
                            <source language="xml"><![CDATA[
<ItemGroup>
  <Compile Include="Properties\AssemblyInfo.cs" />
  <Compile Include="target\TimeTracker\Domain\*.cs" />
</ItemGroup>]]>
                            </source>
                        </li>
                        <li>Save and close <code>TimeTrackerCommon.csproj</code>.</li>
                        <li>Open <code>TimeTrackerCore.csproj</code> in a text editor.</li>
                        <li>
                            Search for the following ItemGroup:
                            <source language="xml"><![CDATA[
<ItemGroup>
  <Compile Include="Properties\AssemblyInfo.cs" />
</ItemGroup>]]>
                            </source>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Modify the ItemGroup as follows to compile all C# files in the <code>src</code> and
                            <code>target</code> directories:
                            <source language="xml"><![CDATA[
<ItemGroup>
  <Compile Include="Properties\AssemblyInfo.cs" />
  <Compile Include="src\TimeTracker\Domain\*.cs" />
  <Compile Include="target\TimeTracker\Domain\*.cs" />
</ItemGroup>]]>
                            </source>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Add another ItemGroup right after the one above to embed the NHibernate mapping files
                            in the project:
                            <source language="xml"><![CDATA[
<ItemGroup>
  <EmbeddedResource Include="target\TimeTracker\Domain\*.hbm.xml" />
</ItemGroup>]]>
                            </source>
                        </li>
                        <li>Save and close <code>TimeTrackerCommon.csproj</code>.</li>
                        <li>Now open the TimeTracker solution in Visual Studio and notice that it shows the
                            C# files and NHibernate mappings added to the two projects.</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                    Let's implement the convenience methods added to the 3 classes in the diagram shown earlier.
                    <ol>
                        <li>Open the file <code>PersonImpl.cs</code> in the project <code>TimeTrackerCore</code>.
                            Implement <code>AddTimecard()</code> as follows:
                            <source language="java">
                                <![CDATA[
public override void AddTimecard(TimeTracker.Domain.Timecard timecard)
{
    Timecards.Add(timecard);
    timecard.Owner = this;
}]]>
                            </source>
                        </li>
                        <li>Open the file <code>TimecardImpl.cs</code> in the project <code>TimeTrackerCore</code>.
                            Implement <code>AddTimeAllocation()</code> as follows:
                            <source language="java">
                                <![CDATA[
public override void AddTimeAllocation(TimeTracker.Domain.TimeAllocation timeAllocation)
{
    Allocations.Add(timeAllocation);
    timeAllocation.Timecard = this;
}]]>
                            </source>
                        </li>
                        <li>Open the file <code>TaskImpl.cs</code> in the project <code>TimeTrackerCore</code>.
                            Implement <code>AddTimeAllocation()</code> as follows:
                            <source language="java">
                                <![CDATA[
public override void AddTimeAllocation(TimeTracker.Domain.TimeAllocation timeAllocation)
{
    Allocations.Add(timeAllocation);
    timeAllocation.Task = this;
}]]>
                            </source>
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                    Let us now add references to the various projects to reflect their dependencies. To add a reference,
                    simply right-click on the project in the Solution Explorer and select Add Reference. Then select
                    the Projects tab to add a reference to an internal project or select the Browse tab to add a
                    reference to an external DLL (for example, a DLL in the Lib directory).
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Add the following references to the <code>TimeTrackerCore</code> project:
                            <ol>
                                <li>TimeTrackerCommon project</li>
                                <li>Iesi.Collections.dll</li>
                                <li>log4net.dll</li>
                                <li>NHibernate.dll</li>
                                <li>NHibernate.Caches.SysCache.dll</li>
                                <li>NHibernate.Nullables2.dll</li>
                                <li>NHibernate.Support.dll</li>
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Add the following references to the <code>TimeTrackerConsole</code> project:
                            <ol>
                                <li>All references that are included above in the TimeTrackerCore project</li>
                                <li>TimeTrackerCore project</li>
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Add the following references to the <code>SchemaExport</code> project:
                            <ol>
                                <li>All references that are included above in the TimeTrackerCore project</li>
                                <li>TimeTrackerCore project</li>
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>

                <p>
                    We need to do one more thing before building the application. As part of the initial setup,
                    AndroMDA had generated the NHibernate configuration file for the SchemaExport application.
                    This file needs to be added to the SchemaExport project. Here are the steps to do this.
                    <ol>
                        <li>Right-click on the SchemaExport project in the Solution Explorer and select
                            Add > Existing Item.</li>
                        <li>In the Add Existing dialog, change the value for the drop down "Files of type"
                            to "All Files(*.*). Now the file called <code>nhibernate.config</code> will be visible in
                            the dialog. Select it and click Add. The file will be added to the project.</li>
                        <li>Select the file <code>nhibernate.config</code> in Solution Explorer.</li>
                        <li>In the Properties window, change the value of the field "Copy to output directory" to
                            "Copy if newer"</li>
                        <li>Open the <code>nhibernate.config</code> file in Visual Studio and change any values
                            if necessary. For example, if the name of your database is not TimeTracker, then change
                            the value of the <code>hibernate.connection.connection_string</code> property
                            accordingly.</li>
                        <li>Save the solution by selecting File > Save All.</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>

                <p>
                  At this point we are ready to build the solution. Select Build > Build Solution. Visual Studio
                  should be able to build the solution without any errors.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Create the database schema">
                <p>
                    It is now time to create the database schema for TimeTracker entities and relations.
                    Use the SchemaExport application generated by AndroMDA to do this. Here are the steps.
                    <ol>
                        <li>Open a Command Prompt and change your directory to
                            <code>C:\TimeTracker\SchemaExport\bin\Debug</code></li>
                        <li>Execute the command <code>SchemaExport t t</code>. This will create the
                            TimeTracker schema in the database.</li>
                    </ol>

                    The output from the execution of SchemaExport is shown below. Notice that you can
                    copy the DDL script from the output and use it in your own build scripts.

                    <pre class="console">
C:\TimeTracker\SchemaExport\bin\Debug>SchemaExport t t

Usage:
SchemaExport [script] [export]
script=t outputs DDL to the console
export=t exports schema to the database
Example:
SchemaExport t f

Calling CreateDatabase with script = True and export = True...

alter table TIMECARD  drop constraint TIMECARD_OWNER_FKC
Unsuccessful: Cannot alter table 'TIMECARD' because this table does not exist in database 'TestDB'.
alter table TIME_ALLOCATION  drop constraint TIME_ALLOCATION_TASK_FKC
Unsuccessful: Cannot alter table 'TIME_ALLOCATION' because this table does not exist in database 'TestDB'.
alter table TIME_ALLOCATION  drop constraint TIME_ALLOCATION_TIMECARD_FKC
Unsuccessful: Cannot alter table 'TIME_ALLOCATION' because this table does not exist in database 'TestDB'.
drop table TIMECARD
Unsuccessful: Cannot drop the table 'TIMECARD', because it does not exist in the system catalog.
drop table TASK
Unsuccessful: Cannot drop the table 'TASK', because it does not exist in the system catalog.
drop table PERSON
Unsuccessful: Cannot drop the table 'PERSON', because it does not exist in the system catalog.
drop table TIME_ALLOCATION
Unsuccessful: Cannot drop the table 'TIME_ALLOCATION', because it does not exist in the system catalog.
create table TIMECARD (
ID NUMERIC(19,0) IDENTITY NOT NULL,
STATUS INT not null,
BEG_DATE DATETIME not null,
OWNER_FK NUMERIC(19,0) not null,
primary key (ID)
)
create table TASK (
ID NUMERIC(19,0) IDENTITY NOT NULL,
NAME VARCHAR(255) not null,
primary key (ID)
)
create table PERSON (
ID NUMERIC(19,0) IDENTITY NOT NULL,
NAME VARCHAR(255) not null,
RATE_VALUE FLOAT not null,
RATE_UNIT VARCHAR(255) not null,
primary key (ID)
)
create table TIME_ALLOCATION (
ID NUMERIC(19,0) IDENTITY NOT NULL,
BEG_TIME DATETIME not null,
END_TIME DATETIME not null,
TIMECARD_FK NUMERIC(19,0) not null,
TASK_FK NUMERIC(19,0) not null,
primary key (ID)
)
alter table TIMECARD  add constraint TIMECARD_OWNER_FKC foreign key (OWNER_FK) references PERSON
alter table TIME_ALLOCATION  add constraint TIME_ALLOCATION_TASK_FKC foreign key (TASK_FK) references TASK
alter table TIME_ALLOCATION  add constraint TIME_ALLOCATION_TIMECARD_FKC foreign key (TIMECARD_FK) references TIMECARD
                    </pre>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Build and test the TimeTrackerConsole application">
                <p>
                    It is now time to test all the functionality we have implemented so far using the
                    <code>TimeTrackerConsole</code> application. Follow the steps below to do this.
                    <ol>
                        <li>Instead of writing the entire console program from scratch we will copy it
                            from the <code>samples</code> folder in the <code>contrib</code> module.
                            So go to Windows Explorer and copy the file <code>Program.cs</code> under
                            <code>contrib\samples\time-tracker-dotnet\TimeTrackerConsole</code> to the
                            folder <code>C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerConsole</code>
                            (overwriting the original file).</li>
                        <li>Review the Program.cs file to understand how the DAO classes are used to
                            manipulate entities. Specifically look at the methods <code>AddPerson()</code>,
                            <code>AddTask()</code>, <code>AddTimecard()</code> and <code>ShowData()</code>.</li>
                        <li>Now copy the two files <code>App.config</code> and <code>nhibernate.config</code>
                            from the directory <code>C:\TimeTracker\SchemaExport</code> to
                            <code>C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerConsole</code>. This will configure the application
                            to work with NHibernate.</li>
                        <li>Right-click on the TimeTrackerConsole project in the Solution Explorer and select
                            Add > Existing Item.</li>
                        <li>In the Add Existing dialog, change the value for the drop down "Files of type"
                            to "All Files(*.*). Now the file called <code>nhibernate.config</code> will be visible in
                            the dialog. Select it and click Add. The file will be added to the project.</li>
                        <li>Select the file <code>nhibernate.config</code> in Solution Explorer.</li>
                        <li>In the Properties window, change the value of the field "Copy to output directory" to
                            "Copy if newer"</li>
                        <li>Save the solution by selecting File > Save All.</li>
                        <li>Select Build > Rebuild Solution. Visual Studio should be able to build the solution
                            without any errors.</li>
                        <li>Open a Command Prompt and change your directory to
                            <code>C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerConsole\bin\Debug</code></li>
                        <li>Execute the command <code>TimeTrackerConsole</code>. This will display menu.</li>
                        <li>Select various menu items to add people, tasks and timecards to the database.</li>
                    </ol>

                    A sample run of  TimeTrackerConsole is shown below.

                    <pre class="console">
C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerConsole\bin\Debug>TimeTrackerConsole

1. Create Database
2. Add Person
3. Add Task
4. Add Timecard
5. Update Timecard
6. Delete Timecard
7. Show Data

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): 2

Person Name: Naresh Bhatia
Naresh Bhatia added.

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): 2

Person Name: Louis Coude
Louis Coude added.

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): 3

Task Name: Research
Task 1 added: Research

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): 3

Task Name: Development
Task 2 added: Development

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): 4

Adding timecard...
Timecard 1 created with 1 allocations

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): 4

Adding timecard...
Timecard 2 created with 2 allocations

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): 4

Adding timecard...
Timecard 3 created with 2 allocations

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): 4

Adding timecard...
Timecard 4 created with 2 allocations

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): 7

People:
1: Naresh Bhatia, rate=10 USD/hour
2: Louis Coude, rate=10 USD/hour

Tasks:
1: Research
2: Development

Timecards:
1: Naresh Bhatia, Draft, 11/16/2005 5:58:29 PM
    1: 11/16/2005 5:58:29 PM, 11/16/2005 6:58:29 PM, Research
2: Naresh Bhatia, Draft, 11/16/2005 5:58:31 PM
    2: 11/16/2005 5:58:31 PM, 11/16/2005 6:58:31 PM, Research
    3: 11/16/2005 6:58:31 PM, 11/16/2005 7:58:31 PM, Development
3: Louis Coude, Draft, 11/16/2005 5:58:32 PM
    4: 11/16/2005 5:58:32 PM, 11/16/2005 6:58:32 PM, Research
    5: 11/16/2005 6:58:32 PM, 11/16/2005 7:58:32 PM, Research
4: Louis Coude, Draft, 11/16/2005 5:58:33 PM
    6: 11/16/2005 5:58:33 PM, 11/16/2005 6:58:33 PM, Research
    7: 11/16/2005 6:58:33 PM, 11/16/2005 7:58:33 PM, Research

Please make a choice ([h]elp [q]uit): q

C:\TimeTracker\TimeTrackerConsole\bin\Debug>
                    </pre>
                </p>
            </subsection>

        </section>

        <section name="Where to go from here ?">
            <p>
                In this tutorial we have shown you how to set up your development environment and
                build your first .NET application using AndroMDA. But this is just the beginning.
                You can now use AndroMDA to build your own applications. Try out the various features
                documented under each .NET cartridge. If you don't find a feature that you need,
                write yourself a template or an entire cartridge. If you think your work might be
                useful to other developers, don't forget to contribute it to the AndroMDA project.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>