<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="naresh@andromda.org">Naresh Bhatia</author>
        <title>Create Associations</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Create Associations">
            <p>
                In this section we will learn how to create associations between entities. We will
                start out by modeling a <code>Timecard</code> entity and then creating two
                associations between <code>Timecard</code> and <code>Person</code>. The completed
                model will be as shown below.
            </p>

            <p>
                <div align="center">
                    <img src="images/magicdraw/TimecardEntity.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>

            <p>
                The <code>Timecard</code> has three attributes:
                <ol>
                    <li><strong>status:</strong> an enumeration with 4 values as shown</li>
                    <li><strong>begDate:</strong> the beginning date of the timecard, which should fall at the start of a week</li>
                    <li><strong>comments:</strong> comments added by the submitter and/or the approver of the timecard</li>
                </ol>
            </p>

            <p>
                The <code>Timecard</code> has two associations with <code>Person</code>:
                <ol>
                    <li><strong>submitter:</strong> the person who has submitted the timecard</li>
                    <li><strong>approver:</strong> the person who will approve the timecard</li>
                </ol>
            </p>

            <p>
                The arrows on the two associations indicate that both associations are navigable from
                <code>Timecard</code> to <code>Person</code>, i.e. the timecard keeps references to its
                submitter and approver. Note that two-way navigability is indicated by not having arrows
                at either end of the association. The "1" and "*" at each end of the association indicate
                their multiplicity. The top association means one person can submit many (indicated by "*")
                timecards. Similarly the bottom association means one person can approve many timecards.
            </p>

            <p>
                We are now ready to add these additional elements to our TimeTracker model. To do this,
                click the link below for your UML modeling tool.
            </p>

            <p>
                <a href="resources/uml-tools/argouml/create-timecard-entity.html" target="_blank">ArgoUML</a>
                <a href="resources/uml-tools/magicdraw/create-timecard-entity.html" target="_blank">MagicDraw</a>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Generate Code">
            <p> Follow the steps below to generate code.
                <ol>
                    <li>Open a Command Prompt and change your directory to <code>C:/timetracker</code>.</li>
                    <li>Execute the command <code>maven -o clean install</code>. Make sure you get a
                    <code>BUILD SUCCESSFUL</code> message.</li>
                </ol>
            </p>

            <p>
                Open the folder C:/timetracker/core/target/src/org/andromda/timetracker/domain in Windows Explorer.
                You will see 7 new files in there all related to the timecard entity. Review these files. Note that
                the <code>Timecard</code> class contains two references to the <code>Person</code> class, but the
                <code>Person</code> class contains no references to the <code>Timecard</code> class. This is because
                both associations between these classes are one-way from <code>Timecard</code> to <code>Person</code>.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="What's Next?">
            <p>
                At this point we have covered most of the important modeling concepts. In the next section we
                will add the remaining functionality to the TimeTracker model. Click <a href="complete-timetracker-model.html">here</a>
                to get started.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
