<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="mbohlen@mbohlen.de">Matthias Bohlen</author>
    <title>AndroMDA - Homepage</title>
    <gennews>no</gennews>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <freetext name="Section 1">
      <h1>Components quickly with AndroMDA</h1>

      <p class="std">
        Did you ever think: "mmm... all this J2EE stuff is too complex! There must
        be an easier way to program?" Read the good news: AndroMDA is here to help
        you! Generating J2EE components quickly and reliably from models drawn in the
        graphical Unified Modeling Language is the main feature of AndroMDA.
      </p>

      <p class="std">
        AndroMDA (pronounced: andromeda) is an open source code generation framework
        that follows the <a href="http://www.omg.org/mda">model driven architecture</a>
        (MDA) paradigm. It takes a UML model from a CASE-tool and generates
        classes and deployable components (J2EE or other), specific for your
        application architecture.
      </p>

      <p class="std">
        This project is the successor of the <a href="http://uml2ejb.sourceforge.net">
        UML2EJB</a> project which started in July 2002 and generates Enterprise
        JavaBeans from UML models. Meanwhile, the scope has broadened, the number of
        developers has increased and so we decided to rename our project. AndroMDA
        will reuse the code base of
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=57059&amp;release_id=129056">
            UML2EJB 1.3.x
        </a>
        which is rock solid.
      </p>

      <p class="std">Currently, we are...</p>
      <ul>
        <li class="std">migrating the source files to the new CVS repository</li>
        <li class="std">changing our base to <a href="http://mdr.netbeans.org/">Netbeans metadata
          repository</a> (MDR), an implementation of the OMG <a href="http://www.dstc.edu.au/Research/Projects/MOF/">MOF</a>
          standard</li>
        <li class="std">restructuring packages and classes</li>
        <li class="std">adding support for non-EJB persistence like JDO or Hibernate</li>
        <li class="std">adding support for more CASE tools (MagicDraw, Together CC, etc.)</li>
        <li class="std">rewriting the web pages</li>
      </ul>

      <p class="std">
        Please be patient, migrating the whole stuff into a new project takes more
        time than we thought. So, stay tuned, you will see much more here in the
        near future. AndroMDA will be as beautiful as the galaxy, promised!
      </p>

      <p class="std">
        Read more about AndroMDA, using the links on the left side menu. If you start
        using AndroMDA, we invite you to subscribe to the project's
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=73047">mailing lists</a>. Another
        intersting place to watch is the Code Generation Network site where
        you can read an
        <a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/tiki-read_article.php?articleId=8">interview with Matthias Bohlen</a>, the lead engineer
        behind AndroMDA.
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        <div align="center">
          <img src="images/andromda.jpg" width="508" height="421" align="middle" alt=""/>
        </div>
      </p>

    </freetext>

  </body>
</document>
