<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>
            Create Search Timecards Use Case
        </title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Create Search Timecards Use Case">

            <p>
                This page provides directions to create the
                <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                use case
                along with its state machine diagram and the <tt>SearchController</tt>. Note that all three elements
                mentioned here will be placed in the package <tt>org.andromda.timetracker.web.timecardsearch</tt>.
            </p>

            <p>
                Let's start by creating the
                <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                use case.
            </p>

            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Create a package under the
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model by right-clicking on it
                    in the containment tree and selecting New Element &gt; Package. Name this new package
                    <tt>Use Cases</tt>
                    because we will create our use case diagrams here.
                </li>
                <li>In the
                    <tt>Use Cases</tt>
                    package, create a use case diagram by right clicking
                    on it and selecting New Diagram &gt; Use Case Diagram. Type in the name
                    <tt>Application Use Cases</tt>
                    for this diagram and press Enter
                </li>
                <li>In the toolbar on the left of the use case diagram click on the Use Case icon (2nd
                    icon from Use Case Diagram group). Now click anywhere inside the diagram.
                    A new use case will be created. Type the phrase &quot;Search Timecards&quot; to name the use case.
                    Note that the use case is created under the
                    <tt>Use Cases</tt>
                    package in the containment tree.
                    This is not the final location of the use case, but we will move later to the correct
                    location.
                </li>
                <li>Right click on the use case and give it two stereotypes as discussed earlier:
                    <tt>
                        FrontEndUseCase
                    </tt>
                    and <tt>FrontEndApplication</tt>.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                Now lets create the package
                <tt>org.andromda.timetracker.web.timecardsearch</tt>
                which is the final destination of our front-end elements.
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Create a package called
                    <tt>web</tt>
                    under <tt>org.andromda.timetracker</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Create a package called
                    <tt>timecardsearch</tt>
                    under <tt>web</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Drag the
                    <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                    use case under the
                    <tt>timecardsearch</tt>
                    package.
                </li>
                <li>Right-click on the
                    <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                    use case and choose
                    <i>New Diagram
                        &gt; State Diagram
                    </i>
                    to create an state diagram. Name it <tt>Search Timecards State Machine Diagram</tt>.
                    This action automatically creates a state machine in the
                    <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                    use case
                    and associates the create state diagram to the state machine.
                </li>
                <li>Rename the state machine by selecting it and pressing F2. Type in
                    <tt>Search Timecards State Machine</tt>
                </li>
                <li>Now create a class called
                    <tt>SearchController</tt>
                    under the
                    <tt>Search Timecards State Machine</tt>
                    state machine. Do this by right-clicking on <tt>Search Timecards State Machine</tt>, choose
                    <i>New Element
                        &gt; Class</i>.
                </li>
            </ol>

            <p>
                We are done with the basic structure for the web page. Now let's create the page
                flow on the <tt>Search Timecards State Machine Diagram</tt>. Open this diagram and
                follow the steps below. Use the tool bar on the left to create various elements
                on the diagram. Use the tool tips and the status bar to identify the tool bar icons.
            </p>

            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Create an Initial State at the top.</li>
                <li>Drop a state below it. Type
                    <tt>Populate Search Screen</tt>
                    as the name for this state.
                </li>
                <li>Create a transition from the initial state to the
                    <tt>Populate Search Screen</tt>
                    state.
                </li>
                <li>Drop another action state below <tt>Populate Search Screen</tt>. Name it <tt>Search Timecards</tt>.
                    Since this state represents a screen, give it the stereotype of <tt>FrontEndView</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Create a transition from
                    <tt>Populate Search Screen</tt>
                    to
                    <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                    and another in the reverse direction. In other words, the use case simply switches
                    between the two states - of course, most of the time it stays in the
                    <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                    state, waiting for user input.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Right click on the transition out of
                    <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                    and open its
                    specification.
                </li>
                <li>Find the sub-panel
                    <i>Effect</i>
                </li>
                <li>Specify
                    <tt>Activity</tt>
                    as the type of behavior of the effect.
                </li>
                <li>Enter the word
                    <tt>search</tt>
                    in the name field and click<i>OK</i>.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                The effect modeled on the transition out of
                <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                will make
                AndroMDA render a form in the Search Criteria panel. This form will submit 5 parameters to server: submitter, approver,
                status, start date minimum and start date maximum. Follow the steps below to specify these parameters.
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Right click on the
                    <tt>search</tt>
                    activity and open its specification.
                </li>
                <li>Click on the Parameters tab.</li>
                <li>
                    Click
                    <i>Create</i>
                    to add the first parameter. The Parameter Specification dialog
                    comes up. Enter
                    <tt>submitter</tt>
                    as the name of the parameter and
                    <tt>Long</tt>
                    as its type (note that it is <tt>Long</tt>, not <tt>long</tt>). Now click
                    on the
                    <i>Tag Values</i>
                    tab and click on the tagged value named <tt>@andromda.presentation.web.view.field.type</tt>.
                    This tagged value tells AndroMDA what type of field
                    <tt>submitter</tt>
                    is. Since
                    submitter is a drop-down box, i.e. selection, we need to set the value of this tag
                    to <tt>select</tt>. To do this, click the
                    <i>Add Value</i>
                    button. The
                    value is shown in the right panel and is already set to <tt>select</tt>. So
                    just click<i>Back</i>.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Add the second parameter called
                    <tt>approver</tt>
                    with type of <tt>Long</tt>.
                    Again set the tagged value
                    <tt>@andromda.presentation.web.view.field.type</tt>
                    to <tt>select</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Add the third parameter called
                    <tt>status</tt>
                    with type of <tt>String</tt>.
                    Again set the tagged value
                    <tt>@andromda.presentation.web.view.field.type</tt>
                    to <tt>select</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Add the fourth parameter called
                    <tt>startDateMinimum</tt>
                    with type of <tt>
                    Date</tt>. This time set the tagged value
                    <tt>@andromda.presentation.web.view.field.calendar</tt>
                    to <tt>true</tt>. This will make sure that you will get a text field for the
                    date along with a calendar widget on its side.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Add the fifth parameter called
                    <tt>startDateMaximum</tt>
                    with type of <tt>
                    Date</tt>. Again set the tagged value
                    <tt>@andromda.presentation.web.view.field.calendar</tt>
                    to <tt>true</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Click
                    <i>Close</i>
                    to dismiss the dialog box.
                </li>
            </ol>
            
            <p>
                We are now almost done with our activity diagram except for one thing. The state machine
                still has to call the
                <tt>SearchController</tt>
                to populate the submitter
                and approver drop-downs. To do this we will first specify a method on
                <tt>SearchController</tt>
                called <tt>populateSearchScreen()</tt>. Follow the steps below to add this method:
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>In the containment tree, right-click on
                    <tt>SearchController</tt>
                    and select
                    <i>New &gt; Operation</i>.
                </li>
                <li>Enter
                    <tt>populateSearchScreen</tt>
                    as the name of the operation.
                </li>
                <li>Double click on the operation to open the Operation Specification dialog.</li>
                <li>Specify the return type as <tt>void</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Click on the Parameters tab.</li>
                <li>Add the same 5 parameters that you added to the effect above - the names and types
                    should match exactly. But don't add the tag values.
                    That's how AndroMDA knows how to call the controller method.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Tips &amp; Tricks</b>: You can simply copy the five parameters from
                    <tt>search</tt>
                    activity
                    to the
                    <tt>populateSearchScreen</tt>
                    operation. To do this:
                    <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                        <li>
                            In the containment tree, select the five parameters in the
                            <tt>search</tt>
                            activity. Copy them (<i>Ctrl + C</i>).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Select the
                            <tt>populateSearchScreen</tt>
                            operation and
                            paste the parameters (<i>Ctrl + V</i>).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Right click on each pasted parameter,<i>Edit Stereotype</i>,
                            <i>Clear All</i>
                            and finally<i>Apply</i>. This will remove their stereotype thus their tag value.
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </li>
                <li>Click
                    <i>Close</i>
                    to close the dialog.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                Now that we have an appropriate controller method, let's call it from the state machine
                diagram.
            </p>

            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Right-click on the
                    <tt>Populate Search Screen</tt>
                    state and open its
                    specification.
                </li>
                <li>Find the sub-panel
                    <i>Entry</i>
                </li>
                <li>Specify
                    <tt>Activity</tt>
                    as the type of behavior of the entry.
                </li>
                <li>Right click on the activity and open its specification.</li>
                <li>Click on the
                    <tt>Node</tt>
                    editing area. A + and a - symbol will appear. Click on the +.
                    Select Call Operation Action
                </li>
                <li>Name the action
                    <tt>Call populateSearchScreen()</tt>
                </li>
                <li>By clicking on ... in the operation field, a dialog box will appear. Select the
                    <tt>populateSearchScreen()</tt>
                    method and click<i>OK</i>.
                </li>
                <li>Click
                    <i>Close</i>
                    to dismiss the dialog box.
                </li>
            </ol>

            <p>
                There is just one more thing left. The
                <tt>SearchController</tt>
                needs to be
                able to call the service layer to get the list of users. To add this capability,
                we need to create a dependency from the
                <tt>SearchController</tt>
                to the <tt>UserService</tt>.
            </p>

            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Open the
                    <tt>Services</tt>
                    diagram in the
                    <tt>service</tt>
                    package.
                </li>
                <li>From the Containment Tree on the left, drag the
                    <tt>SearchController</tt>
                    class
                    on to the diagram.
                </li>
                <li>Draw a dependency from
                    <tt>SearchController</tt>
                    to <tt>UserService</tt>.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                We have now completely modeled the Search Criteria panel. Save your model, and export it,
                as usual.
            </p>
            <p>
                Please go back to the main tutorial page and continue from where you left off.
            </p>

        </section>
    </body>
</document>
