<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>
            Create User Entity
        </title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Create User Entity">

            <p>
                This page provides directions to create the
                <tt>User</tt>
                entity using MagicDraw 15.5.
            </p>

            <p>
                We will create
                <tt>User</tt>
                in a package named <tt>org.andromda.timetracker.domain</tt>.
            </p>

            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>In the TimeTracker model create a package called
                    <tt>domain</tt>
                    under <tt>
                        org.andromda.timetracker</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>In the Containment Tree on the left, right-click on the
                    <tt>domain</tt>
                    package
                    and select<i>New Diagram &gt; Class Diagram</i>. The diagram is created and opened in a new window.
                    Type in
                    <tt>Domain Objects</tt>
                    as the name of this diagram and press Enter.
                </li>
                <li>Add a new class to the diagram and name it <tt>User</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Add the stereotype called
                    <tt>Entity</tt>
                    (The one from AndroMDA Profile, starting with an 'E' and
                    not the one from UML2 Standard Profile, starting with an 'e') to <tt>User</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Add the 3 attributes to <tt>User</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Double click on the class to open the class specification.</li>
                <li>Click on the
                    <i>Tagged Values</i>
                    tab and then click on the tagged value named
                    <tt>@andromda.persistence.table</tt>. This tagged value allows you to override
                    the default table name for the entity. Click the
                    <i>Add Value</i>
                    button. Enter
                    the value
                    <tt>USERS</tt>
                    in the right panel. Click
                    <i>OK</i>
                    to add this tagged value
                    to the
                    <tt>User</tt>
                    entity.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Note</b>: In our UML2 profile, each tag value has it own stereotype. Having such a stereotype
                    applied on an element will make AndroMDA consider this element tagged by the corresponding tag value.
                    If there is no specified value (but the stereotype is applied) AndroMDA will use the default value, defined
                    in the profile. Keep this in mind, when removing a tag value: unapply the stereotype as well.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Note that the tagged value shows up in the diagram and its owning stereotype
                    <tt>@andromda.persistence.table</tt>.
                    You can make MagicDraw 15.5 hide the tagged values, but you can't select which stereotypes
                    you want to be displayed. If you want to hide the tag value, right-click
                    on the entity and choose<i>Presentation Options</i>, then deselect<i>Show Tagged
                    Values</i>. You may want to hide stereotypes as well:
                    <tt>Entity</tt>
                    stereotype has an icon
                    which will remain displayed.
                </li>
                <li>Make sure your class diagram matches the one shown on the right (depending on the choice you made just before).</li>
                <li>Make sure that the MagicDraw containment tree matches the screen shot shown below.</li>
                <li>Save your
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model by selecting<i>File &gt; Save Project</i>.
                </li>
                <li>Export it in EMF/UML2 format by selecting<i>File &gt; Export &gt; EMF UML2 XMI</i>.
                    Choose
                    <tt>C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/uml</tt>
                    as export directory and click<i>Open</i>.
                </li>
            </ol>

            <p>
                Now go back to the main tutorial page and continue from where you left off.
            </p>

        </section>
    </body>
</document>
