<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>
            Create UserVO
        </title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Create UserVO">

            <p>
                This page provides directions to create the <tt>UserVO</tt>.
            </p>

            <p>
                Let's take a look at the initial content of the freshly generated model.
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Start MagicDraw 15.5.</li>
                <li>Select
                    <i>File &gt; Open Project...</i>
                    and traverse to <tt>C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/uml/timetracker.xml</tt>.
                    Click
                    <i>Open</i>
                    to open this model.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                On the left of the window, there is the containment tree. It displays the objects
                that make, together, the model. AndroMDA sees the model like it is displayed here (and not
                through the several diagrams). By making sure that the content of your model is matching the pictures
                shown during this tutorial, you'll avoid a lot of errors.
            </p>
            <p>
                As you can see, the model is not empty. Some of work has already be done for you. Let's review the initial
                content of the model.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <tt>UML standard profile</tt>: This module contains (as its name says) the standard profile
                    from UML2. In previous AndroMDApp generated models, this module was removed. For UML2 models,
                    it is necessary because it define the metaclasses where stereotypes are applied.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <tt>datatype</tt>: This package contains some platform independent datatypes
                    that have be used in your UML model. AndroMDA will map then to platform specific datatypes.
                    <i>Important</i>: A common source of errors is to use UML's datatypes instead of these.
                    When specifying datatypes, make sure that they come from this package. Example: use
                    <tt>datatype::String</tt>
                    instead of <tt>String</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <tt>org.andromda.profile</tt>: This collection of profiles define all the stereotypes and
                    tag values that will be used by AndroMDA for generating code.
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                Note: all this content is not
                <i>included</i>
                in the xml file. It's only
                <i>references</i>
                to
                files located into your maven 2 repository.
            </p>
            <p>
                MagicDraw has the concept of a hierarchy of models. Each model in the hierarchy can be broken
                out and stored as a separate file. This allows multiple developers to work on different
                parts of a master model. Let's create a new model for TimeTracker.
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>In the Containment Tree on the left, right-click on the root element called Data
                    and select<i>New Element &gt; Model</i>. A new model will be created under the root element
                    with an edit box to its side. Type in
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    as the name of this model.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                As said previously, AndroMDA can't read MagicDraw MagicDraw 15.5 models directly. You have to export it
                to another file format: EMF-UML2.
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Save your
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model by selecting<i>File &gt; Save Project</i>.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Select<i>File &gt; Export &gt; EMF UML2 XMI</i>. Choose
                    <tt>C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/uml</tt>
                    as export directory and click<i>Open</i>.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                If you want to see the result of this export, open the folder
                <tt>C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/uml</tt>
                in explorer.
                Let's look closer at its content.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li> <tt>timetracker.xml</tt>: the MagicDraw 15.5 model file.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <tt>timetracker.uml</tt>: the <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model in EMF/UML2 format. It's the file that will be processed by AndroMDA.
                </li>
                <li>10 files ending with <tt>.profile.uml</tt>: the different profiles used by
                    <tt>timetracker.uml</tt>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                As you can see, all modules on which your model depends are present in this directory. This explained why the
                <tt>moduleSearchPath</tt> section in <tt>andromda.xml</tt> is empty.
            </p>
            <p>
                If you have installed the
                <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/uml2">uml2 plugin</a>
                for Eclipse, you can open
                <i>timetracker.uml</i>
                to look at its content. You'll see almost the same objects than those in containment tree.
            </p>
            <blockquote>
                <b>Important</b>: Always use the
                <i>timetracker.xml</i>
                file for editing. After edition, don't forget to export the model
                to EMF/UML2. AndroMDA won't take your changes into account if you don't export your model.
            </blockquote>
            <p>
                Let's start the 'real' work. We will create
                <tt>UserVO</tt>
                and
                <tt>UserVO[]</tt>
                in a package named
                <tt>org.andromda.timetracker.vo</tt>. When finished, the containment tree in
                MagicDraw will look like the screen shot on the bottom of this page.
            </p>

            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Now right-click on the timetracker model you just created and select New Element
                    &gt; Package. A new package will be created under the
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model element with
                    an edit box to its side. Type in
                    <tt>org.andromda.timetracker</tt>
                    as the name
                    of the package. AndroMDA will map this package to a Java package with the same name.
                    Note: Make sure the package name is exactly <tt>org.andromda.timetracker</tt>,
                    with no leading or trailing spaces. We have found that some browsers introduce a
                    leading space in the package name if you copy it from this page!
                </li>
                <li>Now create a package called
                    <tt>vo</tt>
                    under <tt>org.andromda.timetracker</tt>.
                    We will create our value objects in this package. Note that AndroMDA does not require
                    this package structure. We are doing it simply to separate our value objects from
                    other type of objects such as business entities, services etc.
                </li>
                <li>In the Containment Tree on the left, right-click on the
                    <tt>vo</tt>
                    package
                    and select<i>New Diagram &gt; Class Diagram</i>. The diagram is created and opened in a new window.
                    You can see that the diagram's name is being edited. Type in
                    <tt>Value Objects</tt>
                    as the name of
                    this diagram and press Enter.
                </li>
                <li>In the toolbar on the left of the class diagram click on the
                    <i>Class icon</i>
                    (1st icon
                    from the class diagram group). Now click anywhere inside the diagram. A new class will be created.
                    The class will be automatically selected as indicated by the 4 knobs around it.
                    (If you somehow deselected the class, then select it again by clicking on it.) Now
                    type the word <tt>UserVO</tt>. This word will be entered as the name of the class.
                </li>
                <li>Let's add some documentation for the
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class. It is always a good
                    idea to document your model. Documentation added to model elements such as classes,
                    attributes and methods is carried over to the code as comments. Double-click on
                    the
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class to bring up the Class Specification dialog. Add the
                    following sentence in the Documentation field and click<i>OK</i>:
                    <tt>This class represents
                        a value object that carries information about a TimeTracker user.
                    </tt>
                </li>
                <li>Now add the stereotype
                    <tt>ValueObject</tt>
                    to class <tt>UserVO</tt>. To
                    do this, right-click on the class and select<i>Stereotype</i>. In the next level menu,
                    check
                    <tt>ValueObject</tt>
                    and click<i>Apply</i>. The
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class will now have the
                    <tt>ValueObject</tt>
                    stereotype.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Tips &amp; Tricks</b>: AndroMDA profiles define a lot of profiles. On the widget displaying
                    all available stereotypes, start to type the name of the searched Stereotype. By typing <tt>Va</tt>,
                    only
                    <tt>ValueObject</tt>
                    is displayed.
                </li>
                <li>Let's add
                    <tt>id</tt>
                    as an attribute of <tt>UserVO</tt>. Right-click on the
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class and select<i>Insert New Attribute</i>. A new attribute is inserted with the
                    specification <tt>-unnamed1</tt>. Write over this specification with this new one:
                    <tt>+id
                        : Long
                    </tt>
                    (be sure to delete the minus sign in front of the name). Do not press Enter
                    after typing this attribute (that will create another attribute). Instead click
                    outside the class to finish entering the attribute. Note that attributes are always
                    generated as private members of a class. However the visibilities of the associated
                    getter and setter are determined by the visibility of the attribute specification.
                    In this case we have specified public visibility (by using the plus sign) and hence
                    the getter and setter for the
                    <tt>id</tt>
                    attribute will be public.
                    <blockquote>
                        <b>Tips &amp; Tricks</b>: MagicDraw 15.5 provides an auto completion feature for choosing an element type.
                        To use it, simply type in
                        <tt>+id:L</tt>
                        and press<i>ctrl + space</i>.
                        MagicDraw 15.5 will then show you different possible completions: choose <tt>Long</tt>.
                    </blockquote>
                </li>
                <li>Now add three more public attributes called <tt>username</tt>,
                    <tt>firstName</tt>
                    and
                    <tt>lastName</tt>
                    to the
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class. Make them
                    <tt>String</tt>
                    type. In your model two different types called String are available (see above).
                    Use the one displayed <tt>String [datatype]</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Add a new class to the diagram and name it <tt>UserVO[]</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Make sure your class diagram matches the one shown on the right exactly. (It is okay if
                    your class shows an empty operation compartment. This can be hidden very easily).
                </li>
                <li>Make sure that the MagicDraw containment tree matches the screen shot shown below.</li>
                <li>
                    <b>Tips &amp; Tricks</b>: MagicDraw MagicDraw 15.5 displays objects that have changed since
                    the last save in blue.
                </li>
                <li>Save your
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model by selecting<i>File &gt; Save Project</i>.
                </li>
                <li>Export it in EMF/UML2 format by selecting<i>File &gt; Export &gt; EMF UML2 XMI</i>.
                    Choose
                    <tt>C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/uml</tt>
                    as export directory and click<i>Open</i>.
                </li>
            </ol>

            <p>
                Congratulations! You have now specified the
                <tt>UserVO</tt>
                value object of
                the
                <tt>TimeTracker</tt>
                application. We are now ready to generate some code.
                Please go back to the main tutorial page and continue from where you left off.
            </p>

        </section>
    </body>
</document>
