<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="wouter@andromda.org">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Bpm4Struts - HowTo - Calling Back-End Services</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Calling Back-End Services">
            <p>
                It is possible to connect the presentation layer to the service (application) layer, if you
                are modeling your application's back-end with one of the other cartridges, and you're modeling
                services using the <![CDATA[<<Service>>]]> stereotype you will simply need to model a dependency
                from the <a href="howto3.html">controller class</a> to the service class.
            </p>
            <p>
                You can have dependencies to as many services as you like, for each one of the them an accessor
                will be generated.
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                Because of the strict separation between the three enterprise tiers it would not be a good idea
                to make the bpm4struts cartridge aware of how to call the actual service instances in the
                back-end tier, since this
                is most likely different on different platforms (Spring, EJB, ...). For this reason we have
                introduced a <a href="namespace.html">namespace</a> property called
                <a href="namespace.html#serviceAccessorPattern">serviceAccessorPattern</a>.
                It allows you to specify how calls to the back end ought to be rendered, if you have generated the
                project structure using the
                <a href="../../starting.html#My_first_AndroMDA_project">andromdapp:generate</a> Maven plugin you should
                not need to change this property.
            </p>
            <p>
                One could argue why not calling service operations directly from the activity graph, here are a few
                reasons:
                <ol>
                    <li>Activity graphs can have only one context at a time, so your deferred calls would
                        be limited to a single service
                    </li>
                    <li>Operation signatures do not always perfectly map, parameter names and types might be different;
                        generally speaking it is good practice to have an intermediate layer in which you
                        can handle these differences.
                    </li>
                    <li>Often you will not want to directly expose exceptions from the back-end to your presentation
                        layer, this can also be handled in the controller.
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="howto/org/andromda/test/back-end.gif"/>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                Next section: <a href="howto8.html">Tables</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
