<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="wouter@andromda.org">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Bpm4Struts - Tips</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Tips for using AndroMDA bpm4struts">
            <p>
                This section provides you with some pointers that might prove helpful when using AndroMDA with
                the bpm4struts cartridge.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Naming Conventions">
            <p>
                Give good names to all the elements you model, try to give names that uniquely identify the element
                in its context. For example, instead of calling an action state 'login' you might consider
                using 'enter name and password' instead. The same goes for controllers and use-cases. The better
                names you give, the less ambiguity you will have in the long run.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Code Regeneration">
            <p>
                The power of AndroMDA is apparent when you will need to apply changes to your model and regenerate
                the set of code files. Using bpm4struts these files comprise Java classes as well as properties
                files and JSPs.
            </p>
            <p>
                You will not want to lose your changes to the generated code, to ensure this the cartridges have
                been designed never to overwrite the implementation classes and files. On the other hand you will
                most probably want to see the most recent changes in the model reflected in the code.
            </p>
            <p>
                For classes this is not a problem because the cartridges generating them will provide you with
                an implementation class that will only be written when it does not yet exist. Subsequent changes
                during generation will be reflected automatically in the abstract parent classes. The implementation
                classes extending them will require a manual update.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="The copy-over feature">
            <p>
                So what about JSPs ? The most efficient and effective way of maintaining manually edited changes
                in JSP files seems to be to copy the generated JSPs into your source directory (and subsequently
                adding it to your <code>Control Versioning System</code>), making your changes and copying them
                over the generated ones prior to building the WAR bundle.
            </p>
            <p>
                If you have generated your project build structure using
                <a href="../../starting.html#My_first_AndroMDA_project">andromdapp:generate</a> you will have a section
                in <code>/web/maven.xml</code> that is commented out, it is a <code>preGoal</code> to
                <code>war:init</code>, just uncomment it in order to have files in <code>/web/src/jsp</code> copied
                over the existing ones in the <code>.war</code> bundle.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="JavaScript">
            <p>
                JavaScript can greatly improve a web application's look and feel, the bpm4struts cartridge
                generates a few common routines that can be used in the pages. The files containing these routines
                have a <code>.js</code> extension and can be found in the set of generated pages, typically
                <code>/web/target/src/layout</code>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Let us know if you think more JavaScript should be added, just supply us with the ones you would like
                to see in there.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Dynamic Content">
            <p>
                The <a href="howto2.html#Action_States">Action States</a> page explained how you can take control
                of the HTTP response to return anything you like back to the browser. Nice to know is that
                you can also use this feature to send downloadable content so the browser will prompt you with
                a download dialog instead of trying to render everything on screen.
            </p>
            <p>
                Here's an example that will prompt for PDF download, notice how the preferred file name has
                been specified:
<source language="java">
<!--
byte[] exportBytes = getReportingService().getReport(reportId);

response.setContentType("application/pdf");
response.setContentLength(exportBytes.length);
response.setHeader("Content-disposition",
    "attachment; filename=InactiveArticlesReport.pdf");

response.getOutputStream().write(exportBytes);
-->
</source>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Validation of numbers when using Strings">
            <p>
                Because Bpm4Struts will automatically provide validation for any modeled numeric type 
                (i.e. a modeled <em>datatype::Integer</em> will be validated that the field is indeed a valid integer
                value) it saves you a lot of trouble right?  Well, this is all great unless of course you
                don't want the annoying <em>0</em> that Struts likes to provide as the default when no value as
                been entered.
            </p>
            <p>
                So how do you get the great default validation and yet avoid the default zero you ask?  
                Very easy: just continue to model the parameters as a number 
                (i.e. <em>datatype::Integer</em> for example), then within a customized Java mappings file
                for the Bpm4Struts namespace just map this number type to a java.lang.String.
                For example, here we add the mapping for <em>datatype::Integer</em>
<source language="xml">
<![CDATA[
<mappings name="Java">
    ...
    <mapping>
        <from>datatype::Integer</from>
        <to>java.lang.String</to>
    </mapping>
    ...
</mappings>
]]>
</source>
                and then specify the mapping in the bpm4struts namespace, like so:
<source language="xml">
<![CDATA[
<namespace name="bpm4struts">
    <properties>
         ...
         <property name="languageMappingsUri">file:${maven.conf.dir}/mappings/JavaMappings.xml</property>
         ...
    </properties>
</namespace>
]]>
</source>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Performance">
            <p>
                You might want to turn on the JSP precompilation feature, it will compile your JSPs into Java files
                and compile those into Java classes. Since this is done during the build process the Web container
                will not need to lose time compiling your JSP pages at runtime. Additionally you will find any
                compilation errors that might occur. It has shown that performance increases by a factor 10 when
                accessing the pages for the first time, in all other cases performance is the same.
            </p>
            <p>
                To enable jsp precompilation simply go into your
                <a href="../../starting.html#My_first_AndroMDA_project">andromdapp:generate</a> generated
                project, open the <code>/web/project.properties</code> file and make sure the
                <code>precompileJsps</code> property has been set to <code>true</code>.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Troubleshooting">
            <subsection name="Precompilation">
                <p>
                    In some cases it is known precompiled applications to intermittently throw exceptions on Windows
                    machines. This is a known issue and is related to the Windows operating system not allowing
                    file names to be longer than 255 characters. When you precompile JSPs, and the resulting classes
                    are stored deep into the EAR, into the WAR, into the
                    <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> subdirectory. Windows
                    might not be able to properly resolve them if the fully qualified path to the file is longer than
                    255 characters, the path will silently be truncated and the Java VM will report it was unable to
                    find the class.
                </p>
                <p>
                    This problem cannot be solved, but a few workarounds exist:
                    <ul>
                        <li>Move the deployment directory closer to the root of the drive</li>
                        <li>Shorten the name of the JSP page on which the loading fails</li>
                        <li>Explode the contents of the EAR and the WAR, this can be done automatically for you
                            if you set the <code>explodeOnDeploy</code> property to <code>true</code>
                            in <code>/app/project.properties</code>. The next time you deploy using the maven
                            <code>deploy</code> goal, a directory containing everything be deployed
                            instead of a single EAR bundle.
                        </li>
                        <li>Move to a Unix-based system, such as Linux.</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Compatibility">
                <p>
                    Although most applications are perfectly portable across
                    different containers it might happen that some specific feature
                    needs special attention.
                </p>
                <p>
                    An example is WebSphere which requires the web.xml to contain
                    an <code>id</code> attribute for most elements, Resin on the
                    other hand can get into trouble this way. This example can be
                    configured using the <code>generateWebXmlIds</code> namespace
                    property.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Bpm4Struts generates code that is compliant to the J2EE v1.4
                    and Struts 1.2.x specifications. You will need Java 1.4
                    or higher to be able to run the generated applications.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
