<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="tfmorris@tigris.org">Tom Morris</author>
        <title>Create PersonVO using ArgoUML</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Create PersonVO using ArgoUML">
            <p>
                This page provides directions to create the PersonVO using ArgoUML. The model is
                shown below for your reference.
            </p>

            <p>
                <div align="center">
                    <img src="../../../images/argouml/PersonVO.png"/>
                </div>
            </p>

            <p>
              <ol>
                <li>In the TimeTracker model create a package called <code>vo</code> under
                    <code>org.andromda.timetracker</code>. We will create our value objects in this package.</li>
                <li>Select the <code>vo</code> package in the Explorer pane and click the
                    Class Diagram icon in the Diagrams toolbar to create a new diagram in
                    this package.</li>
                <li>From the Explorer pane on the left, drag the <code>Person</code> class on to the diagram.
                    Warning: It is important to bring in the existing <code>Person</code> class from the <code>domain</code>
                    package into this diagram. DO NOT create a new <code>Person</code> class in this diagram.
                    Doing so will create a new class in the <code>vo</code> package
                    - this is not our intention. All we need is a reference to the existing <code>Person</code>
                    class in the <code>domain</code> package.</li>
                <li>Add a new class to the diagram and name it <code>PersonVO</code>.</li>
                <li>Add the stereotype called ValueObject to the <code>PersonVO</code> class.</li>
                <li>Add four attributes to <code>PersonVO</code> as shown above.</li>
                <li>Select the Dependency tool (dashed line with open arrowhead) from the toolbar.
                    Now left-click on the<code>Person</code> class, drag to the <code>PersonVO</code>
                    class and release the mouse button. A dependency relationship is added between
                    the two classes.</li>
                <li>Add a new class to the diagram and name it <code>PersonVO[]</code>.</li>
                <li>Make sure your class diagram matches the one shown above.</li>
                <li>Save the model by selecting File > Save Project.</li>
              </ol>
            </p>

            <p>
              We are now ready to generate code for the <code>PersonVO</code> value object. Please go back to the main
              tutorial page and continue from where you left off.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
