<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>
            Starter App
        </title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Starter App">

            <p>
                In this section, we will create a starter application using the AndroMDA plugin.
                We will later build on this application to incrementally add time tracking features.
                We recommend that you have the completed application (downloaded in the previous
                section) on hand in case you need to troubleshoot your version.
            </p>

            <p>
                One caution before we start - please follow all instructions very carefully and
                precisely. DO NOT take any shortcuts because doing so will only waste your time.
                There is a good reason for every step in this tutorial. You will not find any fluff
                here!
            </p>
            <p>
                Ok, we are now ready to start. Follow the steps below to create the starter application:
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Open a Command Prompt and change its directory to a location where you would like
                    to create the application folder. In this example, we have chosen the C:\ directory
                    for this purpose. The application will be created in the directory C:\timetracker.
                    <i>Note: If you decide to create the application at a different location, make sure
                        there are no spaces in your pathname - otherwise Maven will run into build problems.
                    </i>
                </li>
                <li>Now execute the following command to generate the starter application. Answer the
                    questions exactly as shown in the output that follows. You are allowed to enter
                    your own name in response to the first question :-).
                </li>
            </ol>
            <source>
                C:\&gt;mvn org.andromda.maven.plugins:andromdapp-maven-plugin:3.4-SNAPSHOT:generate
                [INFO] Scanning for projects...
                [INFO] Searching repository for plugin with prefix: 'andromdapp'.
                [INFO] ----------------------------------------------------------------------------
                [INFO] Building Maven Default Project
                [INFO]    task-segment: [org.andromda.maven.plugins:andromdapp-maven-plugin:3.4-SNAPSHOT:generate] (aggregator-style)
                [INFO] ----------------------------------------------------------------------------
                [INFO] [andromdapp:generate] {execution: default-cli}]
                INFO [AndroMDA] discovered andromdapp type --&gt; 'j2ee'
                INFO [AndroMDA] discovered andromdapp type --&gt; 'richclient'

                Please choose the type of application to generate [richclient, j2ee]
                j2ee

                Please enter the parent directory of your new application directory, using forward slashes (i.e. C:/workspaces):
                C:/

                Please enter your first and last name (i.e. Chad Brandon):
                Bob Fields

                Which kind of modeling tool will you use? (uml1.4/uml2 for .xml.zip/.xml files,
                emf-uml22 for .uml files, rsm7 for .emx files) [uml1.4, uml2, emf-uml22, rsm7,]
                Use the list below to enter the correct choice:
                ArgoUML: uml1.4
                MagicDraw 9.x: uml1.4
                MagicDraw 11.5: uml2
                RSM 7, 7.5, 8: emf-uml22
                uml1.4

                Please enter the name of your J2EE project (i.e. Animal Quiz):
                TimeTracker

                Please enter an id for your J2EE project (i.e. animalquiz):
                timetracker

                Please enter a version for your project (i.e. 1.0-SNAPSHOT):
                1.0-SNAPSHOT

                Please enter the root package name for your J2EE project
                (i.e. org.andromda.samples.animalquiz):
                org.andromda.timetracker

                Would you like an EAR or standalone WAR? [ear, war,]:
                ear

                Please enter the type of transactional/persistence cartridge to use (enter 'none' 
                if you don't want to use one) [hibernate, ejb, ejb3, spring, none,]:
                spring

                Please enter the programming language to be used in service and dao implementations 
                [java, groovy,]:
                java
                Please enter the database backend for the persistence layer
                [hypersonic, mysql, oracle, db2, informix, mssql, pointbase,
                postgres, sybase, sabdb, progress, derby,]:
                mysql

                Will your project need workflow engine capabilities?
                (it uses jBPM and Hibernate3)? [yes, no,]:
                no

                Will your project have a web user interface? [yes, no,]:

                yes

                Would you like your web user interface to use JSF or Struts? [jsf, struts,]:
                struts

                Would you like to be able to expose your services as web services? [yes, no,]:
                no
                -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
                G e n e r a t i n g A n d r o M D A P o w e r e d A p p l i c a t i o n
                -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/core/target/classes/META-INF/ejb-jar.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/core/pom.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/app/src/main/config/timetracker-ds.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/app/src/main/application/META-INF/jboss-app.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/app/pom.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/m2eclipse.bat'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/common/pom.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/web/src/main/properties/messages.properties'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/web/pom.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/web/target/timetracker-1.0-SNAPSHOT/WEB-INF/web.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/web/target/timetracker-web-1.0-SNAPSHOT/WEB-INF/web.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/pom.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/config/mappings/WebMergeMappings.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/config/mappings/JavaMappings.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/config/mappings/SpringMergeMappings.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/config/andromda.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/src/main/uml/timetracker.xmi'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/pom.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/log4j.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/build.xml'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/readme.txt'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/build.properties'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/mda/.project'
                Output: 'file:/C:/timetracker/readme.txt'
                -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
                New application generated to --> 'file:/C:/timetracker/'
                Instructions for your new application --> 'file:/C:/timetracker/readme.txt'                -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
                -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
                [INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
                [INFO] BUILD SUCCESSFUL
                [INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
                [INFO] Total time: 3 minutes 45 seconds
                [INFO] Finished at: Tue Dec 07 00:23:13 EST 2010
                [INFO] Final Memory: 39M/133M
                [INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------

                C:\&gt;
            </source>
            <p>
                Examine the various folders and files created by the
                <tt>andromdapp</tt>
                plugin.
                You will notice files called
                <tt>pom.xml</tt>
                in various folders under timetracker.
                These files make up several Maven projects. In fact, the timetracker directory contains
                a hierarchy of Maven projects as shown below.
            </p>
            <source>
                timetracker
                |
                |-- mda
                |
                |-- common
                |
                |-- core
                |
                |-- web
                |
                +-- app
            </source>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <b>timetracker:</b>
                    This is the master project that controls the overall
                    build process and common properties.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>mda:</b>
                    The mda project is the most important sub-project of the application.
                    It houses the TimeTracker UML model under the src/main/uml directory. The mda project
                    is also where AndroMDA is configured to generate the files needed to assemble the
                    application.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>common:</b>
                    The common sub-project collects resources and classes that
                    are shared among other sub-projects. These include value objects and embedded values.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>core:</b>
                    The core sub-project collects resources and classes that
                    use the Spring framework, optionally making use of Hibernate and/or EJBs under the
                    hood. These include entity classes, data access objects, hibernate mapping files,
                    and services.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>web:</b>
                    The web sub-project collects those resources and classes that
                    make up the presentation layer.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>app:</b>
                    The app sub-project collects those resources and classes that
                    are required to build the .ear bundle.
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                You can find more details about these files in
                <tt>readme.txt</tt>
                under the
                timetracker folder. This file also contains a description of useful Maven targets
                for the project. As a matter of fact, developers frequently refer to this file for
                commonly used Maven commands. Open this file now and get yourself familiar with
                it.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Configure TimeTracker Application">
                <p>
                    We will make minor configuration changes to the project generated by AndroMDA to
                    fine tune how TimeTracker is built, telling you the reason for each change as we
                    go along.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Open the AndroMDA configuration file located at
                    <tt>timetracker\mda\src\main\config\andromda.xml</tt>.
                    Make the following changes:
                </p>
                <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                    <li>Search for the property called
                        <tt>enableSpringTransactionsWhenEjbsEnabled</tt>
                        and change its value from
                        <tt>true</tt>
                        to <tt>false</tt>. Since we will
                        be using EJBs, we do not want Spring to be controlling database transactions.
                    </li>
                    <li>Search for the namespace called <tt>bpm4struts</tt>. In this namespace, add
                        a property to change the default date format for the application so it matches that
                        in the prototype. The property will look like this:
                        <br/>
                        <tt>&lt;property name=&quot;defaultDateFormat&quot;&gt;MM/dd/yyyy&lt;/property&gt;</tt>
                    </li>
                    <li>Add another property in the
                        <tt>bpm4struts</tt>
                        namespace as shown below:
                        <br/>
                        <tt>&lt;property name=&quot;normalizeMessages&quot;&gt;true&lt;/property&gt;</tt>
                        <br/>
                        This property allows generation of smaller resource bundles with duplicate element
                        names specified by a single message. This optimization is turned off by default
                        for backward compatibility.
                    </li>
                    <li>Save and close
                        <tt>andromda.xml</tt>
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>
                    Open the top level POM file located at <tt>timetracker\pom.xml</tt>. Make the
                    following changes:
                </p>
                <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                    <li>Search for the following line which specifies the JDBC driver used by the application:
                        <br/>
                        <tt>&lt;jdbc.driver.jar&gt;${jboss.home}/server/default/lib/hsqldb.jar&lt;/jdbc.driver.jar&gt;</tt>
                        <br/>
                        Since we are using MySQL, change this line as follows (be sure to specify the correct
                        version of your driver):
                        <br/>
                        <tt>&lt;jdbc.driver.jar&gt;${jboss.home}/server/default/lib/mysql-connector-java-5.0.4.jar&lt;/jdbc.driver.jar&gt;</tt>
                    </li>
                    <li>Search for the following two lines which specify the database username and password:
                        <br/>
                        <tt>&lt;jdbc.username&gt;sa&lt;/jdbc.username&gt;
                            <br/>
                            &lt;jdbc.password&gt;&lt;/jdbc.password&gt;
                            <br/>
                        </tt>
                        Change the username and password values to those used during database creation:
                        <br/>
                        <tt>&lt;jdbc.username&gt;timetracker&lt;/jdbc.username&gt;
                            <br/>
                            &lt;jdbc.password&gt;timetracker&lt;/jdbc.password&gt;
                            <br/>
                        </tt>
                    </li>
                    <li>Search for
                        <tt>&lt;repositories&gt;</tt>
                        section. Here you will find a declaration
                        for the AndroMDA Repository. Add a declaration for the Java.net repository. This
                        repository will be used to dowload jars provided by Sun (such as <tt>jta.jar</tt>).
                        The resulting
                        <tt>&lt;repositories&gt;</tt>
                        section is shown below:
                        <source>
<![CDATA[
    <repositories>
        <repository>
            <id>andromda</id>
            <name>AndroMDA Repository</name>
            <url>http://www.andromda.org/maven2</url>
        </repository>
        <repository>
            <id>maven2-repository.dev.java.net</id>
            <name>Java.net Repository for Maven 2</name>
            <url>https://maven2-repository.dev.java.net/nonav/repository</url>
            <layout>default</layout>
        </repository>
    </repositories>
]]>
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>Save and close
                        <tt>pom.xml</tt>
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>
                    Open the POM file for the mda sub-project located at
                    <tt>timetracker\mda\pom.xml</tt>
                    and make the following change:
                </p>
                <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                    <li>Search for property called
                        <tt>hibernate.db.showSql</tt>
                        and change its value
                        from
                        <tt>true</tt>
                        to <tt>false</tt>. This prevents verbose Hibernate messages
                        to be printed on the JBoss console. We will still have the appropriate SQL messages
                        in the JBoss log file, which is the better place to look at these messages.
                    </li>
                    <li>Save and close
                        <tt>pom.xml</tt>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="What's Next?">
                <p>
                    Now that we have created the base application, it is time to start modeling. Click
                    <a href="userservice-definition.html">here</a> to model your first entity.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
