<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>
            Details Column
        </title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Details Column">

            <p>
                In this section we will add the details column to the results table. This column
                will have buttons that will take you to the Timecard Details page when clicked.
                The modified activity diagram for this functionality is shown below:
            </p>

            <div align="center">
                <img src="images/SearchTimecardsAD3.jpg" alt="Search Timecards Activity Diagram"/>
            </div>
            <p>
                This activity diagram has no new modeling concepts, so we will give you just the
                high level steps to construct it. In general, we are trying to create a
                <tt>details</tt>
                trigger coming out of the
                <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                view. The
                <tt>details</tt>
                trigger will contain an
                <tt>id</tt>
                parameter that indicates which timecard
                was clicked. We need to pass this
                <tt>id</tt>
                to the next use case called <tt>
                Timecard Details</tt>. However, since
                <tt>id</tt>
                is not a very descriptive
                name we would like to convert it to a page variable called <tt>timecardId</tt>,
                which will be passed to the next page. The activity called
                <tt>Initialize Timecard Id</tt>
                transforms the
                <tt>id</tt>
                parameter to the
                <tt>timecardId</tt>
                page variable. So, without further delay, here are the steps to update your activity
                diagram:
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>First create the action state called <tt>Initialize Timecard Id</tt>. Remember
                    that the
                    <i>Name</i>
                    of the action state should be
                    <tt>Initialize Timecard Id</tt>
                    (not just its label). This is done by double-clicking the state and entering the
                    name in the action state specification.
                </li>
                <li>Create a transition from
                    <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                    to <tt>Initialize Timecard
                        Id</tt>. Create a signal trigger on this transition called
                    <tt>details</tt>
                    and add a parameter to it called
                    <tt>id</tt>
                    of type <tt>Long</tt>. (This
                    is similar to adding the
                    <tt>search</tt>
                    trigger out of <tt>Search Timecards</tt>.)
                </li>
                <li>Add a tag to the
                    <tt>id</tt>
                    parameter called
                    <tt>andromda_presentation_web_view_field_type</tt>
                    and set its value to <tt>link</tt>. This tag ensures that the
                    <tt>id</tt>
                    column in the table will be a link instead of the default text box.
                </li>
                <li>Add a tag on the transition (not on the trigger) called
                    <tt>andromda_presentation_web_action_tablelink</tt>
                    and set its value to <tt>timecardSummaries</tt>. This tag ensures that the
                    <tt>
                        details
                    </tt>
                    trigger will occur on the table that displays <tt>timecardSummaries</tt>.
                    Also since we are not specifying any attribute in this value (such as <tt>timecardSummaries.id</tt>)
                    a separate column will be created with buttons named <tt>Details</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Create a final state.</li>
                <li>Add a transition from
                    <tt>Initialize Timecard Id</tt>
                    to the final state.
                </li>
                <li>Create a page variable called
                    <tt>timecardId</tt>
                    of type
                    <tt>Long</tt>
                    on this transition. Remember that page variables are created by first creating a
                    signal trigger with no name and adding the page variable as a parameter on this
                    trigger. (This is similar to adding the
                    <tt>timecardSummaries</tt>
                    page variable.)
                </li>
                <li>Switch to the
                    <tt>Services</tt>
                    diagram for a second and add the following method
                    to the
                    <tt>SearchController</tt>
                    <br/>
                    <tt>+initializeTimecardId(id : Long, timecardId : Long) : void</tt>
                </li>
                <li>Switch back to the activity diagram and call the
                    <tt>initializeTimecardId()</tt>
                    method from the
                    <tt>Initialize Timecard Id</tt>
                    action state. Remember that
                    the call should be added as a deferrable event. (This is similar to adding the
                    <tt>
                        populateSearchScreen()
                    </tt>
                    call to the
                    <tt>Populate Search Screen</tt>
                    action state.)
                    <i>MagicDraw users: You can create and call the
                        <tt>SearchController.initializeTimecardId()</tt>
                        method, all in one step, when editing the call trigger. This is done using the &quot;New
                        Button&quot; on the right of the combobox. It's a shortcut that frees you from switching
                        to another diagram.
                    </i>
                </li>
                <li>We need to connect the final state to the next use case which is <tt>Timecard
                    Details</tt>. To do this, simply open the specification for the final state by
                    double-clicking on it. In the
                    <i>Name</i>
                    field, enter <tt>Timecard Details</tt>.
                    AndroMDA does a name match to connect the final state to the target use case (which
                    we have not created yet).
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                That completes the
                <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                activity diagram. Of course, we
                still need to create the
                <tt>Timecard Details</tt>
                use case, otherwise AndroMDA
                will complain that it cannot find the target for the final state in the
                <tt>Search
                    Timecards
                </tt>
                activity diagram. Follow the steps below to create a very simple
                <tt>Timecard Details</tt>
                use case:
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Open the use case diagram called <tt>Application Use Cases</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Add a new use case and call it <tt>Timecard Details</tt>. Give it the
                    <tt>
                        FrontEndUseCase
                    </tt>
                    stereotype.
                </li>
                <li>In the model, create a new package under
                    <tt>org.andromda.timetracker.web</tt>
                    and call it <tt>timecarddetails</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Move the
                    <tt>Timecard Details</tt>
                    use case from the
                    <tt>Use Cases</tt>
                    package to the
                    <tt>timecarddetails</tt>
                    package that we just created. This can
                    be done in the Containment Tree.
                </li>
                <li>Now create a class called
                    <tt>TimecardController</tt>
                    under the
                    <tt>timecarddetails</tt>
                    package.
                </li>
                <li>Create a new activity diagram under the
                    <tt>Timecard Details</tt>
                    use case and
                    name it <tt>Timecard Details Activity Diagram</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Connect the
                    <tt>TimecardController</tt>
                    to the activity diagram using the procedure
                    specific to your modeling tool. (This is similar to the way we connected the
                    <tt>SearchController</tt>
                    to the
                    <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                    activity diagram.)
                </li>
                <li>Open the
                    <tt>Timecard Details</tt>
                    activity diagram and enter the following
                    elements to it. Note that the page variable
                    <tt>timecardId</tt>
                    gets its value
                    from the previous use case ( <tt>Search Timecards</tt>).
                </li>
            </ol>
            <div align="center">
                <img src="images/TimecardDetailsAD1.jpg" alt="Timecard Details Activity Diagram"/>
            </div>
            <p>
                Now let's ask AndroMDA to generate code for the modified model:
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Execute the commands
                    <tt>mvn clean</tt>
                    followed by
                    <tt>mvn install</tt>
                    in the Command Prompt. The build will fail complaining about the
                    <tt>SearchControllerImpl</tt>
                    class because we have not implemented the
                    <tt>initializeTimecardId()</tt>
                    method.
                </li>
                <li>Open
                    <tt>SearchControllerImpl.java</tt>
                    and add the following code to it.
                    <source>
                        public final void initializeTimecardId(
                        ActionMapping mapping,
                        org.andromda.timetracker.web.timecardsearch.InitializeTimecardIdForm form,
                        HttpServletRequest request,
                        HttpServletResponse response)
                        throws Exception
                        {
                        form.setTimecardId(form.getId());
                        }
                    </source>
                </li>
                <li>Build only the web project to make sure the code added above is compiled and packaged.
                    Here's how:
                    <br/>
                    <tt>mvn -f web/pom.xml install</tt>
                </li>
                <li>Make sure the JBoss server is running.</li>
                <li>Deploy the application:
                    <br/>
                    <tt>mvn -f app/pom.xml -Ddeploy</tt>
                </li>
                <li>Open a browser and make it point to http://localhost:8080/timetracker. The TimeTracker
                    search page should appear with
                    <tt>Details</tt>
                    buttons in the results panel.
                    <i>Note: You may have to click your browser's refresh button to clear its cache and
                        grab a fresh copy of the page.
                    </i>
                </li>
                <li>Click on one of the
                    <tt>Details</tt>
                    buttons. The browser should forward to
                    the
                    <tt>Timecard Details</tt>
                    page. Notice that
                    <tt>id</tt>
                    is passed as
                    a parameter in the URL.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                Below is a screen shot of the Search screen so far.
            </p>
            <div align="center">
                <img src="images/SearchResultsPanel2.jpg" alt="Search Results Panel"/>
            </div>
            <subsection name="What's Next?">
                <p>
                    We have now implemented the full functionality of the search screen. All that remains
                    is the look and feel as specified by the TimeTracker prototype.
                    Click <a href="look-and-feel.html">here</a> to start customizing the look and feel.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
