<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
       xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Environment Setup</title>
        <author email="naresh@andromda.org">Naresh Bhatia</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Prepare the Development Environment">
            <p>
                This section provides a step-by-step guide to set up your development environment for AndroMDA.
                We assume that you are working on a Windows platform.
                Throughout this section you will install various programs. The recommended installation paths for
                these programs and other required directories are listed below. Please feel free to change the installation
                paths depending on your configuration and personal preferences. For example, you may choose to install programs
                on the D: drive instead of the C: drive. However, note that some programs don't work well if there are spaces
                in their pathname. So, try to stick to the suggestions below as much as possible.
            </p>
            <table>
                <tr>
                    <th>Recommended Path</th>
                    <th>Purpose</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Documents and Settings\<b>your user name</b>\.m2\repository</td>
                    <td>Maven local repository</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Program Files\Apache Software Foundation\maven-2.2.1</td>
                    <td>Maven program</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Program Files\Java\jdk1.6.0_xx</td>
                    <td>Java Development Kit (xx is the update number)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Program Files\Java\jre1.6.0_xx</td>
                    <td>Java Runtime Engine (xx is the update number)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Program Files\MySQL\MySQL Server 5.0</td>
                    <td>MySQL database server</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Program Files\JetBrains\IntelliJ IDEA 9.0.2</td>
                    <td>IntelliJ IDEA IDE (optional)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\eclipse</td>
                    <td>Eclipse IDE (optional)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\jboss-4.0.5</td>
                    <td>JBoss Application Server</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <p>
                You will also be asked to set up several environment variables. Please set these as SYSTEM variables using the Control Panel
                (Control Panel > System > Advanced > Environment Variables). Note that if you change the installation path of any program
                then you must make sure that the associated environment variable is changed accordingly.
            </p>

            <subsection name="Install Java">
                <p>
                    Install J2SE Development Kit 6 (JDK 6) or newer from <a
                        href="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp">here</a>.
                    This is the preferred version of the JDK for AndroMDA.
                    We also support JDK version 1.5. But we don't support JDK version 1.4 anymore!
                </p>
                <p>
                    Make sure that the
                    <code>JAVA_HOME</code>
                    environment variable is pointing to
                    the directory where you installed the JDK. It is possible you have this
                    variable set already, but just to make sure here's how to check.
                </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>
                        Go to the control panel and double-click on<code>System</code>.
                        If you are a Windows XP user it's possible you have to open
                        <code>Performance and Maintenance</code>
                        before you will see
                        the
                        <code>System</code>
                        icon.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Go to the
                        <code>Advanced</code>
                        tab and click on
                        <code>Environment Variables</code>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Make sure you have set the
                        <code>JAVA_HOME</code>
                        variable set
                        and it is pointing to the directory where you installed the JDK.
                        If not, add/edit the variable and set it to the correct value,
                        e.g. C:\Program Files\Java\jdk1.6.0_xx. You may add the variable
                        to the list of user variables or system variables.
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install Maven">
                <p>
                    <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven2</a>
                    is our preferred tool for building and deploying applications generated by AndroMDA. Based on the concept of a project object model (POM), Maven can manage a project's build, reporting, and documentation from a central piece of information. If you are familiar with Ant, Maven is very similar except that it contains additional functionality:
                </p>

                <ol>
                    <li>
                        A hierarchical build environment, where properties configured in a POM file (pom.xml) flow down to POM files of all child projects.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Standardized build tasks (clean, build, install, deploy, etc.)
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Dependency specifications for build and deploy tasks - for all internal and external libraries; tied to a specific released versions of dependent libraries
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        A repository containing all versioned dependencies. This repository is used during the build and deploy processes (very similar to the .NET Global Assembly Cache concept).
                    </li>
                </ol>

                <p>Install Maven 2.2.1 by following the steps below.</p>

                <ol>
                    <li>
                        Click here and download Maven 2.2.1 or newer.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Unzip this file at C:\Program Files\Apache Software Foundation. A directory called maven-2.2.1 will be created which contains the Maven program.
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>
                    Note: If you are behind a proxy server, you will have to configure Maven to use the proxy. The details can be found here.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Setup environment variables">
                <p>
                    We have seen earlier how to set environment variables such as
                    <code>JAVA_HOME</code>, it is strongly recommended to set the
                    following variables before continuing. We repeat
                    <code>JAVA_HOME</code>
                    here just for completeness.
                </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Property</th>
                        <th>Value</th>
                        <th>Required?</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>JAVA_HOME</td>
                        <td>Java installation directory, e.g.
                            <code>C:\Program Files\Java\jdk1.6.xx</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>Yes</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>M2_HOME</td>
                        <td>Maven installation directory, e.g.
                            <code>C:\Program Files\Apache Software Foundation\Maven 2.2.1</code>
                            (this may have already been set by the Maven installer)
                        </td>
                        <td>Yes</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>M2_REPO</td>
                        <td>Maven local repository, e.g. C:\Documents and Settings\<b>your user name</b>\.m2\repository</td>
                        <td>Yes</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>MAVEN_OPTS</td>
                        <td>Parameters to pass to the Java VM when running Maven. Set this
                            value to:
                            <code>-XX:MaxPermSize=128m -Xmx512m</code>
                            (required to build large maven projects such as AndroMDA itself)
                        </td>
                        <td>No</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>PATH</td>
                        <td>This makes sure the system will search for console commands in
                            the directories listed here. If this property already exists you
                            should simply add
                            <code>%JAVA_HOME%\bin;%M2_HOME%\bin</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>Yes</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>


            <subsection name="Install AndroMDA Application plugin">
                <p>
                    Next we will download and install the AndroMDA Application plugin
                    to the M2_HOME/plugins directory. This plugin allows creation of
                    Java starter applications that use AndroMDA. This is the only AndroMDA
                    artifact that we will install explicitly. All other artifacts, such
                    as AndroMDA cartridges, will be automatically downloaded by the
                    Maven scripts generated by the plugin.
                </p>

                <ul>
                    <li>Click <a href="http://andromda.googlegroups.com/web/andromdapp-maven-plugin-install-3.3.zip">here</a> to download the the AndroMDA plugin installer.</li>
                    <li>Unzip the contents of the installer into your Maven repository at C:\Documents and Settings\<strong>your user name</strong>\.m2\repository.</li>
                    <li>Verify that the following directory was created:C:\Documents and Settings\<strong>your user name</strong>\.m2\repository\org\andromda\maven\plugins\andromdapp-maven-plugin</li>
                    <li>Create a temporary directory, e.g. C:\andromda-temp.</li>
                    <li>Create a file called pom.xml in this directory with the following content.
                        <source><![CDATA[
<project xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/maven-v4_0_0.xsd">
<modelVersion>4.0.0</modelVersion>
<groupId>samples.test</groupId>
<artifactId>test</artifactId>
<version>1.0</version>
<packaging>jar</packaging>
<name>test</name>

<build>
    <defaultGoal>compile</defaultGoal>
    <plugins>
        <plugin>
            <groupId>org.andromda.maven.plugins</groupId>
            <artifactId>andromdapp-maven-plugin</artifactId>
            <version>3.3</version>
        </plugin>
    </plugins>
</build>

<repositories>
    <repository>
        <id>andromda</id>
        <name>AndroMDA Repository</name>
        <url>http://www.andromda.org/maven2</url>
    </repository>
</repositories>

<pluginRepositories>
    <pluginRepository>
        <id>andromda</id>
        <name>AndroMDA Repository</name>
        <url>http://www.andromda.org/maven2</url>
    </pluginRepository>
</pluginRepositories>
</project>
                                ]]>
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>Open a Command Prompt in the directory where you created this pom.xml and
                        run the command mvn without any arguments. Make sure the command completes successfully
                        by displaying the BUILD SUCCESSFUL message.</li>
                    <li>You can now delete the temporary directory you created in step 1.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install a UML tool">
                <p>
                    Install a tool that will allow you to model your applications in UML and
                    export these models into a format that AndroMDA can understand. AndroMDA
                    currently supports UML 1.4 and XMI 1.2. Please follow one of the links
                    below to install the UML tool of your choice. (We invite UML tool vendors
                    and open-source projects to test their tools with AndroMDA and supply
                    installation instructions for inclusion in this section.)
                </p>

                <p>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/argouml/install.html">ArgoUML (UML 1.4/XMI 1.2)</a><br/>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/magicdraw/install.html">MagicDraw 9.5 (UML 1.4/XMI 1.2)</a><br/>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/magicdraw/install16.html">MagicDraw 16.5 (UML 2/EMF)</a><br/>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/rsm/install.html">RSM 6 (Rational Software Modeler/Architect)(UML 2/EMF)</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install a database">
                <p>
                    Install a database that is supported by Hibernate. Click
                    <a href="http://www.hibernate.org/260.html">here</a>
                    to see
                    the list of supported databases. For the purpose of this tutorial we will
                    assume that you have installed one of the following databases. If you have
                    installed another database then you will have to change the Hibernate
                    configuration accordingly.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <strong>MySQL 5.0:</strong>
                        MySQL is an open source database. You can download it from
                        <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/mysql/5.0.html"
                          >here</a>. We recommend
                        downloading the full Windows installation - not just the "Essentials". In addition, download and install
                        <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/administrator/1.1.html"
                          >MySQL Administrator
                        </a>
                        as well as <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/query-browser/1.1.html"
                                    >MySQL Query Browser</a>.
                        These are GUI based tools that will make your development much easier. Finally, download and unzip
                        <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/connector/j/3.1.html"
                          >MySQL Connector/J
                        </a>
                        (the MySQL JDBC driver) in a convenient directory. For the purpose of this tutorial we will assume that
                        you have installed the driver at
                        <code>C:\Program Files\MySQL\mysql-connector-java-3.1.12</code>.
                    </li>

                    <li>
                        <strong>PostgreSQL 8.1:</strong>
                        PostgreSQL is an open source database. You can download it from
                        <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/ftp/binary/v8.1.2/win32/"
                          >here</a>. The Postgres
                        installation contains a GUI based administrative tool called pgAdmin III. JDBC drivers are also
                        included as part of the installation.
                    </li>

                    <li>
                        <strong>Oracle 9i:</strong>
                        Oracle 9i is an commercial database sold by
                        <a href="http://www.oracle.com">Oracle</a>. We assume that you
                        have the necessary distribution media to install it. Oracle 9i includes a GUI
                        based administrative tool called Enterprise Manager. JDBC drivers are also
                        included as part of the installation.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install Eclipse (Optional)">
                <p>
                    Eclipse is a popular open source IDE that is useful in developing Java
                    applications. AndroMDA does not require the use of Eclipse. However we
                    do recommend using it for development as it helps increase your
                    productivity. You can download Eclipse from
                    <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/downloads/">here</a>.
                    We recommend downloading the Eclipse Europa Package called "Eclipse IDE for Java EE Developers".
                    Follow the steps below to install and configure Eclipse:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Unzip the downloaded archive to a suitable location on your hard drive. The recommended location is C:\eclipse.</li>
                    <li>Edit the file eclipse.ini under C:\eclipse to increase the memory available for Eclipse. Here are the suggested contents for this file:
                        <source>
                        -vmargs
                        -Xms256m
                        -Xmx512m
                        -XX:PermSize=128m
                        -XX:MaxPermSize=256m
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>Start Eclipse by double-clicking on eclipse.exe.</li>
                    <li>Eclipse asks for a folder where it can store your projects. This folder is called the Eclipse workspace. Set the workspace to a location where you generally creates projects, such as C:\Projects.</li>
                    <li>Choose Preferences from the Window Menu.</li>
                    <li>In the left pane, select Java &gt; Build Path &gt; Classpath Variables.</li>
                    <li>Click New.</li>
                    <li>Add M2_REPO in the Name field and the path of your M2 repository in the Path field (for example, C:\Documents and Settings\<strong>your user name</strong>\.m2\repository). This value is needed in order to import Maven generated project configurations.</li>
                    <li>Click OK twice to close the dialog boxes.</li>
                </ul>
                
            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="What's Next?">
            <p>
                Now that the development environment is set up we are ready to create the TimeTracker application.
                Click
                <a href="create-application.html">here</a>
                to get started.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
