<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>UserService Definition</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="UserService Definition">

            <p>
                As discussed under <a href="development-approach.html">
                Development Approach</a>, our first iteration will focus on getting the search
                screen to work. Here's a mockup of this screen:
            </p>

            <div align="center">
                <img src="images/SearchScreen.jpg" alt="Search Screen"/>
            </div>
            <p>
                To support this screen, the service layer needs to provide two functions:
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Ability to get a list of all users in order to populate the search criteria drop-downs
                    (<i>Submitter</i> and <i>Approver</i>)
                </li>
                <li>Ability to get a list of all timecards that match a specific search criteria.</li>
            </ol>
            <subsection name="UserVO Value Object">
                <p>
                    Let's zoom in on the first function, i.e. get a list of all users. Let's decide
                    that we will create a service called <tt>UserService</tt> that will provide
                    this functionality via the method specified below:
                </p>
                <source>
                public interface UserService
                {
                    public Collection&lt;UserVO&gt; getAllUsers();
                }
                </source>
                <p>
                    
                </p>
                <p>
                    <tt>UserVO</tt> is a value object associated with the <tt>User</tt>
                    entity (refer to <a href="application-architecture.html">Application Architecture</a> for a discussion
                    of entities and value objects). At a minimum,
                    the UserVO will need two attributes for the drop-downs to function properly: the
                    user's id and login name. However, to make <tt>UserVO</tt> a little more reusable,
                    let's add two more attributes to it: user's first name and last name. Based on this
                    discussion, the <tt>UserVO</tt> should be modeled as shown on the right.
                    <img src="images/UserVO.jpg" alt="UserVO"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Note that we have marked the <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class with a stereotype of <tt>ValueObject</tt>.
                    This tells AndroMDA that <tt>UserVO</tt> is a ValueObject as opposed to other
                    type of model elements such as Entity or EmbeddedValue. Stereotypes determine what
                    pattern of code AndroMDA will generate for a model element. More specifically, they
                    determine which AndroMDA code generation templates will be triggered.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Note that we have marked one attribute to be of type <tt>Long</tt> and three
                    attributes to be of type <tt>String</tt>. These types should not be confused
                    with the Java types <tt>java.lang.Long</tt> and <tt>java.lang.String</tt>.
                    In model driven architecture, the model is kept independent of technology and hence
                    all model elements are defined in terms of platform independent types. So
                    <tt>Long</tt> and <tt>String</tt>
                    in this context are platform independent types. When we
                    run AndroMDA to generate code, it will translate platform independent types into
                    platform dependent types such as <tt>java.lang.Long</tt> and <tt>java.lang.String</tt>.
                    If we were to use the same model to generate a .NET application, AndroMDA will translate
                    <tt>Long</tt> into <tt>long?</tt> and <tt>String</tt> into <tt>System.String</tt>,
                    which are .NET equivalents of <tt>java.lang.Long</tt> and <tt>java.lang.String</tt>.
                    As you can see, a key advantage of the model driven approach is that your investment
                    in the business models is preserved even as technologies come and go.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Now let us enter <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    in the empty model that was created by the
                    AndroMDA application plugin. If you remember, this model was created at
                    <tt>timetracker/mda/src/main/uml/timetracker.xmi</tt>.
                    Please follow one of the links below to edit the model with the UML tool of your
                    choice.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <a href="resources/uml-tools/argouml/UserVO.html">ArgoUML</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="resources/uml-tools/magicdraw/UserVO.html">MagicDraw</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="resources/uml-tools/rsm/UserVO.html">RSM/RSA</a>
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    Now let's ask AndroMDA to generate code for <tt>UserVO</tt>:
                </p>
                <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                    <li>Open a Command Prompt and change your directory to <tt>C:/timetracker</tt>.
                    </li>
                    <li>Execute the command <tt>mvn install</tt>. Make sure you get a
                        <tt>BUILD SUCCESSFUL</tt>
                        message.
                    </li>
                    <li>Keep the Command Prompt open for future builds.</li>
                </ol>
                <p>
                    Open the folder
                    <tt>C:/timetracker/common/target/src/org/andromda/timetracker/vo</tt>
                    in Windows Explorer. Note that the <tt>UserVO</tt> class is generated here.
                    Open the class and review its contents. The <tt>ValueObject</tt> stereotype
                    triggers the generation of only one artifact in the code, namely the Java class
                    representing the value object. Later we will see examples of stereotypes that trigger
                    the generation of multiple artifacts.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <b>Eclipse Users:</b>
                    To view your source in Eclipse, follow the steps below:
                </p>
                <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                    <li>Execute the command <tt>mvn install -Peclipse</tt> to generate <tt>.project</tt> and <tt>.classpath</tt></li>
                </ol>
                <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                    <li>Start Eclipse.</li>
                    <li>Choose Import from the File menu.</li>
                    <li>Select &quot;Existing Projects into Workspace&quot; and click Next.</li>
                    <li>In the Import dialog box, click Browse.</li>
                    <li>Browse to
                        <tt>C:/timetracker</tt>
                        and click OK.
                    </li>
                    <li>Click Finish. The
                        <tt>timetracker</tt>
                        project is now available in Eclipse.
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>
                    This setup procedure is required only once. In future, when you regenerate code, simply
                    right-click on the <tt>timetracker</tt> project in Package Explorer and choose
                    Refresh.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="UserService">
                <p>
                    <img src="images/UserService.jpg" alt="UserService"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Now that the <tt>UserVO</tt> is defined, we can model the <tt>UserService</tt>.
                    Based on our discussion above, the model for the <tt>UserService</tt> is shown
                    on the right. Please follow one of the links below to edit the model with the UML
                    tool of your choice.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <a href="resources/uml-tools/argouml/UserService.html">ArgoUML</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="resources/uml-tools/magicdraw/UserService.html">MagicDraw</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="resources/uml-tools/rsm/UserService.html">RSM/RSA</a>
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    Now let's ask AndroMDA to generate code for <tt>UserService</tt>:
                </p>
                <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                    <li>Execute the command <tt>mvn install</tt> in the Command Prompt. 
                    Make sure you get a <tt>BUILD SUCCESSFUL</tt> message.
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>
                    Unlike the <tt>ValueObject</tt>, a <tt>Service</tt> generates a trio of
                    classes: an interface, an abstract base class and a concrete implementation. Here
                    are the 3 classes generated for <tt>UserService</tt>
                </p>
                <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                    <li>
                        <b>UserService.java:</b>
                        <tt>UserService</tt> is the interface that
                        specifies the service methods. Since this interface is needed by client applications
                        as well as the service implementation, it is generated in the target branch of the
                        <tt>common</tt> project.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <b>UserServiceBase.java:</b>
                        <tt>UserServiceBase</tt> implements the methods specified by the
                        <tt>UserService</tt> interface. These methods essentially
                        do some parameter checking and then delegate the actual business functionality to
                        &quot;handle&quot; methods. Handle methods are expected to be implemented manually in the
                        <tt>UserServiceImpl</tt> class. <tt>UserServiceBase</tt> also manages transactional
                        behavior of the application. Transactions are started on entry of service methods
                        and finished on exit from these methods. <tt>UserServiceBase.java</tt>
                        is generated in the target branch of the <tt>core</tt> project.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <b>UserServiceImpl.java:</b>
                        <tt>UserServiceImpl</tt> is a concrete extension of the <tt>UserServiceBase</tt>
                        class. This is where developers are
                        expected to code the main business logic for the service methods. UserServiceImpl.java
                        is generated in the source branch of the <tt>core</tt> project.
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="UserService Test">
                <p>
                    In the spirit of Test Driven Development (TDD), we will write a test for the
                    <tt>UserService</tt>
                    even before it is implemented. The whole point of TDD is to write robust tests that
                    verify the complete functionality of the system under test -- if the tests pass,
                    you have good confidence that the system will function correctly; if not, then you
                    have some work cut out for you :-). Of course, once the tests are defined, you must
                    write implementation code to make them pass. The good part is that you need to write
                    just enough code to make the tests pass - no more, no less! For our simple
                    <tt>getAllUsers()</tt>
                    method, we will write a simple test that gets all the users and verifies the returned
                    values against what is expected.
                </p>
                <blockquote>
                    TODO: The test described below is completely manual -- we have not yet incorporated
                    a framework to populate the database with known values during the build process
                    and then to verify against those values. The test framework we use (a combination
                    of TestNG and DBUnit) is fully capable of doing that, so we will incorporate an
                    automated test in a future version of this tutorial. For now, we will simply inspect
                    the test results visually.
                </blockquote>
                <p>
                    We will use
                    <a href="http://www.testng.org/doc/index.html">TestNG</a>
                    for testing our service layer.
                    TestNG is a powerful testing framework, very similar to JUnit, but offers several
                    additional features, such as data-driven testing, to simplify the testing process.
                    In order to make our testing process efficient, we will not test the service layer
                    on JBoss. Instead, we will configure our tests to talk directly to the POJO services,
                    bypassing the EJB container completely. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    Copy the entire
                    <tt>test</tt>
                    directory located under
                    <tt>C:\timetracker-completed\core\src</tt>
                    to the corresponding
                    location in your own TimeTracker directory. After copying, delete the file
                    <tt>core\src\test\java\org\andromda\timetracker\service\TimeTrackingServiceTest.java</tt>
                    in your TimeTracker directory - we are not yet ready to compile this file.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Explore the
                    <tt>core\src\test</tt>
                    directory to get familiar with its contents.
                    Use the steps below to guide you along and to run the test:
                </p>
                <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                    <li>
                        <tt>UserServiceTest</tt>
                        is located under <tt>test\java\org\andromda\timetracker\service</tt>.
                        The test is pretty simple. The
                        <tt>initializeTestSuite()</tt>
                        method gets a
                        reference to the <tt>UserService</tt>. This reference is used by the
                        <tt>testGetAllUsers()</tt>
                        method to get all users and log them.
                        <tt>UserServiceTest</tt>
                        is shown below
                        for your convenience:
                        <source>
<![CDATA[
public class UserServiceTest {
    private Log logger = LogFactory.getLog(UserServiceTest.class);
    private UserService userService;

    @Configuration(beforeSuite=true)
    public void initializeTestSuite() {

        // Initialize ServiceLocator
        logger.info("Initializing ServiceLocator");
        ServiceLocator locator = ServiceLocator.instance();
        locator.init("testBeanRefFactory.xml", "beanRefFactory");

        // Initialize UserService
        logger.info("Initializing UserService");
        userService = locator.getUserService();
    }

    @Test
    public void testGetAllUsers() {

        logger.info("testGetAllUsers:");
        UserVO[] users = userService.getAllUsers();

        for (int i=0; i<users.length; i++) {
            logger.info(users.getUsername());
        }
    }
}
]]>
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>The directory
                        <tt>test\resources</tt>
                        contains configuration files needed for
                        testing.
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                <tt>log4j.xml</tt>
                                controls the logging behavior
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <tt>testBeanRefFactory.xml</tt>
                                enables the tests to directly talk to the services
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Execute the following command in the
                        <tt>C:\timetracker</tt>
                        directory to run
                        the test.
                        <br/>
                        <tt>mvn -f core/pom.xml test</tt>
                        <br/>
                        Note that
                        <tt>mvn install</tt>
                        will also run the test, but it will do everything
                        starting from regeneration of code. Since we have not changed the model after the
                        last code generation, we are simply asking Maven to run the tests in the core sub-project.
                        You will find that the test fails with the following message:
                        <source>
<![CDATA[
-------------------------------------------------------
 T E S T S
-------------------------------------------------------
Running TestSuite
Tests run: 2, Failures: 1, Errors: 0, Skipped: 1, Time elapsed: 0.872 sec <<< FAILURE!

Results :

Failed tests: 
  initializeTestSuite(org.andromda.timetracker.service.UserServiceTest)

Tests run: 2, Failures: 1, Errors: 0, Skipped: 1

[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[ERROR] BUILD FAILURE
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] There are test failures.

Please refer to /home/walter/test_workspace/timetracker/core/target/surefire-reports for the individual test results.
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] For more information, run Maven with the -e switch
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] Total time: 5 seconds
[INFO] Finished at: Sun Apr 03 16:24:55 BRT 2011
[INFO] Final Memory: 31M/604M
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
]]>
                        </source>
                        The test failed because initializeTestSuite() could not initialize the UserService
                        correctly. The reason for this is that Spring could not find a bean called 'sessionFactory'
                        which it was expecting. This problem will be fixed when we implement entities in
                        the middle-tier.
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="What's Next?">
                <p>
                    We now have our work cut out for us. We need to implement the
                    <tt>getAllUsers()</tt>
                    method so it returns a
                    <tt>UserVO[]</tt>
                    even if there are no users in the database.
                    Click <a href="userservice-implementation.html">here</a> to start our implementation.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
