<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="vancek@users.sourceforge.net">Vance Karimi</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - EJB3 - HowTo Entities</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Entities">
            <p>
                With entities we mean what is usually implemented using Entity Beans or EJB3 POJOs (i.e. a
                persistent entity like a Company or Person for example);
                in the EJB3 cartridge you will not need to worry about the underlying persistence technology, but
                you will probably want to know that EJB3 POJOs will be generated for the
                entities you model.  The EJB 3.0 container (i.e. JBoss) adopts a suitable configurable persistence 
                technology. (i.e Hibernate)
            </p>
            <p>
                In order to successfully generate a single entity it is sufficient to simply
                model a single class and assign it the <![CDATA[<<Entity>>]]> stereotype, this stereotype tells
                the EJB3 cartridge to treat this class as an entity.
            </p>
            <p>
                Let's start by modeling a package <code>org.andromda.test</code> and putting a class
                inside that package, give that class the name <code>Car</code>.  Now make sure that entity
                has the <![CDATA[<<Entity>>]]> stereotype, it depends on your UML tool how you need to do
                that exactly.
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="images/org/andromda/test/1/a/uml.gif"/>
            </p>
            <p>
                You can now try to generate code
                from your model and take a look at what is generated.  If you don't know how to generate code using
                AndroMDA then head on over to the
                <a href="../starting.html">getting started</a> guide (specificly the section explaining
                <a href="../starting.html#My_first_AndroMDA_project">how to setup your first AndroMDA project</a>).
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                Please note that until the EJB3 cartridge is included in the AndroMDAPP project, you 
                will not be able to generate your project structure using that generator.
            </p>
            <p>
                If everything went well, all code related to this class will have been generated into
                the <code>/core/entity/target/src</code> project subdirectory, no manual implementation will need
                to be added at this point.
            </p>
            <p>
                The EJB3 cartridge changes the conventional entity creation hierarchy.  Instead of generating
                an entity base class with an entity implementation class, you now have an entity embeddable super
                class with an entity class that inherits from this embeddable super class.  This is the case
                for simple non-inheriting hierarchies, however once you introduce inheritance, this changes.
                To find out more about inheritance, go to the <a href="howto9.html">inheritance</a> section.
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/a/CarEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/a/Car.java.txt"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                The class we have modelled does not have any properties, however, by default, AndroMDA creates the
                <code>id</code> attribute of type <code>datatype:Long</code> if no identifier (primary key)
                attribute has been modelled by the user.
                It is possible to override these settings in the
                <a href="../maven-andromda-plugin/properties.html#Defining_Namespace_Properties">namespace
                properties for Maven</a> or the
                <a href="../anttask.html#andromda-example">namespace properties for Ant</a>. Click
                <a href="../andromda-metafacades-uml/namespace.html">here</a>
                if you want to know more about the default namespace properties you can set.
            </p>
            <a name="Entity_Operations"/>
            <subsection name="Entity Operations">
                <p>
                    You may also model operations on an entity, this will generate them as methods in the resulting
                    Java subclass. Operations can be classifier scoped (<code>static</code> in Java) where they will
                    be underlined in UML diagrams as shown below.
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    Operations will not be defined in the embeddable superclass.  They will be defined in the 
                    inheriting subclass.  This has consequences when dealing with a multi-tier inheritance 
                    hierarchy.  Refer to the <a href="howto9.html">inheritance</a> howto for further information.
                    This also implis that operations are only added to the implementation class on the first
                    run of AndroMDA.  Operations defined in the UML model must be manually added to the
                    implementation class afterwards.  This shouldn't cause any issues as the developer would have
                    to define the operation implementation anyway to correspond to the abstract definition in
                    the embeddable superclass.  The primary purpose for this strategy is to avoid having to
                    annotate the entity operation with <code>@javax.persistence.Transient</code> annotation
                    in both the embeddable superclass and the inheriting implementation class.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="images/org/andromda/test/1/b/uml.gif"/>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/b/CarEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/b/Car.java.txt"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                Entity operations can also be Query operations.  This is discussed further in the
	                <a href="howto6.html">Query Howto</a>.  However, in general entities should NOT contain
	                any business logic.  The EJB3 cartridge, like other persistence modeling cartridges, 
	                uses the session facade pattern to contain business logic in session bean operations.
	            </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Entity_Relation_Table"/>
            <subsection name="Entity Relation Table">
                <p>
                    Your relational table's name which persists an entity is determined by default from the 
                    actual entity name.
                    To change the table name assignment in the <code>@javax.persistence.Table</code> annotation,
                    set the <code>@andromda.persistence.table</code> tag on the entity.
                    The same tag can be modelled on a Many-To-Many association relationship.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="images/org/andromda/test/1/c/uml.gif"/>
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/c/CarEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/c/Car.java.txt"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Primary_Key_Identifiers"/>
            <subsection name="Primary Key - Identifier">
                <p>
                    To assign an entity's attribute as a primary key, you must assign the <![CDATA[<<Identifier>>]]>
                    stereotype to it.  If this identifier is not part of a composite primary key, then
                    <code>@javax.persistence.Id</code> annotation is added to the attribute getter method.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="images/org/andromda/test/1/d/uml.gif"/>
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/d/CarEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/d/Car.java.txt"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
                <p>
                    An entity identifier attribute's table generator can be modelled via the
                    <code>@andromda.persistence.generator.type</code> tag on the identifier attribute ONLY.
                    This is used to model the primary key generation strategy associated with the
                    <code>@javax.persistence.Id</code> annotation for an entity attribute.
                    Currenly, the EJB3 cartridge supports:
                    <ul>
                        <li>The default type is <code>AUTO</code></li>
                        <li><code>TABLE</code></li>
                        <li><code>SEQUENCE</code></li>
                        <li><code>NONE</code></li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The table generator name can be set using the <code>@andromda.persistence.generator.name</code> tag.
                    This must be a unique name which is referenced by one or more classes to be the generator
                    for an entity bean.  By setting the <code>@andromda.persistence.generator.source.name</code> tag,
                    you can specify either the table name that stores the generated ids or the sequence name
                    which is the name of the database sequence object used to get the ids.  For table generator types,
                    you must specify the <code>@andromda.persistence.generator.pkcolumn.value</code> tag which defines
                    the primary key value in the generator table to identify the specified generated value from 
                    other values.  For sequence generator types, you can specify the initial value of the 
                    sequence using <code>@andromda.persistence.generator.initial.value</code> tag and the 
                    allocation size by <code>@andromda.persistence.generator.allocation.size</code> tag.  The allocation
                    size sets the amount to increment by when allocating id numbers from the sequence generator.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Unique_Attributes"/>
            <subsection name="Unique Attributes">
                <p>
                    In case you want an entity's attribute to be unique for all instances of that entity's type you
                    should assign the <![CDATA[<<Unique>>]]> stereotype to it.  This will define the corresponding
                    unique element in the <code>@javax.persistence.Column</code> annotation.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Attribute_Fetch_Type"/>
            <subsection name="Attribute Fetch Type">
                <p>
                    By default, the EJB3 cartridge and EJB 3.0 spec defines an attribute fetch type as eagerly
                    fetched.  To specify an attribute as lazy fetched, we hint to the persistence container 
                    by modelling the <code>@andromda.persistence.fetch.type</code> tag on the attribute.  Under
                    normal circumstances, you do not need to specify this tag.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Transient_Attribute"/>
            <subsection name="Transient Attribute">
                <p>
                    To indicate an attribute as transient (not persisted by the persistence container), you
                    model the <![CDATA[<<Transient>>]]> stereotype on the attribute.  This adds the
                    <code>@javax.persistence.Transient</code> annotation to the attribute.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Version_Attribute"/>
            <subsection name="Version Attribute">
                <p>
                    To specify an attribute as a version attribute, where it becomes the optimistic lock value
                    for an entity, you model the <![CDATA[<<Version>>]]> stereotype on this attribute.  
                    This can only apply to ONE attribute per class.  Attributes with this stereotype
                    will not be updated by the persistent container.  The attribute can only of the following types:
                    <ul>
                        <li>int</li>
                        <li>short</li>
                        <li>long</li>
                        <li>Integer</li>
                        <li>Short</li>
                        <li>Long</li>
                        <li>Timestamp</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Attribute_Multiplicity"/>
            <subsection name="Attribute Multiplicity">
                <p>
                    It's possible to configure the multiplicity of an entity's attribute, by setting it to
                    <code>[0..1]</code> an attribute is not required and is allowed to be set to
                    <code>null</code>; setting the multiplicity to a value greater than <code>0</code>
                    means the attribute is required.  In the former case the nullable element will be set to
                    <code>true</code> for the <code>@javax.persistence.Column</code> annotation on the
                    attribute.  The following class assigns a multiplicity of [0..1] to the <code>name</code>
                    attribute which means <code>name</code> can be null.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="images/org/andromda/test/1/e/uml.gif"/>
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/e/CarEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/e/Car.java.txt"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
                <p>
                    Please note that some UML tools have a default multiplicity value for attributes when not
                    specified by the user, these default values may differ from tool to tool.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Constant_Attribute"/>
            <subsection name="Constant Attributes">
                <p>
                    To define static constants within an entity POJO (constants that are not resource injections),
                    model a classifier scoped attribute (<code>static</code> in Java).  These attributes are defined
                    as static with public visibility.  Constants must define a default value in the model.
                    The following entity defines 3 constants for type.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="images/org/andromda/test/1/f/uml.gif"/>
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/f/CarEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/f/Car.java.txt"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Nullable_Parameters"/>
            <subsection name="Nullable Parameters">
                <p>
                    If you want an operation to have a parameter which is allowed to be <code>null</code> then simply
                    assign the <![CDATA[<<Nullable>>]]> stereotype to that parameter. By default service
                    operations throw an exception when a <code>null</code> argument has been passed.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It is possible to globally disable checking for <code>null</code> arguments, so you will never
                    need to specify the <![CDATA[<<Nullable>>]]> stereotype; to do so just specify the
                    <code>parameterRequiredCheck</code> namespace property to have the <code>false</code> value.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="LOB_CLOB_Attribute"/>
            <subsection name="LOB/CLOB Attributes">
                <p>
                    An attribute can be specified as either a BLOB or CLOB field.  This is modelled by assigning
                    the <code>@andromda.persistence.lob.type</code> tag to the required type.  This will add
                    the <code>@javax.persistence.Lob</code> annotation to the entity attribute.
                </p>
                <p>
                    For BLOB fields, the attribute type must be modelled as one of:
                    <ul>
                        <li>Byte[]</li>
                        <li>Serializable type</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    For CLOB fields, the attribute type must be modelled as one of:
                    <ul>
                        <li>char[]</li>
                        <li>Character[]</li>
                        <li>String</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The default fetch type for a LOB typed attribute is lazy.  To assign a LOB attribute
                    to be eagerly fetched, model the <code>@andromda.persistence.fetch.type</code> tag on the
                    attribute.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="images/org/andromda/test/1/g/uml.gif"/>
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/g/CarEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/g/Car.java.txt"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
                <p>
                    This example models the type attribute as a CLOB, since it's of type String and
                    sets the fetch type for the attribute to eagerly fetch.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Column_Specifics"/>
            <subsection name="Column Specifics">
                <p>
                    Here is an example of some of the tagged values available to model on
                    entity attributes.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="images/org/andromda/test/1/h/uml.gif"/>
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/h/CarEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto1/h/Car.java.txt"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
                <p>
                    To change the default naming schema for the relational table column, model the
                    <code>@andromda.persistence.column</code> tag on the attribute.
                </p>
                <p>
                    You can set the column length for the relational database table for string based columns 
                    by modelling the <code>@andromda.persistence.column.length</code> tag on the attribute.
                </p>
                <p>
                    If the column is defined as a decimal column (i.e. float or double), you can model the precision
                    and scale of the column by setting <code>@andromda.persistence.column.precision</code> tag to set 
                    the precision of the decimal column and/or <code>@andromda.persistence.column.scale</code> tag
                    to set the scale for a decimal column, on the attribute.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In order to change the creation DDL for the column in the relational table, you can model
                    <code>@andromda.persistence.column.definition</code> tag on the attribute.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Listener_Callback"/>
            <subsection name="Listener Callback">
                <p>
                    In some cases, setting up lifecycle event callbacks for the entity beans can be quite
                    useful.  The EJB3 cartridge provides the facility to define these callback methods
                    in the listener class.  This class if NOT generate by default.  To find out more information,
                    click on <a href="howto14.html">Listener Callback</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                In the next section we'll learn about entity relationships, click
                <a href="howto2.html">here</a> to continue.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>