<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="vancek@users.sourceforge.net">Vance Karimi</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - EJB3 - HowTo Service</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Services">
            <p>
                A common strategy to shield the presentation tier from the persistence tier is to model
                the services in between.  These services implement the business logic in the application tier.
                In the EJB3 cartridge, these services are stateless or stateful session beans.
            </p>
            <p>
                To create a service you just create another class and model the <![CDATA[<<Service>>]]> stereotype
                on this class. 
            </p>
            <p>
                Most of the time you only model operations in these services which represent
                the operations that can be called remotely (default view type).  The EJB3 cartridge allows you to
                specify <i>local</i> operation or even both.  These operations are the <b>API</b> of your 
                application's back-end.
            </p>
            <p>
                The following illustrates the use of a service bean that operates on the 2 entities.
                Notice how we have modelled dependencies from the service to the entities.  This will render 
                the getter accessor to the DAOs of both entities in the service and inject the corresponding
                DAO (stateless session bean containing CRUD API for entity).
            </p>
            <p>
                Drawing these dependencies indicates the need to access the persistent storage 
                of entities via the persistence entity manager injected in the DAO that handle this task and
                eliminates much of the complexity.
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="images/org/andromda/test/3/a/uml.gif"/>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/CarEmbeddable.java"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/Car.java"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/CarDao.java"><code>CarDao.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/CarDaoBase.java"><code>CarDaoBase.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/CarDaoImpl.java"><code>CarDaoImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/CarDaoException.java"><code>CarDaoException.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/Person.java"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/PersonDao.java"><code>PersonDao.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/PersonDaoBase.java"><code>PersonDaoBase.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/PersonDaoImpl.java"><code>PersonDaoImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/PersonDaoException.java"><code>PersonDaoException.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/RentalServiceBean.java"><code>RentalServiceBean.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/RentalServiceRemote.java"><code>RentalServiceRemote.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/RentalServiceDelegate.java"><code>RentalServiceDelegate.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/RentalServiceBase.java"><code>RentalServiceBase.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/a/RentalServiceException.java"><code>RentalServiceException.java</code></a></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                There are a few other things you can do with these services, these features will be presented
                in the sections ahead.
            </p>
            <p>
                The <code>RentalServiceBase.java</code> injects the <code>javax.ejb.SessionContext</code> by
                default and makes this available for use in the subclass via the <code>context</code> protected
                attribute.
            </p>
            <p>
                The default persistence context is injected into the Entity Manager.  This is defined via the
                <code>@javax.persistence.PersistenceContext</code> annotation in <code>RentalServiceBase.java</code>.
                The <code>unitName</code> property matches the entity manager name in <code>persistence.xml</code>
                and is determined from the project name for the default persistence context.
            </p>
            <a name="Session_Type"/>
            <subsection name="Session Type">
                <p>
                    By default, if a session bean does not have any instance attributes, then it is by definition
                    a <code>Stateless</code> session bean since there are no attributes to maintain state between
                    bean method invocations.
                </p>
                <p>
                    If you model an <code>instance</code> scoped attribute on the bean, the EJB3 cartridge will
                    declare this session bean as a <code>Stateful</code> session bean in the ejb-jar.xml
                    deployment descriptor.
                </p>
                <p>
                    If you wish, you can override this feature by modelling the <code>@andromda.service.type</code>
                    tagged value on the session bean class.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="View_Interface"/>
            <subsection name="View Interfaces">
                <p>
                    By default, the EJB3 cartridge creates and registers a remote view interface which implies 
                    that the client view of the session bean is location-independent.  In this case, the session bean
                    and the client can exist in different JVMs on the same or different machines.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To create a local view interface and register this with the container, you model the
                    <code>@andromda.ejb.viewType</code> on the session bean operation or at the class level
                    of the session bean.  Your options are:
                    <ul>
                        <li>remote - This is the default and doesn't need to be specified</li>
                        <li>local - Assigns to class/operation to the local view interface</li>
                        <li>both - This class/operations are available via the local and remote interfaces</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Transactions"/>
            <subsection name="Transactions">
                <p>
                    To declare the transactional nature of session bean business methods, you can model
                    the <code>@andromda.ejb.transaction.type</code> tagged value on the session bean business 
                    methods individually, or on the session bean class.  To find out more information, click on
                    <a href="howto15.html">Transaction</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Security"/>
            <subsection name="Security">
                <p>
                    The EJB3 cartridge provides the ability to set security constraints to allow
                    role based security when accessing and invoking session bean business operations.
                    To find out more information, click on <a href="howto8.html">Security</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Environment_Entry_Injection"/>
            <subsection name="Environment Entry Injections">
                <p>
                    To inject an environment entry resource value, model a service attribute with 
                    <code>classifer</code> scope
                    and set the attribute stereotype to <![CDATA[<<EnvEntry>>]]>.  The environment
                    entries will be defined in the session bean class and configured in the ejb-jar.xml 
                    deployment descriptor.
                    You must define a default value for these attributes in the model.  Refer to 
                    <a href="howto11.html#Simple_Environment_Entry_Injection">Environment Entry Injections</a> 
                    for further information. 
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Nullable_Parameter"/>
            <subsection name="Nullable Parameters">
                <p>
                    If you want an operation to have a parameter which is allowed to be <code>null</code> then simply
                    assign the <![CDATA[<<Nullable>>]]> stereotype to that parameter.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Session_Delegate"/>
            <subsection name="Session Delegate">
                <p>
                    As you saw in the example in this howto, a session bean delegate class is generated for
                    every session bean.  A client invokes the session bean's business methods via the delegate
                    class, acting like a proxy via the service locator class.  Both the service delegate and
                    service locator classes are regenerated every time AndroMDA is run.  You can find out
                    more information about session delegates from <a href="howto12.html">here</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Listener_Callback"/>
            <subsection name="Listener Callback">
                <p>
                    In some cases, setting up lifecycle event callbacks for the session bean can be quite
                    useful.  The EJB3 cartridge provides the facility to define these callback methods
                    in the listener class.  This class if NOT generate by default.  To find out more information,
                    click on <a href="howto14.html">Listener Callback</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Interceptors"/>
            <subsection name="Interceptors">
                <p>
                    You can intercept calls to session bean business method invocations via an interceptor class.  
                    By default,  this class is NOT generated.  To find out more information, click on
                    <a href="howto13.html">Interceptors</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="JNDI_Bindings"/>
            <subsection name="JNDI Bindings">
                <p>
                    The container will supply default JNDI bindings for the remote and local interface of 
                    the session bean.  By default, JBoss will use <code>ejbName/local</code> and 
                    <code>ejbName/remote</code> for the local and remote interfaces, respectively.  Other providers
                    will do something similar.
                </p>
                <p>
                    You can override the default JNDI bindings.  To specify the JNDI name of the local interface
                    bound to the session bean, model the <code>@andromda.service.jndi.local</code> tagged value on
                    the session bean class.  To specify the JNDI name of the remote interface bound to
                    the session bean, model the <code>@andromda.service.jndi.remote</code> tagged value
                    on the session bean class.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Persistence_Context_Entity_Manager"/>
            <subsection name="Persistence Context Entity Manager">
                <p>
                    The EJB3 cartridge derives a default persistence context associated with the default
                    entity manager for every session bean.  The persistence context <code>unitName</code>
                    property is determined via the <code>persistenceContextUnitName</code> namespace property
                    which is provided via your application <code>andromda.xml</code> descriptor. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    Every session bean provides the facility to override the default persistence context
                    annotation declaration by modelling the following tagged values on the session bean class:
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <code>@andromda.service.persistence.context.unit.name</code>
                            Override the unit name for the default persistence context.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <code>@andromda.service.persistence.context.unit.type</code>
                            Specifiy whether a trasaction scoped or extended scoped persistence context
                            is required for the persistence context associated with the default entity manager.
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    To inject another persistence context, associated with a different entity manager, you need
                    to model a new class with the <![CDATA[<<PersistenceContext>>]]> stereotype and draw
                    a dependency from the session bean to the this new class.  The entity manager attribute
                    declaration will use the class name as the attribute name.  To define the properties of
                    the persistence context annotation, you need to model the above tagged values on
                    this new class.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The following example shows a new persistence context <code>securityEntityManager</code>.
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <img src="images/org/andromda/test/3/b/uml.gif"/>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
                        <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/CarEmbeddable.java"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/Car.java"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/CarDao.java"><code>CarDao.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/CarDaoBase.java"><code>CarDaoBase.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/CarDaoImpl.java"><code>CarDaoImpl.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/CarDaoException.java"><code>CarDaoException.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/Person.java"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/PersonDao.java"><code>PersonDao.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/PersonDaoBase.java"><code>PersonDaoBase.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/PersonDaoImpl.java"><code>PersonDaoImpl.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/PersonDaoException.java"><code>PersonDaoException.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/RentalServiceBean.java"><code>RentalServiceBean.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/RentalServiceRemote.java"><code>RentalServiceRemote.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/RentalServiceDelegate.java"><code>RentalServiceDelegate.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/RentalServiceBase.java"><code>RentalServiceBase.java</code></a></li>
                        <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/RentalServiceException.java"><code>RentalServiceException.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto3/b/persistence.xml"><code>persistence.xml</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                Notice that <code>SecondaryEntityManager</code> has defined the 
	                <code>@andromda.service.persistence.context.datasource</code> tagged value specifiying the
	                JNDI name of the JDBC datasource used in this persistence context.  You can specify this tag 
	                on a class where the <![CDATA[<<PersistenceContext>>]]> stereotype has been modelled.
	            </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="EJB_Injections"/>
            <subsection name="EJB Injections">
                <p>
                    To inject another session bean into the current session bean, simply model a dependency
                    from the source session bean (which will contain the <code>@javax.annotation.EJB</code>
                    annotation) to the target session bean.  For more information on dependency injections, 
                    click <a href="howto11.html#Dependency_Injection">here</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="JMS_Injections"/>
            <subsection name="JMS Injections">
                <p>
                    The EJB3 cartridge provides the facility to develop message driven beans.  To find out
                    more information, click on <a href="howto10.html">message driven beans</a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Once you have modelled the MDB with <![CDATA[<<MessageDriven>>]]> stereotype,
                    you can model a dependency from the source session bean to the MDB.  This will render
                    the appropriate <code>@javax.annotation.Resource</code> injections associated with JMS specific 
                    objects such as <code>QueueConnectionFactory</code>, <code>TopicConnectionFactory</code> and
                    the <code>Destination</code> object.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="EJB_Timer_Service"/>
            <subsection name="EJB Timer Service">
                <p>
                    To setup a timeout callback and use the EJB Timer Service, just model the
                    <![CDATA[<<Timeout>>]]> stereotype on a session bean operation.  This will
                    render the <code>@javax.ejb.Timeout</code> annotation on the operation.  Every session
                    bean injects <code>SessionContext</code> with the <code>@javax.annotation.Resource</code>
                    annotation which allows registration of the timer with the EJB Timer Service.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                In the next section we'll learn about composite primary keys, click
                <a href="howto4.html">here</a> to continue.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
