<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="vancek@users.sourceforge.net">Vance Karimi</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - EJB3 - Interceptors</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Interceptor">
            <p>
                Adding custom written interceptors is very easy using the EJB3 cartridge.  The following sections
                will provide you with enough detail to add your custom made interceptors to session and
                message-driven beans.  It discusses default, class and method interceptors.
            </p>
            <p>
                All interceptors are configured through the ejb-jar deployment descriptor.  The EJB3 cartridges
                does NOT use annotations to define interceptors and their exclusions.
            </p>
            <p>
                The following example shows how to model a default interceptor as well as 2 class level
                interceptors for the <code>RentalService</code> bean.  Method level interceptor are
                modelled in the same fashion, but a dependency is drawn from the session bean method.
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="images/org/andromda/test/13/a/uml.gif"/>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/CarEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/Car.java.txt"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/CarType.java.txt"><code>CarType.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/PersonEmbeddable.java.txt"><code>PersonEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/Person.java.txt"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/ServiceLocator.java.txt"><code>ServiceLocator.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/RentalServiceBean.java.txt"><code>RentalServiceBean.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/RentalServiceRemote.java.txt"><code>RentalServiceRemote.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/RentalServiceDelegate.java.txt"><code>RentalServiceDelegate.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/RentalServiceBeanImpl.java.txt"><code>RentalServiceBeanImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/RentalServiceException.java.txt"><code>RentalServiceException.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/RentalException.java.txt"><code>RentalException.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/ejb-jar.xml.txt"><code>ejb-jar.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/jboss.xml.txt"><code>jboss.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/persistence.xml.txt"><code>persistence.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/DefaultInterceptor.java.txt"><code>DefaultInterceptor.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/LogInterceptor.java.txt"><code>LogInterceptor.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto13/a/AdminCheckerInterceptor.java.txt"><code>AdminCheckerInterceptor.java</code></a></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <a name="Default_Interceptors"/>
            <subsection name="Default Interceptor">
                <p>
                    A default interceptor is invoked any time a business method of any bean within that
                    deployment is invoked, unless default interceptors have been excluded on beans or
                    business methods of beans.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To define a default interceptor for your deployment, model the standard
                    <![CDATA[<<Interceptor>>]]> stereotype on a class and specify the
                    <code>@andromda.service.interceptor.default</code> tagged value as true.
                    Since this interceptor is invoked
                    for all business methods of all beans, you do not need to model any dependencies on it.
                    The cartridge will generate the class with the necessary interceptor operation and
                    corresponding annotations within the interceptor class.  It will also add the
                    <code>interceptor-binding</code> attribute to the <code>assembly-descriptor</code> element
                    of the ejb-jar deployment descriptor.
                </p>
                <p>
                    You can model as many default interceptor as you require, but at this stage, the ordering
                    of default interceptors is not guaranteed.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Class_Level_Interceptor"/>
            <subsection name="Class Level Interceptor">
                <p>
                    Class level interceptors are invoked when business methods of the modelled class are invoked,
                    unless class level interceptors have been excluded on business methods.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To define a class level interceptor, model the <![CDATA[<<Interceptor>>]]> stereotype on
                    a class.  You must model a dependency from a source bean to this target class level interceptor
                    so that the cartridge knows to configure this interceptor at the class level in the ejb-jar
                    deployment descriptor.
                </p>
                <p>
                    If you would like to define multiple class level interceptors, then to guarantee the ordering
                    in which these interceptors are invoked, you must draw a dependency from the first interceptor
                    to the second interceptor and so forth.  This will chain the interceptors and allow the 
                    cartridge to configure them correctly in the ejb-jar deployment descriptor.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Method_Level_Interceptor"/>
            <subsection name="Method Level Interceptor">
                <p>
                    Method level interceptors are very much similar to class level interceptors, but they are
                    bound to a specific business method within a bean.  This means that they are only invoked
                    when the modelled business method of a bean are invoked.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To define a method level interceptor, model the <![CDATA[<<Interceptor>>]]> stereotype on
                    a class.  You must model a dependency from a bean method to this target method level interceptor
                    so that the cartridge knows to configure this interceptor at the method level in the ejb-jar
                    deployment descriptor.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Chaining method level interceptors is exactly the same process as for class level interceptors.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Interceptor_Ordering"/>
            <subsection name="Interceptor Ordering">
                <p>
                    The following shows the ordering of default, class and method level interceptors.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Default Interceptors - Invoked before all other interceptors</li>
                        <li>
                            Class Level Interceptors - Invoked in the chain after default interceptors and before
                            method level interceptors.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Method Level Interceptors - Invoked in the chain after all class level interceptors.
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The above are the ordering for externally defined interceptors.  If you define
                    class interceptor methods within your bean, then these are the last interceptors
                    to be invoked.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Interceptor_Exclusion"/>
            <subsection name="Interceptor Exclusions">
                <p>
                    The EJB3 cartridge allows you to exclude default interceptors for beans and bean methods.
                    It also allows you to exclude class level interceptors for bean methods.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To exclude the default interceptors, model the 
                    <code>@andromda.service.interceptor.excludeDefault</code> tagged value.  If this is applied to
                    a bean class, then the interceptor will be ignored for all methods of the bean class.  If
                    it is modelled on a business method of a bean, then invocation of that business method
                    will NOT trigger invocation of the defined default interceptors.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To exclude class level interceptors, model the
                    <code>@andromda.service.interceptor.excludeClass</code> tagged value on business method
                    of beans.  This will prevent the container from invoking the defined class level interceptor
                    when the associated bean method is invoked.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Interceptor_Tips"/>
            <subsection name="Interceptor Tips">
                <p>
                    In situations where you have an inheritance hierarchy, interceptor methods from the super
                    class are always invoked first.  The exception to this rule is the case where the interceptor
                    has been overridden, regardless of whether the overriding method is defined as an 
                    interceptor.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Once the interceptors have been generated, they will never be overwritten.  This way, you
                    can add your implementation for the interceptor and call <code>InvocationContext.proceed()</code>
                    to continue to call the next interceptor.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Similar to bean classes, interceptor classes enjoy the benefits of dependency injection 
                    in much the same way.
                    You can inject resources using the <code>@Resource</code> annotation or an
                    entity manager using the <code>@PersistenceContext</code> annotation.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                For usage of lifecycle callbacks in entity, session and message-driven beans
                click <a href="howto14.html">here</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
