<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="vancek@users.sourceforge.net">Vance Karimi</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - EJB3 - HowTo Relationships</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Relationships">
            <p>
                Most of the entities that appear in real applications have relationships with other
                entities; consider the simple case of a person owning a car. Here we say
                <code>Person</code> has an <code>owning</code> relationship with the <code>Car</code>, and from
                the perspective of the person there can be any number of cars that are owned, denoted in UML
                by <code>[0..*]</code> at the car's end.
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                Make sure the association ends are <code>public</code>; some tools allow to specify the 
                visibility of an association end.
            </p>
            <p>
                In UML, relationships are modeled using associations, and associations themselves have different
                properties, which will be discussed here.
            </p>
            <p>
                Let's model another entity, call it <code>Person</code> and give it a few attributes,
                just make sure you give them one of the platform independent datatypes that can be mapped
                onto a platform specific datatype (you can find them in the <code>datatype</code> package).
            </p>
            <p>
                Draw an association between both entities you have just modeled. Set the multiplicity at the end
                of the car to <code>[0..*]</code> and name the other end <code>'owner'</code>.
                Run AndroMDA again on your model, this is what you should see:
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="images/org/andromda/test/2/a/uml.gif"/>
            </p>
            <p>
                In this example we have added two attributes: 
                <ul>
                    <li>name of type <code>datatype::String</code></li>
                    <li>birthDate of type <code>datatype::Date</code></li>
                </ul>
                Please note that also for this entity an identifier will be added by default. 
                If you explicitely want to add an identifier you should add the <![CDATA[<<Identifier>>]]> 
                stereotype to an attribute. Refer to <a href="howto1.html">Entities</a> for more information.
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/a/CarEmbeddable.java"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/a/Car.java"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/a/PersonEmbeddable.java"><code>PersonEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/a/Person.java"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                As you can see the relationships have been generated in the embeddable superclasses.  Since both
                ends of the association are navigable, we have a bi-directional relationship.
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p>Person.getCars() : Collection</p>
                        <p>
                            A One-To-Many relationship has been defined from the
                            Person entity to the Car entity.  This adds the <code>@javax.persistence.OneToMany</code> 
                            annotation to the getter method and sets the <code>mappedBy</code> property to 
                            <code>'owner'</code>. The <code>mappedBy</code> property indicates the other end of 
                            the association is the owning side of the relationship.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>Car.getOwner() : Person</p>
                        <p>
                            A Many-To-One relationship has been defined from the
                            Car entity to the Person entity.  This adds the <code>@javax.persistence.ManyToOne</code>
                            annotation to the getter method of the Car entity.  Since the multiplicity on the
                            Person end of the association is set to 1, the annotation has defined the
                            <code>optional</code> property to <code>false</code> which indicates non-null entries
                            cannot exists in this foreign key column in the relational database table.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            Since the Car entity end is the owning end, the <code>@javax.persistence.JoinColumn</code>
                            annotation has been defined with a <code>name</code> property.  
                            This annotation is used to indicate a mapped column for joining an entity association. 
                            The <code>name</code> property defines the foreign key column name.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
                By default AndroMDA will look at the multiplicity to generate a good name for the relationship,
                a few examples where the multiplicity is greater than one:
                <ul>
                    <li>car: cars</li>
                    <li>property: properties</li>
                    <li>toy: toys</li>
                    <li>animal: animals</li>
                    <li>bus: busses</li>
                </ul>
                You can override these names by adding your own names to the association ends, in our example
                you might set the name of the association end at the side of the person to <code>person</code>,
                this will emit the following output during generation:
                <ul>
                    <li>Person.getCars() : Collection</li>
                    <li>Car.getPerson() : Person</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <subsection name="Cascading">
                <p>
                    You can set the cascade option on all association ends by modelling the
                    <code>@andromda.persistence.cascade.type</code> tagged value on the target association end.
                    The cascadable options are:
                    <ul>
                        <li>ALL</li>
                        <li>PERSIST</li>
                        <li>MERGE</li>
                        <li>REMOVE</li>
                        <li>REFRESH</li>
                    </ul>
                    You can set multiple cascade options on the target association end which will define
                    the <code>cascade</code> property of the annotation as array.
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <img src="images/org/andromda/test/2/b/uml.gif"/>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/b/CarEmbeddable.java"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/b/Car.java"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/b/PersonEmbeddable.java"><code>PersonEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/b/Person.java"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Fetch Type">
                <p>
                    The fetch type tagged value <code>@andromda.persistence.fetch.type</code> can be modelled on
                    all association ends.  To set the fetch type on an end, you model this tagged value on
                    the target association end.  The following default are the default fetch types for the
                    available relationships:
                    <ul>
                        <li>Many-To-One : EAGER</li>
                        <li>One-To-Many : LAZY</li>
                        <li>One-To-One : EAGER</li>
                        <li>Many-To-Many : LAZY</li>
                    </ul>
                    Therefore, you only need to specify the latter tagged value if you wish to change
                    the fetch type property from the default.
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <img src="images/org/andromda/test/2/c/uml.gif"/>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/c/CarEmbeddable.java"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/c/Car.java"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/c/PersonEmbeddable.java"><code>PersonEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/c/Person.java"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Ordering Collection Valued Association">
                <p>
                    You can order the elements of a collection valued association by modelling the
                    <code>@andromda.persistence.orderBy</code> tagged value on the target association end.
                    A few notes to consider:
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            If <code>ASC</code> or <code>DESC</code> is not specified, <code>ASC</code> order is
                            assumed.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            If the ordering tagged value is modelled but no ordering element is supplied, this
                            renders an empty <code>@javax.persistence.OrderBy</code> annotation which indicates
                            to the container to assume ordering by primary key as per the spec.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            The property used in the order by clause must correspond to a persistent field of
                            the associated class and that corresponding column must support comparison operators.
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
	            <p>
	                <img src="images/org/andromda/test/2/d/uml.gif"/>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/d/CarEmbeddable.java"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/d/Car.java"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/d/PersonEmbeddable.java"><code>PersonEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/d/Person.java"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Join Table for Many-To-Many Relationship">
                <p>
                    For a Many-To-Many association, the <code>@javax.persistence.JoinTable</code> annotation
                    is specified on the OWNING side of the association.  This is determined by modelling the
                    <code>owning</code> side as an aggregation or composition.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The join table name is defined by default to be the table name of the primary table of owning 
                    side concatenated with the table name of the primary table of the inverse side.  
                    You can override the <code>name</code> property by modelling the 
                    <code>@andromda.persistence.table</code> tagged value on the assocation.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Aggregation and Composition">
	            <p>
	                To model the owning side of a One-To-One or Many-To-Many bidirectional relationship, you
	                indicate that end (the owning end) of the relationship as an <code>aggregate</code> or
	                <code>composite</code> end. You should use aggregation when an entity is part of 
	                another one but the latter one does not need the former to exist.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                By default, the EJB3 cartridge enables the following via the 
	                <code>compositionDefinesEagerLoading</code> namespace property.  These are employed if no
	                <code>@andromda.persistence.fetch.type</code> tagged value exists.
	                <ul>
	                    <li>aggregation: lazy-loaded, no cascade</li>
	                    <li>composition: eager-loaded, cascade update (cascade option not yet implemented)</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                The following example illustrates the Many-To-Many bidirection relationship between
	                <code>Car</code> and <code>Person</code> entities.  The aggregate end on the
	                <code>Person</code> entity indicates that <code>Person</code> is the owning entity.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <img src="images/org/andromda/test/2/e/uml.gif"/>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
	                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
	                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                <ul>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/e/CarEmbeddable.java"><code>CarEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="impl"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/e/Car.java"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/e/PersonEmbeddable.java"><code>PersonEmbeddable.java</code></a></li>
	                    <li class="gen"><a href="src/org/andromda/test/howto2/e/Person.java"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
	                </ul>
	            </p>
	        </subsection>
            <p class="highlight">
                Don't forget to properly set the multiplicity on the association ends and whether and end
                is navigable.  This will ensure the proper code is generated.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                In the next section we'll learn about services, click
                <a href="howto3.html">here</a> to continue.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
