<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>AndroMDA - EJB3 - JBoss Seam Integration</title>
        <author email="vancek@users.sourceforge.net">Vance Karimi</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="JBoss Seam Integration">
            <p>
                The EJB3 cartridge now has the ability to enable your EJB 3.0 components as Seam components.
                The JBoss Online Booking example tries to illustrate how you can use the EJB3 cartridge with
                Seam enabled features.
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                Please note that the EJB3 cartridge will NOT generate any view components.  A Seam cartridge is
                planned which will do this job and can be used with the EJB3 cartridge.
            </p>
            <p>
                This howto will presume you have an understanding of the JBoss Seam framework.  Read about
                <a href="http://labs.jboss.com/jbossseam">JBoss Seam</a> and try out the examples.
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                Remember: You must set the 
                <a href="namespace.html#seamEnabled">seamEnabled</a> and 
                <a href="namespace.html#persistenceProviderExtensions">persistenceProviderExtensions</a>
                namespace properties such that Seam specific project settings are generated and 
                Hibernate validator specific annotations are generated.
            </p>
            <a name="Seam_Version"/>
            <subsection name="Seam Version">
                <p>
                    The cartridge will generate the Seam components using <b>JBoss Seam 1.1.0-GA</b>.  Read
                    the <a href="http://labs.jboss.com/portal/jbossseam/gettingstarted">JBoss Seam Getting Started</a>
                    guide to learn how to download and setup your Seam environment, plus play around with the examples.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Project_Generator"/>
            <subsection name="Project Generator">
                <p>
                    The AndroMDApp project generator from <code>3.3-SNAPSHOT</code> in CVS onwards supports JBoss Seam 
                    for EJB3 and JSF for web project only.  As long as you select these components, all the necessary
                    JBoss Seam properties will be enabled in your project.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Once you run the project generator 
                    <i>mvn org.andromda.maven.plugins:andromdapp-maven-plugin:generate</i>, you must select
                    EJB 3.0 as the persistence framework and JSF as the web framework.  You will then be prompted
                    to enable JBoss Seams.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Seam_Profile"/>
            <subsection name="Seam Profile">
                <p>
                    There exists a separate Seam profile that needs to be imported into your project UML.  This profile
                    contains the Seam specific tags and stereotypes you need to model on your components.
                </p>
                <p>
                    You can
                    get this profile by if you have checked out the latest <i>andromda-plugins</i> project from 
                    <b>HEAD</b> (follow <a href="installation.html">Installation</a>) and build the
                    <b>Profiles</b> project.  Once this is done, the profile will be copied to your M2 repository
                    under <i>M2_REPO/org/andromda/profiles/uml14/andromda-profile-seam/VERSION/</i>.
                    You can then import this <i>andromda-profile-seam-VERSION.xml.zip</i> profile into your
                    model to utilize the Seam components.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Seam_Quick_Start_Guide"/>
            <subsection name="Seam Quick Start Guide">
                <p>
                    Because we are not going to replace the existing JBoss tutorials here, it is assumed you have
                    followed the links above to understand the Seam framework and where you need the appropriate
                    annotation or metadata.  The following sections will briefly explain the more common Seam 
                    stereotypes and tagged values. You can always find more documentation on these within
                    the <i>andromda-profile-seam</i>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Seam Component">
				<p>
					Every entity or session bean which is to be modeled as a Seam component must have an 
					extra <![CDATA[<<Seam>>]]> stereotype, along with the traditional <![CDATA[<<Entity>>]]> 
                    or <![CDATA[<<Service>>]]> stereotypes.  However, now you can also model a value object with
                    the <![CDATA[<<ValueObject>>]]> stereotype as a Seam component in the same way.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Component Name">
				<p>
					If you model the <![CDATA[<<Seam>>]]> stereotype, the <![CDATA[@Name]]> annotation will be 
                    generated with the value being the class name. You can override this by modeling the 
					<![CDATA[andromda_seam_component_name]]> tagged value.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Component Scope">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[andromda_seam_component_scope]]> tagged value on Seam component classes provides
                    enumerated values to set the scope of the component.  The default scope depends on the component
                    type.
				</p>
                <p>
                    If you have modeled roles for the component, then you can use the 
                    <![CDATA[andromda_seam_component_role_scope]]> tagged value where the list of scopes must be
                    in the same order as the role names.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Logger">
				<p>
					To make use of the JBoss Seam logger, you can model a component attribute of <i>Object</i>
                    type with stereotype <![CDATA[<<Logger>>]]>.  You can further specify the name of the log
                    category with <![CDATA[andromda_seam_bijection_logger_value]]> tagged value.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Bijection">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[@In]]> and <![CDATA[@Out]]> annotations for bijection are rendered on attributes 
                    defined on session bean classes where <![CDATA[<<In>>]]> and <![CDATA[<<Out>>]]> stereotypes are
					modeled respectively.
                </p>
                <p>
                    If attribute multiplicity is 0, 0..1, 0..*, the 
					<i>require</i> property is defined in both annotations.
                </p>
                <p>
                    If attribute multiplicity is 1, 1..* 
					the <i>create</i> property is defined on the <![CDATA[@In]]> annotation.  You can explicitly
                    specify this using the <![CDATA[andromda_seam_bijection_in_create]]> tagged value.
				</p>
                <p>
                    To explicitly specify the name of the context variable for the <![CDATA[@In]]> annotation,
                    model the <![CDATA[andromda_seam_bijection_in_value]]> tagged value.  This can also be used
                    to specify the JSF EL expression.  If not specified, the name will default to the component
                    attribute.  The <![CDATA[andromda_seam_bijection_out_value]]> tagged value can be used for
                    the <![CDATA[@Out]]> annotation.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Creating Seam Component">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[@Create]]> annotation is rendered on session bean operations if a 
					<![CDATA[<<Create>>]]> stereotype is modeled on this method, indicating that the method
                    should be called when an instance of the component is instantiated by Seam.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Destruction of Context Variables">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[@Destroy]]> annotation is rendered on a session bean operation if a 
					<![CDATA[<<Destroy>>]]> stereotype is modeled on it.  Otherwise, by default,
                    a <b>Destroy</b> method is generated with this annotation.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Not Null Validation">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[@NotNull]]> annotation will be rendered on getters based on attribute multiplicity.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Length Validation">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[@Length]]> annotation's max property is taken from 
					<![CDATA[andromda_persistence_column_length]]> tagged value. It is planned to specify a min 
					length, set via the same tagged value with format x,y where x is min, y is max. 
					This has currently not been implemented.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Component Validation">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[<<Valid>>]]> stereotype can be modeled on session bean component attributes 
					to render the <![CDATA[@Valid]]> annotation for Hibernate Validator to recursively 
                    validate this and related objects.
				</p>
                <p>
                    The <![CDATA[<<Validator>>]]> stereotype can be modeled on Seam component operations indicating
                    the validator must validate the component before invoking the method.
                </p>
				<p>
					This component operation can now model the 
                    <![CDATA[andromda_seam_validation_outcome]]> tagged value to indicate the JSF outcome when
                    validation fails.
                </p>
                <p> 
					The <![CDATA[andromda_seam_validation_refreshEntities]]> tagged value can also optionally be
                    modeled with values 'true' or 
					'false' and if defined, adds the <i>refreshEntities</i> property to the annotation.  This will
                    indicate any invalid entity in the managed state be refreshed from the database when 
                    validation fails.  This is used in conjunction with extended persistence context.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Stateful Session Bean Components">
				<p>
					As soon as you introduce session bean attributes, the cartridge defines 
					the bean as a stateful session bean only if none of the attributes are modeled with Seam related
                    stereotypes or tagged values.  If you have only Seam component attributes in the session bean
                    (which by the way, is a Seam component), the bean is not defined as a SFSB.  If you wish 
                    to explicitly define this bean as a SFSB you can do this via the tagged value 
                    <![CDATA[andromda_service_type]]>.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Data Model">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[<<DataModel>>]]> stereotype can be modeled on component attributes 
					of type List, Map, Set or Object[]. 
					This will render <![CDATA[@DataModel]]> on the attribute. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    An optional tagged value 
					<![CDATA[andromda_seam_data_datamodel_value]]> can be modeled on such 
					attributes to defined the context variable name if more than one datamodel exists.
				</p>
                <p>
                    The exposed attribute will have the scope of the owning component, or the <b>EVENT</b>
                    scope if the owning component itself has a <b>STATELESS</b> scope.  You can optionally
                    explicitly define the scope using <![CDATA[andromda_seam_data_datamodel_scope]]> tagged value.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Data Model Selection">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[<<DataModelSelection>>]]> stereotype can be modeled on component attributes 
					to inject the selected value from the <b>DataModel</b> into the attribute. The JSF
                    DataModel is the underlying collection or map value.  This 
					will render <![CDATA[@DataModelSelection]]> on the attribute.
                </p>
                <p>
                    An optional tagged value 
					<![CDATA[andromda_seam_data_datamodelselection_value]]> can define the 
					name of the context variable specified by the appropriate <![CDATA[@DataModel]]>.  
                    This tagged value is
                    not needed is there is only one <![CDATA[@DataModel]]> element in the Seam component.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Initializing Context Variable">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[<<Factory>>]]> stereotype can be modeled on session bean 
					component operations with the optional <![CDATA[andromda_seam_bijection_factory_value]]>
					tagged value which can be modeled on the operation to set the context variable name.
                    If this tagged value is NOT set, the default value is the property name.  You can optionally
                    explicitly specify the scope of the context variable by using the 
                    <![CDATA[andromda_seam_bijection_factory_scope]]> tagged value.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Request Parameters">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[<<RequestParameter>>]]> stereotype can be modeled on session bean 
					component attributes to indicate an attribute is to be injected with the value 
					of a request parameter. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    The optional tagged value 
					<![CDATA[andromda_seam_component_requestparameter_value]]> will define the 
					request parameter name.  If this is NOT set, the name will default to the name of the
                    component attribute.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Transaction Rollback">
                <p>
                    You can model the <![CDATA[<<Rollback>>]]> stereotype on component method, which will
                    set the transaction to rollback when the method completes, if the outcome of the method
                    matches any of the listed outcomes or when no outcomes are listed.  You set the list
                    of outcomes using the following tagged value.
                </p>
				<p>
					The tagged value <![CDATA[andromda_seam_transaction_rollback_ifoutcome]]> which can be set 
					on bean component operations that have the <![CDATA[<<Rollback>>]]> stereotype, 
                    can have multiple values to indicate the list of outcomes that trigger a rollback.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Action Outcome in Absence of a Conversation">
				<p>
					The tagged value <![CDATA[andromda_seam_component_conversational_ifnotbegunoutcome]]>
					can be set to render the <b>ifNotBegunOutcome</b> property on the <![CDATA[@Conversational]]> 
                    annotation to indicate the JSF outcome for the action, if no long-running conversation is 
					active when the component is invoked.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Beginging a Conversation">
				<p>
					The<![CDATA[<<Begin>>]]> stereotype can be modeled on Seam component operations 
					to indicate a long-running conversation has started.  This will render a <![CDATA[@Begin]]> 
                    annotation on the operation. The following tagged values can be defined within the context of this
                    component:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><![CDATA[andromda_seam_conversation_begin_flushmode]]></li>
                    <li><![CDATA[andromda_seam_conversation_begin_ifoutcome]]> - Can have multiple values</li>
                    <li><![CDATA[andromda_seam_conversation_begin_join]]></li>
                    <li><![CDATA[andromda_seam_conversation_begin_nested]]></li>
                    <li><![CDATA[andromda_seam_conversation_begin_pageflow]]></li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Ending a Conversation">
				<p>
					The <![CDATA[<<End>>]]> stereotype can be modeled on Seam component operations 
					to indicate the end of a long running conversation. The following tagged values can be
                    defined within the context of this component:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><![CDATA[andromda_seam_conversation_end_ifoutcome]]> - can have multiple values</li>
				    <li><![CDATA[andromda_seam_conversation_end_evenifexception]]></li>
                    <li><![CDATA[andromda_seam_conversation_end_beforeredirect]]></li>
               </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="jBPM Tasks and Processes">
				<p>
					Refer to seam profile for docs on stereotypes/tags for jBPM tasks/processes.
				</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Unwrap Stereotype">
				<p>
					The stereotype <![CDATA[<<Unwrap>>]]> can be modeled on attributes but is rendered 
					on getter method of bean components.
				</p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                To read about the test framework using TestNG and JBoss Embeddable microcontainer, click
                <a href="howto22.html">here</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
