<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="vancek@users.sourceforge.net">Vance Karimi</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - EJB3 - Installation &amp; Configuration</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Installation">
            <p>
                Since the EJB3 cartridge is not part of the base AndroMDA package, you need to know a
                few things to get started with the cartridge.  This installation and configuration
                guide should provide enough information to get you started.
            </p>
            <a name="Requirements"/>
            <subsection name="Requirements">
	            <p>
	                You must have the latest Maven (currently 2.0.4) installed and configured.
	                You can install Maven 
	                <a href="http://maven.apache.org/download.html#Installation">here</a>.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                You need to have an instance of AndroMDA 3.3-SNAPSHOT.  At the time of writing this, 3.2
	                was released but the latest 3.3-SNAPSHOT from CVS contains updates to the project generator
	                and site plugin; this is more suitable for use with the EJB3 cartridge.  Follow the anonymous
	                CVS access at <a href="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=73047">AndroMDA project</a> to
	                checkout and build the latest <b>andromda-all</b> source from the <i>V3_x_HEAD</i> branch.
	            </p>
                <p>
                    Finally, you will need the JBoss Application Server.  It is recommended to download the
                    latest GA JBoss AS.  At the time of writing this guide and with the current status of the
                    EJB3 cartridge, it is recommended to download JBoss AS 4.0.5-GA using the JEMS installer
                    (at least 1.2.0.GA) and install with the <i>ejb3</i> profile.  Read up more about
                    the <a href="http://labs.jboss.com/portal/jbossas/?prjlist=false">JBoss AS</a> and download
                    the installer.
                </p>
	        </subsection>
            <a name="Getting_the_Cartridge"/>
            <subsection name="Getting the Cartridge">
	            <p>
	                Once you have met the requirements above, checkout the latest EJB3 cartridge from
	                CVS HEAD.  
	                You have two options:
	                <ul>
	                    <li>
                            Follow the anonymous CVS access at
                			<a href="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=154568">andromdaplugins project</a>
                			on SourceForge to checkout the latest <b>andromda-plugins</b> module from 
                			<code>HEAD</code>.
	                	</li>
	                	<li>
                	    	If you are using an IDE like Eclipse, open your CVS repository exploring perspective,
                	    	create a new repository with connection type (pserver), username (anonymous),
                	    	password(<i>blank</i>) host (andromdaplugins.cvs.sourceforge.net) and repository path
                	    	(/cvsroot/andromdaplugins).  Once connected, expand HEAD and check out
                	    	<code>andromda-plugins</code>.
	                	</li>
	                </ul>  
	                Note that this will check out all cartridges and plugins 
	                which are not relevant to the EJB3 cartridge, but will ease the your build process.
	            </p>
	        </subsection>
            <a name="Building_the_Cartridge"/>
            <subsection name="Building the Cartridge">
	            <p>
	                Once you have checked out the <code>andromda-plugins</code> project, you can simply build 
	                the <b>andromda-ejb3</b> catridge in <code>andromda-plugins/cartridges/andromda-ejb3</code>
	                by running <i>mvn</i> in the latter location.
	            </p>
	        </subsection>
            <a name="Building_Documentation"/>
            <subsection name="Building Documentation">
                <p class="highlight">
                    You NO LONGER need to download the Maven 2.0.x source to build the cartridge
                    documentation.
                </p>
	            <p>
	                To build the EJB3 cartridge site documentation requires a few extra Maven 2 plugins
	                to be downloaded from the Maven 2 SVN.  The
	                <a href="http://maven.apache.org/guides/development/guide-building-m2.html">Maven build</a>
	                documentation will give you some information on how to access their SVN.
	            </p>
                <p>
                    Please follow <a href="http://forum.andromda.org/viewtopic.php?t=3976">Maven 2 site Docs</a>
                    to download and build the necessary Maven 2 projects prior to building the EJB3 cartridge site
                    docs.
                </p>
	            <p>
	                You will need to check out <i>maven-plugins</i> from Maven <b>trunk</b>.  You only required
                    the following plugins, so you can disable the other modules if you wish.
	                <ul>
	                    <li>maven-changes-plugin</li>
	                    <li>maven-changelog-plugin</li>
	                </ul>
	                Once you have built them (mvn install), these plugins will reside in your local repo.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                All other require plugins will be downloaded to your local repo if they don't already
	                exist.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                You can download the source examples used in the howto for all sections
	                <a href="howto/HowToModel-src.zip">here</a> and extract to the target/site folder of the
	                andromda-ejb3 plugin.
	            </p>
                <p>
                    You can download the UML model containing all models for all sections
                    <a href="howto/HowToModel.xml.zip">here</a>.
                </p>
	        </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                Before starting with the EJB3 howtos, find out how to generate your
                <a href="project.html">EJB 3.0 project</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
