<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="wouter@andromda.org">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - EJB3 - Tips</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Tips for using the AndroMDA EJB3 cartridge">
            <p>
                This section provides you with some pointers that might prove helpful when using AndroMDA with
                the EJB3 cartridge.  Some of these tips are shared with the Spring cartridge.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Exceptions">
            <p>
                It's not needed to model exceptions for all the services you model, the EJB3 cartridge will
                generate them automatically for you. That way you don't need to keep writing
                <code>try/catch</code> blocks in the <code>handleXXX</code> methods in the service implementation
                classes, just throw any error, it will be handled for you.
            </p>
            <p>
                So basically this snippet is a good example of an implementation of a service operation, there is
                no need to catch any exception and rethrow it:
<source language="java"><![CDATA[
protected PersonDetails handleGet(Long id) throws Exception
{
    return (PersonDetails)getPersonDao().load(PersonDao.TRANSFORM_PERSONDETAILS, id);
}
]]></source>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Using foreign services">
            <p>
                You can connect to "foreign" EJB3 services, which are not implemented  in your application but in
                another one (e.g. a other ear), as with "normal" services: just draw a dependency to the "foreign"
                service class. The foreign service class has to be defined as any other service but without any method
                or property.
            </p>
            <p>
                To prevent the EJB3 cartridge from generating java code you have to exclude the packages with a
                process="false" statement in the andromda configuration just in your appropriate
                <code>&lt;model&gt;</code> tag:
                <source language="xml"><![CDATA[
<modelPackages>
    <modelPackage process="false">de::my::foreign.package::name</modelPackage>
</modelPackages>
                ]]></source>
                (look at http://team.andromda.org/docs/configuration.html#modelPackage)
                The EJB3 cartridge should generate the <code>@EJB</code> injections from the dependency for the 
                source class.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
