<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="mbohlen@mbohlen.de">Matthias Bohlen</author>
    <title>AndroMDA - Installation</title>
    <gennews>yes</gennews>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <freetext name="Section 1">
      <h1>How to install AndroMDA</h1>
      <p class="std">
        <b>Download, unzip, CLASSPATH!</b><br />
        (or was it "Ready ... steady ... go!" ?)
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        The installation of AndroMDA itself is quite easy (the real challenge
        will come later!).
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        Download the files <code>andromda_nnn.zip</code> and <code>andromda_libs_nnn.zip</code> from
        the
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=73047">
          AndroMDA file list
        </a>
        on SourceForge's web site and unzip them into the same directory of your choice.
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        The <code>andromda_nnn.zip</code> ZIP contains the following files:
        <ul>
          <li class="std">
            Template files <code>src/templates/*.vsl</code> - templates for entity beans
            and session beans, written in the Velocity scripting language. Customize these 
            templates if you do not like what you see when the generator has done its job!
          </li>
          <li class="std">
            <code>andromda.jar</code> - the executable code. Put this jar file into
            your CLASSPATH when you run your personal Ant build script.
          </li>
          <li class="std">
            <code>doc</code> - a directory with the documentation. This contains
            the documentation that is found on this website.
          </li>
          <li class="std">
            <code>sample</code> - a directory containing a few samples.  
          </li>
          <li class="std">
            <code>src</code> - a directory with the sources of AndroMDA. This contains
            all of the hand-written code for AndroMDA. 
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        The <code>andromda_libs_nnn.zip</code> ZIP contains the following files:
        <ul>
          <li class="std">
            <code>lib</code> - a directory that contains most of the jars that 
            you will need to build and run the <code>car-rental-system</code> 
            sample.  You will find the jars for Velocity, Castor, Junit, Log4j, and 
            XDoclet.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        <b>Other software that you will need</b>
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        AndroMDA is based upon some other software components that
        you will need to download from the Internet and include in
        the CLASSPATH of your build script. These components
        are:
        <ul>
          <li class="std">
            <code>Ant</code> - the famous build tool, made by the Apache Jakarta project.
            You can download it from
            <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">
              the Apache Ant website
            </a>
            . Unpack ant into a directory of your choice and set the property
            <code>myant.home</code> in your file <code>build.properties</code>
            before you run your personal Ant build script.
          </li>
          <li class="std">
            <code>JBoss</code> - a very popular open source application server.
            You can download it from
            <a href="http://www.jboss.org/">
              the JBoss website
            </a>
            . Unpack it into a directory and set the property <code>jboss.home</code>
            in your <code>build.properties</code> before you run your ant build scripts.
          </li>
        </ul>

      </p>
    </freetext>

    <news name="Velocity" href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/">
      <p>
        Velocity is a product written by the famous <b>Apache
        Jakarta</b> project. It can be used to generate Java, web
        pages, SQL, PostScript and other output from
        templates. It can be used either as a standalone
        utility for generating source code and reports, or as
        an integrated component of other systems.
      </p>
    </news>

	<news name="JUnit" href="http://www.junit.org">
      <p>
        JUnit is a regression testing framework written by 
        Erich Gamma and Kent Beck. It is used by the developer who implements 
        unit tests in Java. JUnit is Open Source Software, released under the 
        IBM's Common Public License Version 1.0 and hosted on SourceForge.
      </p>
    </news>
    
    <news name="XDoclet" href="http://www.xdoclet.org">
      <p>
         XDoclet is a code generation engine. It enables Attribute-Oriented 
         Programming for java. In short, this means that you can add more significance 
         to your code by adding meta data (attributes) to your java sources. 
         This is done in special JavaDoc tags. 
      </p>
    </news>
    
  </body>
</document>
