<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="mbohlen@mbohlen.de">Matthias Bohlen</author>
    <title>AndroMDA - Installation</title>
    <gennews>yes</gennews>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="How to install AndroMDA">
      <h1></h1>
      <p class="std">
        <b>Download, unzip, CLASSPATH!</b><br />
        (or was it "Ready ... steady ... go!" ?)
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        The installation of AndroMDA itself is quite easy (the real challenge
        will come later!).
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        Download the distribution file andromda-bin-*.zip from
        the
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=73047">
          AndroMDA file list
        </a>
        on SourceForge's web site and unzip it into a directory of your choice.
        You will notice that it has a release number at the end of the filename.
        After unzipping, you will notice the following directory structure inside:
      </p>
      <table border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="2" class="std">
        <tr>
          <td><b>Directory</b></td>
          <td><b>Contents</b></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td valign="top">
            <code>andromda-core</code>
          </td>
          <td valign="top">
            Core of the generator, along with documentation and source files.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td valign="top">
            <code>cartridges</code>
          </td>
          <td valign="top">
            Home of the pluggable cartridges that generate different
            kinds of output files: EJBs, Hibernate objects, Struts applications,
            plain Java files.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td valign="top">
            <code>docs</code>
          </td>
          <td valign="top">
            Complete documentation as you read here.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td valign="top">
            <code>samples</code>
          </td>
          <td valign="top">
            Several sample applications of AndroMDA, including:
            <ul>
              <li class="std">
                  a complete J2EE sample application (a car rental system), generated
                  with AndroMDA from a UML model that is also included
              </li>
              <li class="std">a template for an empty project using EJB technology</li>
              <li class="std">a template for an empty project using Hibernate technology</li>
              <li class="std">a project that shows how to generate something using
                  all the model information in one template.
              </li>
            </ul>
            The directory also contains wizard.xml, a small script that can
            create empty projects for you to start with (see <a href="starting.html">"Getting started"</a>).
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      <p class="std">
        Unzip the files you need into a directory of your choice. Be prepared to
        insert jar files from these directories onto the classpath of your
        build.properties script (see instructions later in this text). AndroMDA will auto-detect
        a cartridge if its main jar file (e.g. andromda-hibernate.jar) is on
        the classpath when AndroMDA is run.
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        <b>Other software that you will need</b>
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        AndroMDA is based upon some other software components that
        you will need to download from the Internet and include in
        the CLASSPATH of your build script. These components
        are:
        <ul>
          <li class="std">
            <code>Ant</code> - the famous build tool, made by the Apache Jakarta project.
            You can download it from
            <a href="http://ant.apache.org/">
              the Apache Ant website
            </a>
            .
            Unpack ant into a directory of your choice and set the environment
            variable <code>ANT_HOME</code> to the name of that directory before
            you run your personal Ant build script.
          </li>
          <li class="std">
            <code>JBoss</code> - a very popular open source application server.
            You can download it from
            <a href="http://www.jboss.org/">
              the JBoss website
            </a>
            . Unpack it into a directory and set the property <code>jboss.home</code>
            in your <code>build.properties</code> before you run your ant build scripts.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>

      <p class="std">
        <b>Recompiling AndroMDA from the source</b>
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        Recompiling AndroMDA from the source is quite easy. Unpack
        <code>andromda-src-*.zip</code> into a directory of your choice. Copy
        <code>build.properties.sample</code> to <code>build.properties</code>
        and edit it. Insert the directory where you installed JBoss as a value
        for the property <code>jboss.home</code>. That's it! Run <code>ant</code>
        and watch the contents of the "dist" subdirectory!
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        The same rules apply
        if you want to compile the CVS version. Checkout the <code>andromda-all</code>
        module from
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=73047">
          AndroMDA CVS
        </a>
        instead of unzipping the released sources, then proceed as before.
      </p>

    </section>

    <news name="Velocity" href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/">
      <p>
        Velocity is a product written by the famous <b>Apache
        Jakarta</b> project. It can be used to generate Java, web
        pages, SQL, PostScript and other output from
        templates. It can be used either as a standalone
        utility for generating source code and reports, or as
        an integrated component of other systems.
      </p>
    </news>

    <news name="JUnit" href="http://www.junit.org">
      <p>
        JUnit is a regression testing framework written by
        Erich Gamma and Kent Beck. It is used by the developer who implements
        unit tests in Java. JUnit is Open Source Software, released under the
        IBM's Common Public License Version 1.0 and hosted on SourceForge.
      </p>
    </news>

    <news name="XDoclet" href="http://www.xdoclet.org">
      <p>
         XDoclet is a code generation engine. It enables Attribute-Oriented
         Programming for java. In short, this means that you can add more significance
         to your code by adding meta data (attributes) to your java sources.
         This is done in special JavaDoc tags.
      </p>
    </news>

  </body>
</document>
