<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document> 
	<properties>
    	<title>Developing Metafacades</title> 
    </properties>
  	<body> 
  		<section name="Take your time!">
  		    <p>
      		    Writing your own metafacades is a non-trivial task, if you do
      		    it for the first time. You should close the door and get yourself
      		    at least two days in a quiet atmosphere, reducing the context
      		    switches in your mind to a minimum. Otherwise, it might be
      		    a pain! :-)
            </p>
            <p>
                The next section assumes you have brewed a good cup of coffee
                (or tea or whatever) and have at least two hours of time.
                Take a deep breath and start to prepare your working environment.
            </p>  		    
        </section>

  		<section name="Prepare the working environment">
  		    <p>
  		        First, make sure you have the correct directory structure
  		        on disk to keep all the artifacts you need to develop an
  		        AndroMDA cartridge. The easiest way to get such a correct
  		        directory structure is to copy an existing cartridge that
  		        already contains its own metafacades. A good example for
  		        this is the Hibernate cartridge.
  		    </p>
  		    <p>
  		        After you copied the cartridge, you will see a directory
  		        structure like this:
  		    </p>
<source>
src/java
src/templates
src/uml
</source>
  		    <p>
  		        Metafacades are generated from a UML model. Put this UML model 
  		        in a file into the <code>src/uml</code> directory. Open 
  		        MagicDraw and import the basic metafacades module which is 
  		        shipped with AndroMDA. These basic metafacades for UML are in 
  		        the model file <code>andromda/xml.zips/UMLMetafacadeModel-*.xml.zip</code> 
				located in the AndroMDA binary distribution.
  		        You import them using the "File, Use Profile/Module..." menu in MagicDraw. 
  		        After using the module, you should be able to see the basic facade 
  		        classes (like ClassifierFacade, etc.) but MagicDraw should show 
  		        them as read-only.
  		    </p>
  		    <p>
  		        The next step is to model your own metafacades.
  		    </p>
  		    
		</section>

  		<section name="Model and generate your own metafacades">
  		    <p>
  		        A few rules apply if you want to make AndroMDA generate
  		        the metafacades for you. You will see that they are easy
  		        to remember and that they make sense. After a short recap
  		        to clarify the terminology, the rules will be shown here.
  		    </p>
  		    <subsection name="Recap about how metafacades work">
      		    <p>
      		        Later, the user of your cartridge will load a model into 
      		        AndroMDA and will try to run your cartridge. At that time, the 
      		        metadata repository in AndroMDA will instantiate a metaobject 
      		        for each element of the user's model. After this, AndroMDA
      		        optionally instantiates a metafacade object that shields
      		        the metaobject.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Terms used to distinguish classes">
                <p>
                    We choose the following terms when we speak about
                    metafacades:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>A class of the metamodel is called a metaclass.</li>
                    <li>An instance of a metaclass is called a metaobject.</li>
                    <li>A class representing a metafacade is called a metafacade class.</li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    So, don't confuse a metafacade class with a metaclass!
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Modeling rules">
                <p>
                    There are rules that tell you how to shield a metaclass
                    with a metafacade. Metafacades and metaclasses can relate
                    to each other in the following ways:
                </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>A metafacade class can have a direct dependency on a metaclass.</li>
                    <li>A metafacade class can specialize another metafacade
                        class and (in this case) may omit the dependency
                        to a metaclass (because one of the superclasses of
                        the metafacade class already has such a dependency).</li>
                    <li>If (in point 2 above) a metafacade class MF2
                        specializes another metafacade class MF1 <b>and</b> (at the same time)
                        has a direct dependency to a metaclass M2, then
                        the metaclass M2 must specialize the metaclass M1 that
                        is referenced by MF1 as a direct dependency.</li>
                    <li>If you think point 3 is too cryptic then simply think of
                        parallel class hierarchies: the class ordering in the 
                        metafacade class hierarchy must be similar to the
                        class ordering in the metaclass hierarchy.</li>
                    <li>The root metafacade class in the hierarchy
                        <b>must</b> depend on some metaclass. Other metafacade
                        classes may or may not depend on a metaclass.</li>
                </ol>        
                <p>
                    There are two rules how to add stereotypes to the classes:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>The metaclass must have the stereotype "metaclass".</li>
                    <li>The metafacade class must have the stereotype "metafacade".</li>
                </ul>        
                <p>
                    That's it. No more rules for modeling metafacades.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            
		</section>

        <section name="Look at what you get from the metafacade model">
            <p>
                Here, you see a picture of some typical metafacades:
            </p>
            <img src="images/MetafacadePIM.jpg" />
            <p>
                A metafacade can have attributes, operations and associations
                to other metafacade classes. It can also depend on a metaclass
                or specialize another metafacade class. 
                Let's talk about what it means if you add
                various things to a metafacade class.
            </p>
            <p>
                The code for the metafacades will be generated by the
                andromda-meta cartridge. (Cool: you use AndroMDA to develop a cartridge 
                that extends AndroMDA!). Each model element that you add to a 
                metafacade class will later be translated by andromda-meta into
                a bunch of Java elements. The following table shows you which
                model element will be translated to which Java element:
            </p>
            <table>
                <tr><th>Model element</th><th>Java element(s)</th></tr>
                <tr><td>Metafacade class</td>
                    <td>Interface, plumbing and implementation classes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr><td>Attribute</td>
                    <td>Abstract getter</td>
                </tr>
                <tr><td>Operation</td>
                    <td>Abstract method</td>
                </tr>
                <tr><td>Association</td>
                    <td>Abstract getter</td>
                </tr>
                <tr><td>Dependency</td>
                    <td>Ignored except when the target of the dependency
                        is a metaclass. In that case, a constructor with
                        an argument of the metaclass type is generated.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr><td>Specialization</td>
                    <td>Same constructor as in the dependency case except
                        that this constructor calls the "superfacade" constructor.
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <p>
                A metaclass itself translates to three classes in Java:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>An interface with the method signatures of all
                    generated methods in the metafacade.</li>
                <li>A class with automatically generated plumbing logic.
                    This is called the "Logic" class.</li>
                <li>An implementation class which is hand-written.
                    This is called the "LogicImpl" class.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                <i>//TODO: Add pictures of generated metafacades here...</i><br />
                <i>//TODO: Describe what the responsibilities of the three classes are...</i>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Write the metafacade implementations">
            <p>
                Basically, after having generated all those nice metafacade
                classes, you will want to implement their real functionality,
                right? To do that, start your favourite Java IDE (e.g. Eclipse).
            </p>
            <subsection name="Setting up a project in the IDE">
                <p>
                    Open a project that references all the source files,
                    generated as well as hand-written. Make the IDE project
                    reference the standard, basic metafacade project in the 
                    <code>metafacades/uml</code>
                    directory. <i>//TODO: Chad, where are those files in the binary
                    distribution? Metafacade developers should possibly reference a jar file here
                    instead of the source code tree, right?</i>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Implementing the LogicImpl classes">
                <p>    
                    Now, watch out for all
                    those classes that end with "LogicImpl" in their names. These
                    classes have been generated for you but will never be touched by
                    the generator again. This is the place where you can implement
                    your own logic.
                </p>
                <p> 
                    Watch out for the "//TODO" tags in the files.
                    You will notice that getters for attributes and associations
                    are there to be filled by hand. This is the place where the facade
                    does its work - you will want to refer to the contents of the
                    metaobject that is shielded by this facade and translate it in
                    some way so that you can return it from one of those getters.
                    Operations in the metafacade model are translated to abstract
                    Java methods - you will also want to implement these in the
                    LogicImpl class.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="The role of the metafacade factory">
                <p>
                    <i>//TODO: Describe how to create new metafacade objects
                    and how the factory knows which one to instantiate,
                    depending on stereotype and context.
                    </i>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <i>//TODO: Insert reference to <a href="configuring.html">Configuring metafacades</a>
                    so that we explain everything only once.
                    </i>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Returning references to other metafacades ">
                <p>
                    <i>//TODO: Describe how to shield a metaobject
                    with a metafacade object.</i>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Accessing metafacade namespaces">
                <p>
                    <i>//TODO: Describe how to get parameters from the
                    metafacade's namespace in order to control code generation.
                    </i>
                </p>
            </subsection>

        </section>

        <section name="Deploy the metafacades with your cartridge">
            <p>
                After you have modeled, generated and implemented your
                metafacades, you can deploy them with your cartridge.
                To make this work, you need to configure an XML file.
                Read 
                <a href="configuring.html">Configuring metafacades</a>
                to see how to make AndroMDA use your metafacades 
                at the right time.
            </p>
        </section>

  	</body> 
</document>
