<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
       xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Environment Setup</title>
        <author email="naresh@andromda.org">Naresh Bhatia</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Prepare the Development Environment">
            <p>
                This section provides a step-by-step guide to set up your development environment for AndroMDA.
                We assume that you are working on a Windows platform.
                Throughout this section you will install various programs. The recommended installation paths for
                these programs and other required directories are listed below. Please feel free to change the installation
                paths depending on your configuration and personal preferences. For example, you may choose to install programs
                on the D: drive instead of the C: drive. However, note that some programs don't work well if there are spaces
                in their pathname. So, try to stick to the suggestions below as much as possible.
            </p>
            <table>
                <tr>
                    <th>Recommended Path</th>
                    <th>Purpose</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Programs\m2repo</td>
                    <td>Maven local repository M2_REPO</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Programs\maven2</td>
                    <td>Maven2 program M2_HOME</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Programs\Java\jdk\6</td>
                    <td>Java Development Kit JAVA_HOME</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Programs\Java\jdk\6\jre6</td>
                    <td>Java Runtime Engine</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Programs\MySQL</td>
                    <td>MySQL database server 5.5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Programs\JetBrains\IntelliJ IDEA 9.0.2</td>
                    <td>IntelliJ IDEA IDE (optional)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Programs\Eclipse</td>
                    <td>Eclipse IDE (optional)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>C:\Programs\JBoss\6</td>
                    <td>JBoss v6 Application Server JBOSS_HOME</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <p>
                You will also be asked to set up several environment variables. Please set these as SYSTEM variables using the Control Panel
                (Control Panel > System > Advanced > Environment Variables, or Computer > Properties > Advanced > Environment Variables). 
                Note that if you change the installation path of any program
                then you must make sure that the associated environment variable is changed accordingly.
            </p>

            <subsection name="Install Java">
                <p>
                    Install J2SE Development Kit 6 (JDK 6) or newer from <a
                        href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/index.html">http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/index.html</a>.
                    This is the preferred version of the JDK for AndroMDA.
                    We also support JDK version 1.5. Support for version 1.4 requires a specific code generation configuration
                    overriding the default settings, and changing to an earlier maven version and changing compiler settings. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    Make sure that the
                    <code>JAVA_HOME</code>
                    environment variable is pointing to
                    the directory where you installed the JDK. It is possible you have this
                    variable set already, but just to make sure here's how to check.
                </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>
                        From a command prompt type <code>echo %JAVA_HOME%</code>.
                        - OR -
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Go to the control panel and double-click on <code>System</code>.
                        If you are a Windows XP user it's possible you have to open
                        <code>Performance and Maintenance</code>
                        before you will see the
                        <code>System</code> icon.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Go to the <code>Advanced</code> tab and click on
                        <code>Environment Variables</code>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Make sure you have set the <code>JAVA_HOME</code>
                        variable and it is pointing to the directory where you installed the JDK.
                        If not, add/edit the variable and set it to the correct value,
                        e.g. C:\Programs\Java\6. You may add the variable
                        to the list of user variables or system variables.
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install Maven">
                <p>
                    <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven2</a>
                    is our preferred tool for building and deploying applications generated by AndroMDA. Based on the concept of a project object model (POM), Maven can manage a project's build, reporting, and documentation from a central piece of information. If you are familiar with Ant, Maven is very similar except that it contains additional functionality:
                </p>

                <ol>
                    <li>
                        A hierarchical build environment, where properties configured in a POM file (pom.xml) flow down to POM files of all child projects.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Standardized build tasks (clean, build, install, deploy, etc.)
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Dependency specifications for build and deploy tasks - for all internal and external libraries; tied to a specific released versions of dependent libraries
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        A repository containing all versioned dependencies. This repository is used during the build and deploy processes for all referencing projects.
                    </li>
                </ol>

                <p>Install Maven 2.2.1 by following the steps below.</p>

                <ol>
                    <li>
                        Click <a href="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">http://maven.apache.org/download.html</a> and download Maven 2.2.1 or newer.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Unzip this file at C:\Programs\. A directory called maven-2.2.1 will be created which contains the Maven program. Rename to 'maven2'.
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p>
                    Note: If you are behind a proxy server, you will have to configure Maven to use the proxy. The details can be found below.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install JBoss Application Server">
                <p>
                    <a href="http://www.jboss.org/jbossas">JBoss Application Server</a>
                    is a widely used open source Java application server. Install JBoss 6.0 by following the steps below.
                </p>

                <ol>
                    <li>
                        Click <a href="http://www.jboss.org/jbossas/downloads.html">http://www.jboss.org/jbossas/downloads.html</a> to point your browser to the JBossAS download page.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Select the desired version (latest release) and click the Download button on the row that lists JBoss Application Server version 6.0. This should take you to the download page on the SourceForge site.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Click on the link named "jboss-as-distribution-6.0.0.Final.zip" to download this file.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Unzip this file at C:\Programs. A directory called jboss-6.0.0.Final will be created which contains the JBoss application server. Rename this directory to JBoss\6 (just to make the name a little shorter and to allow for multiple versions).
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        If you are planning to install the Oracle database on your machine, then you must change the JBoss HTTP port, which defaults to 8080. 
                        The reason is that Oracle also defaults to this port and it is not easy to change Oracle's configuration. 
                        In order to change JBoss' HTTP port, edit the files called \default\conf\bindingservice.beans\META-INF\bindings-jboss-beans.xml 
                        and server\default\deploy\jbossweb.sar\server.xml and change all occurrences of the number "8080" to something else, say "9090". 
                        This will resolve the conflict between JBoss and Oracle. 
                        If you have followed this step then you must use port 9090 whenever you are instructed to use port 8080 in this tutorial.
                        If you are using JBoss6, use a utility such as WinGrep to search and replace all instances of 8080 with the new port, under server\default,
                        for *.xml and *.properties (about 4 places).
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Test start the JBoss application server: <code>cd %JBOSS_HOME%\bin</code> and <code>run.bat</code>.
                        Make sure the default server starts without errors. If you see the error 
                        <code>java.lang.NoSuchMethodError: javax.annotation.Resource.lookup()Ljava/lang/String;</code>
                        there is a JDK version conflict in the JSR250 jar, add the following to the JBoss command line:
                        <code>-Djava.endorsed.dirs=$JBOSS_HOME/lib/endorsed</code> as explained in
                        <a href="http://community.jboss.org/wiki/EJB31Embeddable">http://community.jboss.org/wiki/EJB31Embeddable</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Verify the JBoss Administration Console after starting JBoss: Open <a href="http://127.0.0.1:8080">http://127.0.0.1:8080</a>.
                        Select the 'Administrative Console' link. Login with 'admin/admin'. The console will be used for adding/configuring databases other than
                        the default Hypersonic DB. See <a href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/EclipseLink/Examples/JPA/JBoss_Web_Tutorial">http://wiki.eclipse.org/EclipseLink/Examples/JPA/JBoss_Web_Tutorial</a> for more detailed information.
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Setup environment variables">
                <p>
                    We have seen earlier how to set environment variables such as
                    <code>JAVA_HOME</code>, it is strongly recommended to set the
                    following variables before continuing. We repeat
                    <code>JAVA_HOME</code>
                    here just for completeness.
                </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Property</th>
                        <th>Value</th>
                        <th>Required?</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>JAVA_HOME</td>
                        <td>Java installation directory, e.g.
                            <code>C:\Programs\Java\jdk16</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>Yes</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>M2_HOME</td>
                        <td>Maven installation directory, e.g.
                            <code>C:\Programs\maven2</code>
                            (this may have already been set by the Maven installer)
                        </td>
                        <td>Yes</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>M2_REPO</td>
                        <td>Maven local repository, e.g. C:\Programs\m2repo</td>
                        <td>Yes</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>MAVEN_OPTS</td>
                        <td>Parameters to pass to the Java VM when running Maven. Set this
                            value to:
                            <code>-XX:MaxPermSize=128m -Xmx512m</code>
                            (required to build large maven projects such as AndroMDA itself)
                        </td>
                        <td>No</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>JBOSS_HOME</td>
                        <td>JBoss installation directory, if running jboss server e.g.
                            <code>C:\Programs\JBoss\6</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>No</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>ANT_HOME</td>
                        <td>Ant installation directory, if running ant scripts from maven e.g.
                            <code>C:\Programs\Ant</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>No</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>PATH</td>
                        <td>This makes sure the system will search for console commands in
                            the directories listed here. If this property already exists you
                            should simply add
                            <code>%JAVA_HOME%\bin;%M2_HOME%\bin;%ANT_HOME%\bin</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>Yes</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Configure and Test Maven and create a local repository">
                <p>
                    Maven is based on the concept of a central, local repository located on your machine, 
                    where it stores artifacts such as 3rd party libraries as well as components created by you. 
                    When you create a new project, you must specify a Project Object Model (POM) in a file named pom.xml. 
                    In this file, you can tell Maven about the various 3rd party libraries and components your 
                    application depends on. When Maven starts to build the application, it will first fetch these 
                    dependencies from one or more remote repositories (generally located on the Internet) and store 
                    them in your local repository. This allows future builds to happen entirely locally. 
                    By default, the local repository is located at C:\Documents and Settings\your user name\.m2\repository. 
                    Note that so far we have installed only the Maven application, we have not created a local repository. 
                    Follow the steps below to test your Maven installation and force the creation of a local repository. 
                    We will use a standard Maven plugin to create a temporary project which we will delete later.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Edit %M2_HOME%\conf\settings.xml to use the Sonatype and JBoss repositories, and to download the andromda
                    plugins. Include proxy settings if behind a firewall. This is described at 
                    <a href="http://maven.apache.org/guides/mini/guide-configuring-maven.html">Configuring Maven</a>
                    and <a href="http://maven.apache.org/ref/3.0.1/maven-settings/settings.html">Maven2 Settings</a>
                        <source><![CDATA[
...
  <!-- localRepository
   | The path to the local repository maven will use to store artifacts. Always set to M2_REPO environment variable.
   |
   | Default: ~/.m2/repository
   | Note: This value overrides the M2_REPO environment variable, if different!
  -->
  <localRepository>${env.M2_REPO}</localRepository>
...
  <!-- pluginGroups
   | This is a list of additional group identifiers that will be searched when resolving plugins by their prefix, i.e.
   | when invoking a command line like "mvn prefix:goal". Maven will automatically add the group identifiers
   | "org.apache.maven.plugins" and "org.codehaus.mojo" if these are not already contained in the list.
   |-->
  <pluginGroups>
    <!-- Specifies a further group identifier to use for plugin lookup. Causes all to be searched for updates.-->
      <pluginGroup>org.andromda.maven.plugins</pluginGroup>
   </pluginGroups>
...
  <!-- proxies
   | This is a list of proxies which can be used on this machine to connect to the network.
   | Unless otherwise specified (by system property or command-line switch), the first proxy
   | specification in this list marked as active will be used.
   |-->
  <proxies>
    <!-- proxy
     | Specification for one proxy, to be used in connecting to the network.
     |
    -->
    <proxy>
      <id>your-proxy</id>
      <active>true</active>
      <protocol>http</protocol>
      <host>your-proxy.company.com</host>
      <port>8080</port>
      <nonProxyHosts>*.company.com|127.0.0.1|localhost</nonProxyHosts>
    </proxy>
  </proxies>
...
  <repositories>
    <repository>
        <id>sonatype</id>
        <name>Sonatype Repository</name>
        <url>http://oss.sonatype.org/content/groups/public</url>
       <snapshots>
          <enabled>true</enabled>
       </snapshots>
    </repository>
    <repository>
        <id>jboss</id>
        <name>JBoss Repository</name>
        <url>http://repository.jboss.org/nexus/content/groups/public-jboss/</url>
    </repository>
  </repositories>
  <pluginRepositories>
    <pluginRepository>
        <id>sonatype</id>
        <name>Sonatype Repository</name>
        <url>http://oss.sonatype.org/content/groups/public</url>
       <snapshots>
          <enabled>true</enabled>
       </snapshots>
    </pluginRepository>
  </pluginRepositories>
...]]>
                        </source>
                    </li>
                </ul>

                <ul>
                    <li>Open a Command Prompt and change the current directory to any temporary directory, such as C:\andromda-temp.
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <ul>
                    <li>Execute the following command to make sure you can run Maven: <code>mvn -v</code>
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <ul>
                    <li>Maven should display the following output: 
<source>Apache Maven 2.2.1 (r801777; 2009-08-06 15:16:01-0400)
Java version: 1.6.0_21
Java home: C:\Program Files\JDK\16\jre</source></li>
                </ul>
                <ul>
                    <li>Now execute the following command to create a temporary project:
<source>mvn archetype:create -DgroupId=testapp -DartifactId=testapp</source>
Make sure that you get a BUILD SUCCESSFUL message at the end. 
Sometimes due to bad Internet connectivity, Maven may not be able to download all dependencies. 
If your build fails due to this reason, try to issue the command again until you get a successful build.
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <ul>
                    <li>Verify that Maven created a temporary project called testapp in the current directory 
                    and also a local repository at the %M2_REPO% location mentioned above. 
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install AndroMDA Application plugin">
                <p>
                    Next we will download and install the AndroMDA Application plugin. This plugin allows creation of
                    Java starter applications that use AndroMDA. All artifacts, such
                    as AndroMDA cartridges, will be automatically downloaded by the
                    Maven scripts generated by the plugin.
                </p>

                <ul>
                    <li>Change to the temporary directory, e.g. C:\andromda-temp.</li>
                    <li>Edit pom.xml in this directory to add the following content:
                        <source><![CDATA[
...
<build>
    <defaultGoal>compile</defaultGoal>
    <plugins>
        <plugin>
            <groupId>org.andromda.maven.plugins</groupId>
            <artifactId>andromdapp-maven-plugin</artifactId>
            <version>3.4-SNAPSHOT</version>
        </plugin>
    </plugins>
</build>]]>
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>Open a Command Prompt in the directory where you edited this pom.xml and
                        run the command mvn without any arguments. Make sure the command completes successfully
                        by displaying the BUILD SUCCESSFUL message.</li>
                    <li>You can now delete the temporary directory you created in step 1.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install a UML tool">
                <p>
                    Install a tool that will allow you to model your applications in UML and
                    export these models into a format that AndroMDA can understand. AndroMDA
                    currently supports UML 1.4/XMI 1.2 as well as UML2 2.x and 3.x/EMF/XMI2. Please follow one of the links
                    below to install the UML tool of your choice. (We invite UML tool vendors
                    and open-source projects to test their tools with AndroMDA and supply
                    installation instructions for inclusion in this section.)
                </p>

                <p>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/argouml/install.html">ArgoUML (UML 1.4/XMI 1.2)</a><br/>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/magicdraw/install.html">MagicDraw 9.5 (UML 1.4/XMI 1.2)</a><br/>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/magicdraw/install16.html">MagicDraw 11.5 through 17 (EMF-UML2 2.x or 3.x)</a><br/>
                    <a href="resources/uml-tools/rsm/install.html">RSM 7, 7.5, 8 (Rational Software Modeler/Architect)(EMF-UML2 2.x or 3.x)</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install a database">
                <p>
                    Install a database that is supported by Hibernate. Click
                    <a href="http://www.hibernate.org/260.html">http://www.hibernate.org/260.html</a>
                    to see
                    the list of supported databases. For the purpose of this tutorial we will
                    assume that you have installed one of the following databases. If you have
                    installed another database then you will have to change the Hibernate
                    configuration accordingly.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <strong>MySQL 5.5:</strong>
                        MySQL is an open source database. You can download it from
                        <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/mysql"
                          >http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/mysql</a>. We recommend
                        downloading the full Windows installation - not just the "Essentials". In addition, download and install
                        <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/workbench">MySQL Workbench</a>,
                        a GUI based tool that will make your development much easier. Finally, download and unzip
                        <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/connector/j">MySQL Connector/J</a>
                        (the MySQL JDBC driver) in a convenient directory. For the purpose of this tutorial we will assume that
                        you have installed the driver at
                        <code>C:\Programs\MySQL\mysql-connector-java-5.1.14</code>. Or - you can wait until running mvn after creating the timetracker project, 
                        which has a dependency on mysql connector.
                        Copy the MySQL driver from C:\Programs\m2repo\mysql\mysql-connector-java\5.1.14\mysql-connector-java-5.1.14.jar to the 
                        JBoss lib directory located at C:\Programs\jboss\6\server\default\lib.
                        This allows JBoss to access your database.
                    </li>

                    <li>
                        <strong>PostgreSQL 8.1:</strong>
                        PostgreSQL is an open source database. You can download it from
                        <a href="http://www.enterprisedb.com/products/pgbindownload.do"
                          >http://www.enterprisedb.com/products/pgbindownload.do</a>. The Postgres
                        installation contains a GUI based administrative tool called pgAdmin III. JDBC drivers are also
                        included as part of the installation.
                    </li>

                    <li>
                        <strong>Hypersonic SQL 2.0:</strong>
                        HSQL is an open source java database. You can download it from
                        <a href="http://hsqldb.org"
                          >http://hsqldb.org</a>. This database ships with JBoss and is often used for unit testing.
                    </li>

                    <li>
                        <strong>Oracle 9i:</strong>
                        Oracle 11g is an commercial database sold by
                        <a href="http://www.oracle.com">Oracle</a>. We assume that you
                        have the necessary distribution media to install it. Oracle 11g includes a GUI
                        based administrative tool called Enterprise Manager. JDBC drivers are also
                        included as part of the installation. The Express edition is free to use.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Install Eclipse (Optional)">
                <p>
                    Eclipse is a popular open source IDE that is useful in developing Java
                    applications. AndroMDA does not require the use of Eclipse. However we
                    do recommend using it for development as it helps increase your
                    productivity. Eclipse users will glad to know that AndroMDA generates fully usable .project and .classpath files,
                    or you can use the Sonatype M2Eclipse plugin to manage your maven projects.
                    You can download Eclipse from
                    <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/downloads">http://www.eclipse.org/downloads</a>.
                    We recommend downloading the Eclipse Helios (v3.6) Package called "Eclipse IDE for Java EE Developers".
                    Follow the steps below to install and configure Eclipse:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Unzip the downloaded archive to a suitable location on your hard drive. The recommended location is C:\Programs\eclipse.</li>
                    <li>Edit the file eclipse.ini under C:\Programs\eclipse to increase the memory available for Eclipse. Here are the suggested contents for this file:
                        <source>
                        -vmargs
                        -Xms256m
                        -Xmx512m
                        -XX:PermSize=128m
                        -XX:MaxPermSize=256m
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>Start Eclipse by double-clicking on eclipse.exe.</li>
                    <li>Eclipse asks for a folder where it can store your projects. 
                    This folder is called the Eclipse workspace. Set the workspace to a location where you generally creates projects, such as C:\Workspaces.</li>
                    <li>Choose Preferences from the Window Menu.</li>
                    <li>In the left pane, select Java &gt; Installed JREs</li>
                    <li>Add the JDK6 from the JAVA_HOME directory, and make it the Workspace default.</li>
                    <li>In the left pane, select Java &gt; Build Path &gt; Classpath Variables.</li>
                    <li>Click New.</li>
                    <li>Add M2_REPO in the Name field and the path of your M2 repository in the Path field (for example, C:\Programs\m2repo). 
                    This value is needed in order to import Maven generated project configurations.</li>
                    <li>In the left pane, select Server &gt; Runtime Environments &gt; Add &gt; Jbossv5 or v6</li>
                    <li>Click OK twice to close the dialog boxes.</li>
                    <li>Create a new JBoss server instance (Window &gt; Show View &gt; Other &gt; Servers &gt; Server) and start the instance from Eclipse.</li>
                    <li>We recommend the following plugins also be installed:</li>
                </ul>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Plugin</th>
                        <th>Repository or Download Location (* = Manual install)</th>
                        <th>Notes</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Sonatype M2Eclipse</td>
                        <td><a href="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/sites/m2e">http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/sites/m2e</a><p></p>
                        <a href="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/sites/m2e-extras">http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/sites/m2e-extras</a></td>
                        <td>Import maven projects, run maven from Eclipse. Instructions at <a href="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org">http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org</a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>SpringSource Tool Suite</td>
                        <td><a href="http://dist.springsource.com/release/TOOLS/update/e3.6">http://dist.springsource.com/release/TOOLS/update/e3.6</a>
                        <p><a href="http://dist.springsource.com/release/TOOLS/composite/e3.6">http://dist.springsource.com/release/TOOLS/composite/e3.6</a></p></td>
                        <td>Install instructions at <a href="http://download.springsource.com/release/STS/doc/STS-installation_instructions.pdf">http://download.springsource.com/release/STS/doc/STS-installation_instructions.pdf</a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>JBoss Tools</td>
                        <td><a href="http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/updates/development">http://download.jboss.org/jbosstools/updates/development/</a></td>
                        <td>If using JBoss server or Hibernate ORM. Install instructions at <a href="http://www.jboss.org/tools/download/installation/update_3_2.html">http://www.jboss.org/tools/download/installation/update_3_2.html</a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>PMD</td>
                        <td><a href="http://pmd.sourceforge.net/eclipse">http://pmd.sourceforge.net/eclipse</a></td>
                        <td>Code quality checker</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>CheckStyle</td>
                        <td><a href="http://eclipse-cs.sourceforge.net/update">http://eclipse-cs.sourceforge.net/update</a></td>
                        <td>Code quality checker</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>FindBugs</td>
                        <td><a href="http://findbugs.cs.umd.edu/eclipse-candidate">http://findbugs.cs.umd.edu/eclipse-candidate</a></td>
                        <td>Code quality checker</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Cobertura</td>
                        <td><a href="http://ecobertura.johoop.de/update">http://ecobertura.johoop.de/update</a></td>
                        <td>Code unit test coverage</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>SVN</td>
                        <td><a href="http://eclipse.svnkit.com/1.3.x">http://eclipse.svnkit.com/1.3.x</a></td>
                        <td>If using SVN repositories, integrate with Eclipse Subversive</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Velocity</td>
                        <td><a href="http://veloedit.sourceforge.net/updates">http://veloedit.sourceforge.net/updates</a></td>
                        <td>If editing Velocity templates</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
                
            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="What's Next?">
            <p>
                Now that the development environment is set up, we are ready to try out the TimeTracker application.
                Click <a href="timetracker-tour.html">here</a> to get started.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
