<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Bpm4Struts - FAQ</title>
        <gennews>no</gennews>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Frequently Asked Questions">
            <p class="std">
                This page contains answer to common questions about bpm4struts. Feel free to send your
                questions to the user list, I will make sure they will be posted here too.
                <blockquote>
                    <ol>
                        <li><a href="#q1">What does bpm4struts stand for ?</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q2">There is another Struts cartridge shipping with AndroMDA, why is that ?</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q3">When I try to run AndroMDA on my model I get an exception!</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q4">Is there a way to validate the correctness of my model ?</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q5">Why do I need to tag elements with stereotypes ?</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q6">Do I need to tag elements with tagged values ?</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q7">What tools can I use to model ?</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q8">I am not happy with the generated code, can I change it ?</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q9">I don't want a Struts application, I like Webwork better!</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q10">Can bpm4struts generate Java Server Faces too ?</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q11">Where is the online documentation ?</a></li>
                        <li><a href="#q12">I still have more questions!</a></li>
                    </ol>
                </blockquote>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Answers">
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q1"/>1. What does bpm4struts stand for ?
                <blockquote>
                    Bpm4Struts stands for: Business Modelling for Struts. It means you will be
                    able to create your Struts web application by modelling business processes.
                    Business processes in a Struts application typically involve displaying JSP pages and
                    sending requests to the server by means of actions performed on those pages, such
                    as button clicks or navigating using hyperlinks. These actions mostly result in code being executed
                    on the server (in the action itself, or better yet: delegated to the business layer),
                    it is this code which contains the business logic.
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q2"/>2. There is another Struts cartridge shipping with AndroMDA, why is that ?
                <blockquote>
                    The original Struts cartridge is legacy is only uses UML classes to model the application.
                    While it is possible to work this way it makes more sense to use the dynamic modelling model
                    elements available in modelling languages such as UML.
                    Bpm4Struts is now the preferred cartridge to use. The other one
                    should be considered deprecated.
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q3"/>3. When I try to run AndroMDA on my model I get an exception, what's going on ?
                <blockquote>
                    You have to make sure your model complies with the constraints as documented
                    in the user guide. Failing to do so will
                    confuse the cartridge and might have unpredicatable behavior such as exceptions or
                    undeployable Struts code.
                    A typical example would to forget to tag the first transition in an activity
                    graph with the FrontEndEvent stereotype.
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q4"/>4. Is there a way to validate the correctness of my model ?
                <blockquote>
                    Yes, and doing so will avoid problems with the code-generation process. Validating
                    the model is not enabled yet in the cartridge code, but it should happen soon enough.
                    What will happen is that when the model is loaded by AndroMDA each element
                    will have its own validation routine to check if its preconditions and
                    invariants are met. For each error or warning a message will be displayed to the user.
                    Model validation will be enabled by default and it will be possible to
                    switch it off using a property.
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q5"/>5. Why do I need to tag elements with stereotypes ?
                <blockquote>
                    Yes, and the reason is very simple: the cartridge maps stereotypes to templates.
                    This is a way of telling which files should be generated from what elements.
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q6"/>6. Do I need to tag elements with tagged values ?
                <blockquote>
                    No, but failing to do so will not enable some of the more interesting cartridge
                    features. Using tagged values you can enable the validation of form
                    input fields, for example. It depends on the context of the specific model
                    element whether or not a tagged value would be needed.
                    All tagged values have a default value, so if you don't
                    add one it' value will be implied.
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q7"/>7. What tools can I use to model ?
                <blockquote>
                    Currently only MagicDraw has been extensively tested, unfortunately this
                    is commercial software and requires a licence to run. Support for a
                    free tool such as Poseidon is underway.
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q8"/>8. I am not happy with the generated code, can I change it ?
                <blockquote>
                    Sure you can, openup the cartridge and go into the 'templates' directory.
                    You will find a bunch of templates, how they map onto files can be found
                    in the deployment-descriptor in the 'META-INF' subdirectory (next to 'templates').
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q9"/>9. I don't want a Struts application, I like Webwork better ... is bpm4struts for me ?
                <blockquote>
                    Not really, at this point there is no cartridge for Webwork, but it can easily
                    be written. Taking a look at how bpm4struts is designed will make it straightforward
                    to implement the same thing for Webwork.
                    This new cartridge could be called bpm4webwork ...
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q10"/>10. Can bpm4struts generate Java Server Faces too ?
                <blockquote>
                    No, JSF is not Struts. For more information go here:
                    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/faqs/kickstart.html#jsf">Apache Struts JSF Faq</a>
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q11"/>11. Where is the online documentation ?
                <blockquote>
                    There is the general documentation Bpm4Struts, there is a user-guide
                    and there is the how-to which serves as a small tutorial describing an example application.
                </blockquote>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <a name="q12"/>12. I still have more questions!
                <blockquote>
                    Subscribe to the mailing lists, there is one for the regular user community, and
                    there is one for the developers. Feel free to subscribe to both lists, but note
                    that the developer list can be quite active from time to time.
                    Go here: <a href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=73047">AndroMDA mailing lists</a>
                </blockquote>
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
