<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Bpm4Struts - HowTo</title>
        <gennews>no</gennews>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Modeling example">
            <p class="std">
                We want to get you kick-started so that you can get productive with this cartridge as soon as
                possible. For this reason this section describes a very small example that has been written especially
                for this wiki-page, this allows me to show more features with less application complexity.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                The application resembles an online store, the customer logs in, selects some items
                to buy, and proceeds to the payment. This all is modelled very roughly, the point is
                to teach you something about bpm4struts, not about online shopping.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                Please note that everything happens in UML! There is no hand-coding needed!
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                The application we are about to model consists of three pages:
                <ul>
                    <li>the first page expects the user to enter his name and password, his name must be
                        at least 3 characters and start with a capital, the password needs to be 6 characters
                        or more and consists of alphanumerical characters (both uppercase and lowercase), when
                        the user clicks on 'proceed' we go to the second page</li>
                    <li>the second page lists items that can be purchased, the user can select an arbitrary number of
                        items from this list, there is also a checkbox where to user can confirm he read
                        the store's licence</li>
                    <li>the third and last page asks the user to enter his email and creditcard number, he
                        also needs to enter his age, which must be in a range from 12 to 112. After placing
                        the order the application returns to the beginning</li>
                </ul>
                Each time we travel between pages the application will store this data in a database somewhere
                (this is transparent for us), but the fact this is done is also modelled in UML.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                Please note that in some cases you will see something slightly different on the images compared to what
                you see when you model it yourself, don't worry, it's me who played with the model
                so it would present nicely.
            </p>
            <h3>Identify the application use-cases</h3>
            <p class="std">
                This is pretty straightforward, it will also force you to think about what your application
                will be doing from a high-level perspective.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                Typical use-cases that you surely are familiar with are 'Login', 'Add item to basket',
                'Place order', etc...
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                In this case we only model a single use-case, let's call it "Purchase Items".
                First of all we create the application namespace, this is done by creating a (tree)
                of packages. In our case the package in which the use-case is put is called
                org.andromda.samples.bpm4struts.onlinestore.purchase
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <div>
                  <img src="images/create-usecase.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                It is very important that one and only one use-case is tagged with the 'FrontEndApplication'
                stereotype. You should take the first use-case because bpm4struts will use this
                use-case as the first one to which to forward control (the welcome page will redirect to it).
            </p>
            <h3>Specify each use-case in more detail</h3>
            <p class="std">
                When you have modelled your use-cases you are ready to tell a little more about them, do
                this by add one (only one!) activity graph to each of them, give it a good name
                (however, it will be ignored by the cartridge)
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <div>
                  <img src="images/add-activity-graph.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>
            <h4>The Initial State</h4>
            <p class="std">
                Add one and only one initial state, you do not need to give it a name, just make
                sure it has a single outgoing transition. Incoming transitions are not allowed on initial states. Since
                this initial state represents an action on the server (forwarding control to the first page)
                you are required to tag this transition using the FrontEndEvent stereotype.
            </p>
            <h4>Action States</h4>
            <p class="std">
                For different atomic events in the system you should model an action state, per convention an
                action state is represented in a diagram using a box with rounded corners.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                You are allowed to model action states even if there is no actual operation behind,
                you may use it to make your model more verbose. Give good names to your action state,
                that's very important.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                Create transitions between action states to express process flow.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                Take a look at the next image to see how it has been done for the sample.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <div>
                  <img src="images/model-action-states.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>
            <h4>Transitions and Parameters</h4>
            <p class="std">
                Each time data needs to be sent between action states you will model this using parameters on
                the transition between these states. More specifically use the trigger on that transition to
                carry the parameters. It does not really matter which type of event you choose, as long
                as it is the trigger (and not the effect) the cartridge will understand.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                Here are some images that show how to add parameters to a transition. We
                use the transition's trigger for this feature.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <div>
                  <img src="images/add-parameter-edit.jpg"/>
                </div>
                <br/>
                <div>
                  <img src="images/add-parameter-add.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                In the next images you can see how to specify that the server sends information to the client.
                In the JSP page these parameters will be exposed as page variables, if you choose to
                manually update you JSPs you can directly use them (you don't need manual updates to run
                the application, but you'll probably want to add layout and style ... this is not modeled in
                UML of course, we only model business processes here)
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <div>
                  <img src="images/model-parameters-0.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                In the next images you can see how a client sends parameters to the server, in fact, it is
                exactly the same as before. Only, this time these parameters will be shown on the page as
                an hyperlink or a form, depending on the fact the user can or cannot alter their respective
                values. The receiving action will have access to these values.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <div>
                  <img src="images/model-parameters-1.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>
                Once you have reached this point it is time to add stereotypes, you will need to tag the
                user pages with the FrontEndView stereotype, transitions going out of those pages must carry
                the FrontEndEvent stereotype. The transition going out of the initial state must also
                carry the FrontEndEvent stereotype.
            <p class="std">
                <div>
                  <img src="images/add-stereotypes-1.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>
            <h4>Decision Points</h4>
            <p class="std">
                Sometimes it is possible the sytem needs to make a decision and based on the outcome it must
                continue along a specific path. This is achieved by modeling something that is known as a decision
                point. A decision point is represented as a diamond shaped figure in the diagram. It has
                at least two outgoing transitions, and all of them must carry a guard.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                The incoming transitions must trigger a call-event that will return a value, this value is
                then matches against all possible guards. The first transition with a guard that matches
                the return value will be processed, the others are ignored.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                Take a look how all of this is done.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                { IMAGE HERE }
            </p>
            <h4>Deferrable Events</h4>
            <p class="std">
                All the action states that do not represent JSP pages represent action logic that is executed on the
                server-side. By default these actions do nothing specific, but optionally you may have them execute
                your custom code.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                In order to do that you can add deferrable events to the action state. These event must be
                call-events. The operations that can be called by such an event ar edetermined by the
                context of the activity graph. So you will need to set it first, here's how:
                <ul>
                    <li>Create a controller class</li>
                    <li>Give it the FrontEndController stereotype</li>
                    <li>Add operations to this controller class</li>
                    <li>Assign this controller class as the context of the activity graph, if your CASE tool
                        does not support this directly you can add a tagged value to the controller:
                        <code>@struts.controller.usecase = &lt;usecase-name&gt;</code>
                        By specifying the use-case name as the value you will assign this controller to be the
                        context of the use-case's activity graph.
                    </li>
                    <li>On the action states, optionally add deferrable events of type 'Call' and
                      reference an operation from the controller.</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                In order to show all these updates to the model you might need to enable this funtionality in your
                CASE tool, for example in MagicDraw you need to right-click on each action
                state and unselect 'Suppress Actions'.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <div>
                  <img src="images/model-controller.jpg"/>
                </div>
                <br/>
                <div>
                  <img src="images/assign-controller-1.jpg"/>
                </div>
                <br/>
                <div>
                  <img src="images/assign-controller-2.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                You may have as many deferrable events on an action state as you like. Events that
                are not of type 'Call' are ignored by the cartridge.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                The result of adding call-events is that on the server-side the action will execute
                each of these events before proceeding to the transition.
            </p>
            <h4>Final States</h4>
            <p class="std">
                Final states represent the end of the activity modelled in the activity graph,
                because we use a single graph to model a use-case a final state represent a
                possible end of the use-case.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                It is perfectly legal to have more than one final state, you might have one for "success"
                and one for "failure" for example. It is very important that the name of the final state
                is the same as the name of a use-case. This may be the same use-case as being modelled.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                We use the name here to interconnect use-cases, for the moment there is no easier or
                more correct way to model such behavior (if someone has an idea, please let me know :-) ).
                Checking for name ignores case. This means: give good descriptive and unique names to your use-cases.
            </p>
            <h3>Add users to your application</h3>
            <p class="std">
                This is a feature that will authorize access to use-cases only to users that have been authenticated.
                If you enable this (optional) feature your application might not run and thrown an exception
                indicating you have no permissions to continue.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                The only thing you need to do is associate users to your use-cases. Using your case tool this is
                possible by simply drawing an association between them.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                Users may generalize other users, for example a "Technical Manager" could have both "Manager"
                and "Developer" roles. Do this by associating "Technical Manager" to "Manager" and "Developer".
                <ul>
                    <li>buttons on pages will be rendered disabled accordingly</li>
                    <li>button tooltips will inform the user he is not allowed to call the specific action</li>
                    <li>actions will throw an exception if called (for example by specifying the URL manually in the
                        browser)</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                <div>
                  <img src="images/model-usecases.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
