<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Bpm4Struts - HowTo - Tables</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Tables">
            <p>
                It's possible to have the cartridge render tables for you from certain parameter
                modeled in UML. These tables are using the <a href="http://www.displaytag.org/">displaytag</a>
                tag-library behind the scenes.
            </p>
            <p>
                In order to have these tables rendered for you you will need to model a
                <a href="howto2.html#Page_Variables">page variable</a> that maps onto a descendant of
                <code>java.util.Collection</code> (for example <code>datatype::Collection</code>).
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                Do not specify type <code>java.util.Collection</code> directly, but use use
                <code>datatype::Collection</code> instead.
            </p>
            <p>
                 Next you will simply need
                to model one or more tagged values onto that parameter. (If you choose to specify more than
                one property per value you can also separate them using commas, nevertheless, it is
                recommended to specify a value per property)
            </p>
<source><![CDATA[
@andromda.struts.view.table.columns=property1,property2,...,propertyN
]]></source>
            <p>
                Just make sure that each property listed has corresponding accessor methods for each element
                in the collection parameter. This requirement cannot be checked during development so failing
                to conform to it will result in a runtime error.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Hyperlinks">
                <p>
                    It's very common that users want to click on a row in the table and continue to the next page,
                    possibly showing the item in more detail. It's possible to have this feature generated by
                    associating one of the table columns to one of the exiting actions on the same page.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In order to model this correctly you basically need to model a regular event with parameters,
                    as you have seen <a href="howto2.html#Event_Parameters">here</a>. Next it is sufficient to add
                    a tagged value to one of one of these event parameters and have it point to the desired table
                    (since there can be more than one). What will happen is that the action will be rendered into
                    each row of the table, the selected column depends on the name of the event parameter
                    but this can be overridden, as you will see in the next paragraph.
                    Any remaining event parameters will be included in the request query.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Use the <code>@andromda.struts.view.field.tablelink</code> tagged value, specify the name of the
                    table page variable followed by a dot and the name of the column, this event parameter will
                    assume it's value. If you do not specify the dot and the column name then the name of the event
                    parameter will be assumed. Here's an example:
                </p>
<source><![CDATA[
@andromda.struts.view.field.tablelink=itemList.id
]]></source>
                <p>
                    If the parameter on which this tag is modeled is called 'id', then this would be perfectly
                    equivalent to:
                </p>
<source><![CDATA[
@andromda.struts.view.field.tablelink=itemList
]]></source>
                <p>
                    The one thing remaining to do is tell the cartridge you want the value rendered as an hyperlink,
                    you do that like this:
                </p>
<source><![CDATA[
@andromda.struts.view.field.tablelink=itemList
@andromda.struts.view.field.type=link
]]></source>
                <p>
                    The <code>id</code> column of the table in the image below is showing the result:
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="resources/howto/org/andromda/test/online-store-table.gif"/>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Widgets">
                <p>
                    Not only hyperlinks can be rendered into a table, basically any kind of widget is allowed,
                    just change the <code>@andromda.struts.view.field.type</code> tag to any of the known values.
                    The <code>author</code> column (which is controlled by the <code>test</code> event parameter)
                    has these tagged values specified:
                </p>
<source><![CDATA[
@andromda.struts.view.field.tablelink=itemList.author
@andromda.struts.view.field.type=select
]]></source>
                <p>
                    Notice how the cartridge generated dummy data to populate the list. That way it's easy to
                    give your application a test-run before doing any manual coding.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Multibox">
                <p>
                    One very special type of widget, which is a little more complicated to understand at first, is
                    the <code>multibox</code> widget. Basically it allows you to render checkboxes whose
                    <code>checked</code> statuses need to be controlled by another property.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Let's say you want to render a checkbox for each row, but the value behind is not of a
                    <code>boolean</code> type but a <code>String</code>; in that case you can setup a page-variable
                    which holds an <code>array</code> or a <code>Collection</code> of <code>String</code> instances,
                    when a value for a specific row matches at least one of the elements the checkbox will be checked.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The <code>available</code> column of the table in the image above has the following tagged values:
                </p>
<source><![CDATA[
@andromda.struts.view.field.tablelink=itemList
@andromda.struts.view.field.type=multibox
@andromda.struts.view.field.multibox=availableItems
]]></source>
                <p>
                    In this example the <code>availableItems</code> page-variable is used to match the
                    <code>available</code> property against.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                Next up is the <a href="howto9.html">Other Content</a> section.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
