<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Bpm4Struts - HowTo (2)</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Activity Graphs">
            <p>
               These graphs allow you to express the way you want your application to behave, this is expressed
               by means of states and transitions. An activity graph therefore, by definition, is a
               <em>state machine</em>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Your activity graph should be modeled as a child element of the use-case. In case your modeling
                tool does not support that you can add a tagged value to the use-case, making it point to the
                activity graph, like this: <code>@andromda.struts.usecase.activity=My Activity Graph</code>
            </p>
            <p>
                On this page you will see how to use the different states, and how to express the flow from one
                state into another.
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                Custom code (methods) can be executed from an action state, you will learn about that in one of the
                later sections, click <a href="howto4.html">here</a> to immediately go there.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Initial States">
                <p>
                    Each use-case needs an <code>initial state</code>, an initial state is displayed as
                    a solid black disc. It denotes the starting point of the use-case, it can have no incoming
                    transitions and only one outgoing transition. Only a single initial state is allowed
                    per activity graph.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Since our example features only one use-case it will therefore
                    contain exactly one initial state.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="resources/howto/org/andromda/test/initial-states.jpg"/>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Action States">
                <p>
                    An action state represents a certain state in which the application can be recorded,
                    an action state is displayed as a rectangle with rounded corners. In bpm4struts you will
                    use action states for both server-side states (the controller: struts actions)
                    as client-side states (the view: JSP, VTL, ...).
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    Make sure the actual name property of each action state is unique in the activity graph.
                    Additionally, make sure the name is properly entered: sometimes people enter the action state's
                    <em>label</em> in the activity diagram instead of the real name of the element.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Client-side action states are tagged with the <![CDATA[<<FrontEndView>>]]> stereotype,
                    they represent a JSP and may have multiple outgoing transitions (one per call
                    to the server). It is not allowed to model a transition between two <![CDATA[<<FrontEndView>>]]>
                    action states.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Server-side action states do not need any stereotype but can only have a single outgoing
                    transition.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="resources/howto/org/andromda/test/action-states.jpg"/>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Action Parameters">
                <p>
                    Action parameters are parameters modeled on transitions exiting client-side action states
                    (the ones with the <![CDATA[<<FrontEndView>>]]> stereotype). Whenever you model such a transition
                    it represents a call to the server from a webpage, usually by sumbitting a form. The parameters
                    you model will represent the form fields.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Please note that you will need to add the parameters to the transition's <code>trigger</code>,
                    this trigger should be of type 'signal', but don't worry about that if your UML tool does
                    not support setting the type of the trigger.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="resources/howto/org/andromda/test/action-parameters.jpg"/>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Page Variables">
                <p>
                    Page variables are modeled the same way action parameters are, the only difference is that
                    you model them on transitions <em>entering</em> a <![CDATA[<<FrontEndView>>]]> action state.
                    In doing so the modeled parameters will be available in the generated JSP page.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="resources/howto/org/andromda/test/page-variables.jpg"/>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Decision Points">
                <p>
                    In some cases action states and transitions just aren't enough, a good example is when you
                    want to fork the flow based on a specific decision. Suppose you want to follow the first
                    transition if the user login credentials are valid, and follow the second transition if they
                    are invalid.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In order to do this we must need to be able to call an operation with a return value, on which
                    the decision is based. We will see how to do this later, click here
                    to proceed there now: <a href="howto4">Custom Code</a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Finally we must tag the transition indicating when it must be followed, in UML this is done
                    by means of <em>guards</em>. Not to make things overly complex it is not necessary to model
                    the OCL for the guard (very few tools properly support this), so instead it will be sufficient
                    to model the name of the guard, it must match the return value of the method call
                    (matching is done using <code>String.valueOf(returnValue)</code>).
                </p>
                <p>
                    Some modeling tools do not properly show the name of the guard in the activity diagram, in that
                    case you might consider copying the name also in the guard's body, this will be ignored by the
                    cartridge and might show it on screen for clarity.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="resources/howto/org/andromda/test/decision-points.jpg"/>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Final States">
                <p>
                    You may have as many final states as you want in an activity graph. In bpm4struts a final state
                    represents the and of the use-case and the flow into the next use-case. Final states are
                    displayed as bulls-eyes in activity diagrams.
                </p>
                <p>
                    There are two ways of modeling a final state: either you give it the name of the next use-case
                    (which can be the same as the current use-case), either you do not name it and you use a hyperlink
                    to the next use-case (this is not supported in all UML tools).
                </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="resources/howto/org/andromda/test/final-states.jpg"/>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                Use-cases usually execute custom code, later we will see how to do that, first you will
                need to understand how to assign a controller to a use-case, this is explained in the
                <a href="howto3.html">next</a> section.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
