<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Bpm4Struts Cartridge Namespace</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Bpm4Struts Cartridge Namespace Properties">
            <p>
                In addition to the applicable
                <a href="../andromda-metafacades-uml/namespace.html">UML Metafacade</a> namespace
                properties which may also be used, this page describes 
                namespace properties specific to this cartridge only.
            </p>
            <table>
                <tr>
                    <th>Property</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                    <th>Required?</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>pages</td>
                    <td>application JSP pages, login pages and stylesheets are outputted here</td>
                    <td>Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>forms</td>
                    <td>The location to which Struts action forms are generated.</td>
                    <td>Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>actions</td>
                    <td>The location to which Struts actions are generated.</td>
                    <td>Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>controllers</td>
                    <td>The location to which abstract controllers are generated.</td>
                    <td>Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>controller-impls</td>
                    <td>The location to which the controller implementation classes are generated.</td>
                    <td>Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>messages</td>
                    <td>The location to which message resource bundles are generated.</td>
                    <td>Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>configuration</td>
                    <td>
                        The location to which Struts configuration files are generated. These are the files
                        that typically appear in WEB-INF, such as validation-rules.xml and tiles-defs.xml.
                    </td>
                    <td>Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>server</td>
                    <td>The location where to store application server specific configuration, such as users.properties
                        and roles.properties (in case security has been enabled)</td>
                    <td>No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>security</td>
                    <td>Whether or not to render code enabling the security features (true/false)</td>
                    <td>No, default is
                        <code>false</code>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>securityRealm</td>
                    <td>The security realm to use when security is enabled.</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>other</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>xhtml</td>
                    <td>true/false on whether or not xhtml should be rendered (instead of just normal html).</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>false</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>welcomeFileName</td>
                    <td>The name of the JSP that is the welcome file.</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>index.jsp</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>clientValidation</td>
                    <td>true/false, denotes if the client should validate user input.</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>true</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>serverValidation</td>
                    <td>true/false, denotes if the server should validate user input.</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>true</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>maxBreadCrumbs</td>
                    <td>an integer denoting the maximum number of breadcrumbs to appear on a
                        page, specify zero to disable breadcrumbs</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>5</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>dummyData</td>
                    <td>true/false, denotes whether or not to render dummy data in things like controllers.</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>true</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>onlineHelp</td>
                    <td>true/false, denotes whether or not to render online help pages.</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>true</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>defaultDateFormat</td>
                    <td>The default date format to use in case it has not been explicitely
                        specified, for example for action parameters of type Date.
                        Take a look
                        <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/api/java/text/SimpleDateFormat.html">here</a>
                        to see how to properly construct date formats.
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>dd/MM/yyyy</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>warningMessagesKey</td>
                    <td>The key to lookup warning messages in a scope, the value will be an 
                        <a href="http://struts.apache.org/api/org/apache/struts/action/ActionMessages.html">
                        ActionMessages</a> instance</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>org.andromda.bpm4struts.warningmessages</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>successMessagesKey</td>
                    <td>The key to lookup success messages in a scope, the value will be an 
                        <a href="http://struts.apache.org/api/org/apache/struts/action/ActionMessages.html">
                        ActionMessages</a> instance</td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is
                        <code>org.andromda.bpm4struts.successmessages</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>hints</td>
                    <td>
                        True/false on whether or not hints should be rendered in the generated
                        JSP pages.
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is <code>true</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>defaultActionRedirect</td>
                    <td>
                        True/false on whether or not redirection should occur on all action forwards.
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is <code>false</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>backendType</td>
                    <td>
                        With this property it is possible to control the generation of pieces of controller code
                        that allow referencing the services, for each dependency going from the
                        &lt;&lt;FrontEndController&gt;&gt; to a &lt;&lt;Service&gt;&gt; an accessor will be generated.
                        Possible values are: <code>ejb</code>,
                        <code>webservice</code> and <code>spring</code>. Generated code is compliant with each
                        corresponding cartridge. Other values might produce uncompilable code.
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        No, default is an empty String (no code is generated).
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
