<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Spring - HowTo (2)</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Relationships">
            <p>
                Most of the entities that appear in real applications have relationships with other
                entities, consider the simple case of a person owning a car. Here we say
                <code>Person</code> has an <code>owning</code> relationship with the <code>Car</code>, and from
                the perspective of the person there can be any number of cars that are owned, denoted in UML
                by <code>[0..*]</code> at the car's end. Make sure the association ends are <code>public</code>
                (some tools allow to specify the visibility of an association end).
            </p>
            <p>
                In UML relationships are modeled using associations, and associations themselves have different
                properties, which will be discussed here.
            </p>
            <p>
                Let's model another entity now, call it <code>Person</code> and give it a few attributes,
                just make sure you given them one of the platform independent datatypes that can be mapped
                onto a platform specific datatype (you can find them in the <code>datatype</code> package).
            </p>
            <p>
                Draw an association between both entities you have just modeled. Set the multiplicity at the end
                of the car to <code>[0..*]</code> and name the other end <code>'owner'</code>.
                Run AndroMDA again on your model, this is what you should see:
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="2/uml.png"/>
            </p>
            <p>
                In this example we have added two attributes: name of type <code>datatype.String</code>
                and birthDate of type <code>datatype.Date</code>; please note that also for this entity
                an identifier will be added by default. If you explicitely want to add an identifier you should
                add the <![CDATA[<<PrimaryKey>>]]> stereotype to an attribute.
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                A zip bundle containing all these files can be downloaded here:
                <a href="resources/howto2.zip">howto2.zip</a>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="2/Car.hbm.xml.html"><code>Car.hbm.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="2/Car.java.html"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="2/CarImpl.java.html"><code>CarImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/CarDao.java.html"><code>CarDao.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/CarDaoBase.java.html"><code>CarDaoBase.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="2/CarDaoImpl.java.html"><code>CarDaoImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="2/Person.hbm.xml.html"><code>Person.hbm.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="2/Person.java.html"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/PersonImpl.java.html"><code>PersonImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/PersonDao.java.html"><code>PersonDao.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/PersonDaoBase.java.html"><code>PersonDaoBase.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/PersonDaoImpl.java.html"><code>PersonDaoImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/ejb-jar.xml.html"><code>ejb-jar.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/jboss.xml.html"><code>jboss.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/applicationContext.xml.html"><code>applicationContext.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="2/beanRefFactory.xml.html"><code>beanRefFactory.xml</code></a></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                As you can see the relationships have been generated in the code:
                <ul>
                    <li>Person.getCars() : Collection</li>
                    <li>Car.getOwner() : Person</li>
                </ul>
                By default AndroMDA will look at the multiplicity to generate a good name for the relationship,
                a few examples where the multiplicity is greater than one:
                <ul>
                    <li>car: cars</li>
                    <li>property: properties</li>
                    <li>toy: toys</li>
                    <li>animal: animals</li>
                    <li>bus: busses</li>
                </ul>
                You can override these names by adding your own names to the association ends, in our example
                you might set the name of the association end at the side of the person to <code>owner</code>,
                this will emit the following output during generation:
                <ul>
                    <li>Person.getCars() : Collection</li>
                    <li>Car.getOwner() : Person</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                Optionally you may indicate the relationship is part of an <code>aggregate</code> or
                <code>composite</code> association. You should use aggregation when an entity is part of another one but the
                latter one does not need the former to exist.
                <ul>
                    <li>aggregation: lazy-loaded, no cascade</li>
                    <li>composition: eager-loaded, cascade update</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                Don't forget to properly set the multiplicity on the association ends, this will ensure
                the proper code is generated.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                In the next section we'll learn about services, click
                <a href="howto3.html">here</a> to continue.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
