<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Spring - HowTo (4)</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Value Objects">
            <p>
                In many cases it is a good idea to never expose your persistence layer to the presentation layer
                directly,
                this dependency could cause your application to be difficult to maintain. For that reason one can
                use value objects, these are simple classes that simply encapsulate information to be presented
                to an end-user. Although these value objects represent different views on the existing business
                objects, they do need to map onto those objects directly. Most of the time you will want to
                collect some information coming from several entities. For this reason value objects are
                <i>coarse-grain</i> objects.
            </p>
            <p>
                Probably the most common situation where value objects are used is the one where you have a list
                of items to be displayed, selecting one of the will show that item's
                details in its entirety. Here we have two value objects: one for the representation in the list, and
                one for the detailed view.
            </p>
            <p>
                In the spring cartridge you can simply model your value objects to be classes with the
                <![CDATA[<<ValueObject>>]]> stereotype, you then add attributes for all fields you want to be
                present. Doing this will generated a simple Java class adhering to the Java Bean specification.
            </p>
            <p>
                An interesting feature is that you can draw a dependency from any <![CDATA[<<Entity>>]]> to a
                <![CDATA[<<ValueObject>>]]>. This will instruct the cartridge to generate a transformation
                method in the entity's DAO class, this transformation method can be called directly or
                it can be invoked from any finder or load operation that exists: just use the
                public constant associated with this transformation and specify it as the optional
                transformation flag, the next example will clarify this in detail.
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="4/uml.png"/>
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                A zip bundle containing all these files can be downloaded here:
                <a href="resources/howto4.zip">howto4.zip</a>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
                    <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
                    <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/Car.hbm.xml.html"><code>Car.hbm.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/Car.java.html"><code>Car.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="4/CarImpl.java.html"><code>CarImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="4/CarDao.java.html"><code>CarDao.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="4/CarDaoBase.java.html"><code>CarDaoBase.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="4/CarDaoImpl.java.html"><code>CarDaoImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="4/CarListItem.java.html"><code>CarListItem.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a class="changed" href="4/CarDetails.java.html"><code>CarDetails.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/Person.hbm.xml.html"><code>Person.hbm.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/Person.java.html"><code>Person.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/PersonImpl.java.html"><code>PersonImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/PersonDao.java.html"><code>PersonDao.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/PersonDaoBase.java.html"><code>PersonDaoBase.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/PersonDaoImpl.java.html"><code>PersonDaoImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/RentalService.java.html"><code>RentalService.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/RentalServiceBase.java.html"><code>RentalServiceBase.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="impl"><a href="4/RentalServiceImpl.java.html"><code>RentalServiceImpl.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/ejb/RentalService.java.html"><code>ejb/RentalService.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/ejb/RentalServiceBean.java.html"><code>ejb/RentalServiceBean.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/ejb/RentalServiceHome.java.html"><code>ejb/RentalServiceHome.java</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/ejb-jar.xml.html"><code>ejb-jar.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/jboss.xml.html"><code>jboss.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/applicationContext.xml.html"><code>applicationContext.xml</code></a></li>
                    <li class="gen"><a href="4/beanRefFactory.xml.html"><code>beanRefFactory.xml</code></a></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                Please note that an entity may be dependent on any number of value objects, and
                different entities may be dependent on the same value object.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                As promised we'll learn how to model entity finders and have the Query Language automatically
                generated, the <a href="howto5.html">next</a> section will go into more details.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
