<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>
            Add Page Variable to Activity Diagram
        </title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Add Page Variable to Activity Diagram">

            <p>
                This page provides directions to add the
                <tt>timecardSummaries</tt>
                page variable
                to the
                <tt>Search Timecards</tt>
                activity diagram. The activity diagram is shown
                below for reference. Note that ArgoUML does not show information about the transition
                trigger (page variable) on the diagram itself.
            </p>

            <p>
                <img src="images/SearchTimecardsAD1.png" alt="Search Timecards Activity Diagram"/>
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Click on the transition out of
                    <tt>Populate Search Screen</tt>
                    and go to its
                    property panel at the bottom of the screen.
                </li>
                <li>Right-click in the field called &quot;Trigger&quot; and select NewSignal Event.</li>
                <li>Leave the name field as blank - this is the only difference between modeling an
                    event (coming out of a view) and a page variable.
                </li>
                <li>Click on the New Parameter tool
                    <img src="images/ToolNewParameter.png" alt="New Parameter Tool"/>.
                </li>
                <li>In the Parameter property panel, enter
                    <tt>timecardSummaries</tt>
                    as the name of the parameter and
                    <tt>TimecardSummaryVO[]</tt>
                    as its type.
                </li>
                <li>Click on the Tagged Values tab and click first blank field in the left column and
                    select the type
                    <tt>@andromda.presentation.view.table.columns</tt>
                    from the
                    pulldown menu. This tagged value tells AndroMDA to render the page variable as a
                    table. In the value column to the right, enter the following column names for
                    the value:
                    <br/>
                    <tt>id, submitterName, approverName, status, startDate</tt>
                    <br/>
                    This tells AndroMDA to display 5 columns in the table corresponding to the 5 attributes
                    of <tt>TimecardSummaryVO</tt>. (Note that the TimeTracker prototype does
                    not have an
                    <tt>Id</tt>
                    column in the results table. However, we add it here
                    so that the
                    <tt>id</tt>
                    is available to each row.)
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                We have now added the
                <tt>timecardSummaries</tt>
                page variable to the
                <tt>Search
                    Timecards
                </tt>
                activity diagram. Please go back to the main tutorial page
                and continue from where you left off.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
