<document>
  <properties>
    <title>EJB3 Cartridge Plugin Project</title>
    <author email="vance@andromda.org">Vance Karimi</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="1.0-SNAPSHOT" date="2006-06-01" desc="Changes for 1.0-SNAPSHOT">
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Introduced changes.xml and report.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Added manageable entity support.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Added JBoss cache support.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Set default discriminator value consisting of first character of entity name if one isn't
        explicitly specified.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Added DAO support for every entity POJO.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Refactored javax.ejb package for interceptor related annotations to javax.annotation.
        NOTE: These annotations are NOT used anyway since interceptor components are configured
        via XML descriptor.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Added Maven reporting facilities to site generation. Using new AndroMDA site skin for site
        generation.  To run these reports, the following Maven report plugins need to be installed.
        Some may only exist on the Maven sandox.  maven-site-plugin, maven-project-info-reports-plugin,
        maven-javadoc-plugin, maven-surefire-report-plugin, maven-jxr-plugin, maven-pmd-plugin,
        maven-checkstyle-plugin, maven-changes-plugin and maven-changelog-plugin.  The maven-changelog-plugin
        will require you to have cvs.exe (if on windows platform) in your path.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Many-to-Many association owning side JoinTable - JoinColumn name property fixed. JIRA EJB-25
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        NamedQuery definition to pick up firstResult and maxResult arguments modelled with these
        stereotypes and NOT include then in where clause.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Added installation howto.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="add">
        Added equals, hashCode and toString methods to entities.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Updates to bring up to date with EJB 3.0 FR.
        Now require JBoss 4.0.4-GA with EJB 3.0 RC8-PFD update.
        Update include
          @javax.annotation.EJB --> @javax.ejb.EJB
          Interceptor related classes and annotations moved to javax.interceptor package.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        MDB base class must implement javax.jms.MessageListener to avoid the following error message
        on deployment:
           java.lang.RuntimeException: unable to determine messagingType interface for MDB
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="remove">
        Removed container configuration option via tagged value on message driven beans since it
        is no longer supported.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Added minimumPoolSize (@andromda.ejb.mdb.pool.size.min) and maximumPoolSize
        (@andromda.ejb.mdb.pool.size.min) tagged value options for message 
        driven beans i.e. to allow singleton message driven beans.  These are added as
        activation config properties to the ejb-jar.xml.  Added documentation.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Updated the EJB3MetafacadeModel.xml to use the maven2.repository environment variable rather than
        hard coded paths for profiles.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        If session bean is a Seam component, then don't set the bean type to stateful if the bean contains an
        attribute.  For session bean Seam components, the only way to specify it as a SFSB is via tagged value on
        the class.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Don't restrict rendering of accessor methods for session bean attributes that only have 'public'
        visibility.  Accessors generated for all attributes for all visilities.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Introduce JBoss Seam components corresponding with Seam 1.0.0-CR3.
        Always generate a local interface for a session bean if it is a Seam component.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-27 - If a session bean operation is modelled for the local view type interface, a local interface is 
        NOT generated.  When returning a view type from the EJB3SessionFacade, must lookup all business operations to 
        determine their view type individually and return a view type for the session bean to accomodate local,
        remote and both.
        Refactor service delegate templates and introduce a parent base class which all service delegates extend.
        Fix problem with exposing only remote operations as webservice endpoints.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="add">
        JIRA EJB-28 - Added support for adding ejb-jar elements to the persistence.xml.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="update">
        Generate documentation for enumeration literals.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Inheritance hierarchies where the super class is a mapped superclass, the subclass should not
        render the DiscriminatorValue annotation.  This annotation should only be rendered in subclasses of
        single table inheritance hierarchies.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Added FAQ support section menu to site.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Remove references to attributes modelled with a @Version annotation (optimistic lock value for entity) in 
        manageable service components.  Initial work removed attribute from getAttributes, but that caused problems
        from the manageable web tier action methods create and update. To account for this, allow the attribute as
        argument to the methods, but do not call the corresponding setter.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Moved the @Version annotation to the entity attribute.  It had no effect on the getter method.
        Removed all annotations on the corresponding getter method.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Render the @Table annotation on every entity to avoid application server detting the default table name
        mapped to by this entity.  Currently, the annotation is only rendered when there is an inheritence hierarchy
        or a mapped superclass.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Update the default Collection for one-to-many and many-to-many associations to the java.util.SortedSet (in
        namespace.xml).  
        Moving away from bag collection as the default since it is unnecessary in the majority of cases.  
        As a result, the @org.hibernate.annotations.Sort annotation is also rendered with a NATURAL sort type.
        The create and update methods of the manageable service implementation wraps the retrieved bag collection(List)
        for the 'many' side of the association with an appropriate collection implementation (unless java.util.List
        is specified as the default).
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Ignore the argument on create and update methods of DAO implementation components where the corresponding 
        entity attribute is modelled as an optimistic lock value with the Version stereotype.  This should be improved
        to eliminate the attribute when retrieving the attribute collection.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Each finder is overloaded in the DAO components.  One finder method that doesn't supply a manual query 
        argument should use the NamedQuery defined on the corresponding entity.  Currently, it generates the query.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Minor fixes to the EJBQL of the finder methods in the manageable service base for manageable entities.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        In the findAll method of the manageable service base implementation, the query now includes 'left join fetch'
        for all related 'many' association ends where the target entity does not define a display attribute (where
        the attribute is modelled with the Unique stereotype).
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Updated the metafacade definitions of EJB3AssociationEndFacadeLogicImpl, EJB3AssociationEndFacadeLogicImpl
        and EJB3MessageDrivenOperationFacadeLogicImpl in metafacade.xml.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Added support for default list, set and map type implementations for collection association ends in 
        namespace.xml.  Also added the ability
        for association end collection index name and type (further map support) to be specified via tagged values 
        @andromda.persistence.collection.index and @andromda.persistence.collection.index.type.  This introduced
        a new facade called EJB3TypeFacade.
        Every collection type association end now instantiates the corresponding implementation upon
        declaration.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Fixed isRequired in EJB3AssociationEndFacade and EJB3EntityAttributeFacade to exclude property if
        the entity has a generalization to an mapped superclass.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        EJB3ManageableEntityAssociationEndFacade now also extends EJB3AssociationEndFacade with precedence tagged value
        set.  EJB3ManageableEntityAttributeFacade also extends EJB3EntityAttributeFacade.  This eliminates the
        need for the existing overwritten methods in the manageable entity facades.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-34 - Fix erroneous signature of entity constructor where no entity attributes exist but navigable 
        associations do exist.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Revert the build back to using the default Java compiler (1.4) - 1.5 isn't supported for the automated
        build process for andromda-plugins.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="add">
        JIRA EJB-31 - Add support for a select few meta type annotations for attribues in embedded value classes. 
        Need to confirm if @Transient, @Version, @Lob and @Basic are supported.  @Column, @Temporal and @Enumerated 
        have been confirmed to work.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="add">
        JIRA EJB-32 - Add support for embedded value object associations as well as attribute overrides.
        NOTE: This is still partial support.  The association mutators need to be added with appropriate
        annotation to the embedded value object base abstract class.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-33 - Fix problem when there are two embedded value objects of the same type in the same entity. 
        Fix for both attribute and association overrides.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="update">
        JIRA EJB-29 - the implementation class of the embedded value object was unused and the base class was abstract.
        This is now fixed with the introduction of the orm.xml deployment descriptor.  Currently, only
        the embeddable classes are defined.  As a result the @Embeddable annotation is removed from the base abstract
        class and the embeddable implementation class is now the defined as the embeddable class using orm.xml rather
        than metadata annotation.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="pawel" type="fx">
        JIRA EJB-36 - Entities and composite primary keys now implement Comparable interface and implement the 
        compareTo method.
        @org.hibernate.annotations.Sort annotation is only set if the collection interface for an association end
        is defined as java.util.SortedSet.  
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Added basic JBoss Seam documentation to site docs.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tlu" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-37 - Fix problem with service delegate switch statement where the break statement should not be
        issued after a return statement. 
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="sverker" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-38 - The query in the DAO base class for finder methods with argument enum type has to set 
        the enum class as the parameter for the querty, not the value (name or ordinal).
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Reset EJB3ManageableEntityAttributeFacade metafacade mapping in metafacades.xml from using property element
        to use context element.  Otherwise, manageable entity attributes would map to EJB3EntityAttributeFacade.
        This resulted in getTemporalType being refactored in EJB3EntityAttributeFacade and the overriding instance
        in EJB3ManageableEntityAttributeFacade to be removed.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        The getter (for BLOB type manageable attributes) in the manageable service base implementation must cast 
        the single result to appropriate type before returning.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Add @RolesAllowed annotation with permitted roles authorised to access the manageable service. This was
        achieved by introducing a new namespace property called <b>manageableRolesAllowed</b> rather than defined
        by actors with dependencies on the manageable entity.  A corresponding getManageableRolesAllowed
        is available through EJB3ManageableEntityFacade to retrieve the formatted comma separated list of roles.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Modelling non-public operations on session beans rendered incorrect method signatures.  This fix will
        generate correct signatures for all operations, but only public methods are exposed in the remote/local 
        interfaces and service base class.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Updated the cartridge.xml to set the outlet for the enumerations template to a new outlet called
        user-types.  This is defined in namespace.xml and must exist in each project andromda.xml.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="sverker" type="update">
        JIRA EJB-39 - Add serialVersionUID to DaoDefaultException.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="KnisterPeter" type="update">
        Changed defaultCollectionInterface namespace property to java.util.TreeSet from
        java.util.SortedSet.  This eliminates the need for the @org.hibernate.annotations.Sort annotation
        on collection association ends.  Aim is to decouple the EJB3 cartridge (with default settings) to Hibernate.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        It is invalid to specify an implementation for defaultCollectionInterfac.  This must specify an
        interface.  Changed from java.util.TreeSet to java.util.Set.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Allow the ability to specify unidirectional associations without having to specify an aggregation or
        composition end.  The non-navigable end is assumed to be the owning end of the association.
        This fix renders the mappedBy property for OneToOne annotations on the inverse side of the association.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="sverker" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-40 - Fix support for modelling map associations ends.
        "The attached patch solves this issue as well as providing an improvement in regards to List associations. 
        If no OrderBy tagged value is provided, the IndexColumn annotation is used (hibernate extension) to provide 
        true list association." - The hibernate annotation needs to be switched depending on the persistence
        provider.  This will be fixed once a namespace property is introduced along the lines of
        persistenceProvider.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Generate JBoss MQ destinations service XML descriptor when hot deployed under JBoss, creates
        the Queue/Topics.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="KnisterPeter" type="update">
        Added new namespace property persistenceProviderExtensions.  Default value is none.  Currently, ony
        hibernate extensions are supported.  If set to hibernate, then hibernate specifc annotations are
        rendered in appropriate locations based on the model.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Updated installation howto to give more accurate directions on getting and building the EJB3 cartridge.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="sverker" type="update">
        JIRA EJB-41 - Cleaned unused imports and some calls to deprecated methods changed to their replacements.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="sverker" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-42 - Fix IllegalStateException "it is illegal to inject UserTransaction into a CMT bean" where a 
        session bean is modelled with bean managed transactions.  This fix sets the <b>transaction-type</b>
        for the session to <b>Bean</b> instead of <b>Container</b>.  This does not affect manageable entity session
        POJOs as they remain container managed transaction demarcation.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="Bertl" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-43 - Fix issues with the default setup of association cascade properties, in particular adding
        support for multiple cascade options for the default cascade property on entities.  Fix the naming
        issue with entityAggregationCascade.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        EJB3MessageDrivenFacade.getDestinationType requires search and replace for destination type retrieved
        from TV.  i.e. replace all '_' with '.'.  Also fix casing for javax.jms.Queue and javax.jms.Topic.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        UMLMETA-78 - Add support for member variables within type safe enumerations.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Demo EJB3 added to andromda-plugins/samples accompanied by quick site docs.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Fix getIdentifier naming in EJB3EntityFacade which eliminates the workaround solution in 
        EJB3ManageableEntityFacade.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="markh" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-45 - ClassCastException when setting Manageable stereotype on entities.  The 
        EJB3ManageableEntityAttributeFacade was not being picked up correctly.  Instead, the 
        emf.uml2.ManageableEntityAttributeFacade was used.  The fix was to simply override the methods returning
        attributes and identifiers in EJB3ManageableEntityFacade.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="harwey" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-46 - Missing javax.ejb.Timer attribute for method on session bean
        modelled as a timeout callback.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="turekvl" type="fix">
        Fix in GlobalMacros.vm to prevent compareTo action on entity properties with Collection/List/Set types.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="harwey" type="fix">
        Add javax.jms.MessageListener messaging-type to ejb-jar.xml for MDBs.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Migrated dependency versions from 3.3-SNAPSHOT to 3.2, overriding dependencies in the pom.xml.
        NOTE: This can be removed once the andromda-plugins package is upgraded as a whole.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Added maven-changelog-plugin, taglist-maven-plugin and jdepend-maven-plugin reporting.  Also added scm
        settings to project pom.xml.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="tp" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-48 - Fix misspelt property names in EntityEmbeddable.vsl for table and sequence generator types.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Moved the changes.xml to src/site.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="sverker" type="add">
        JIRA EJB-47 - Complete remaining support for JBoss Seam within the EJB3 cartridge.  Now uses 
        andromda-plugins-profile-seam profile.  Support for AndroMDApp project generator in AndroMDA 3.3-SNAPSHOT.
        This (EJB3 cartridge with Seam support) is NOT a replacement for the Seam cartridge, but another tool which 
        can be used with the Seam cartridge to develop Seam (JSF)/EJB 3.0 enabled web application.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Fix Entity - EntityVO conversion methods in the DAO base classes by adding the Converter
        template object to the cartridge.xml and the necessary namespace property to namespace.xml.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Inject org.hibernate.Session into DAO base class if hibernateExtensionEnabled is true.  This can be used
        to create Hibernate Search Criteria.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Fix DAO injection into DAO base when entity references another entity.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="rajtuz" type="fix">
        Fix incorrect method name in EJB3MetafacadeUtils.convertTransactionType() for transaction type NotSupported.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Refactored remote and local jndi lookup code generation by extracting to macro in the templates.  This is
        now used by ServiceLocator.vsl and SessionTest.vsl.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Add support for the JBoss Embedded EJB3 server for testing using TestNG.  Cartridge will generate all
        required microcontainer configuration files, an EJB3Container intitialiser that starts and shuts down
        the container before and after all tests, a testng.xml config file and basic test class per session bean
        modelled.  The embeddable container version is ALPHA_9.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Finally added cartridge tests!
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Add support for MDB testing within embedded EJB3 container.  Further customised test templates.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Resource libs jms-ra.rar and jcainflow.rar are copied to src/test/resources folder of the core project
        for testing of message driven test cases.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Added EJB3MappedSuperclassFacade and EJB3MappedSuperclassAttributeFacade metafacades extending EJB3EntityFacade
        and EJB3EntityAttributeFacade respectively.  This enables the ability to model a mapped superclass by modelling
        only the MappedSuperclass stereotype.  The existing way required the Entity stereotype as well as the 
        MappedSuperclass stereotype.  This excludes a mapped superclass in the group of manageable entities, if entities 
        are modelled as Manageable as well.  
        Also added 2 constraints to the EJB3EntityFacade class.  These constraints override
        the default identifier check and generalization check constraints in the parent Entity metafacade.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="Wzzl" type="fix">
        Set default topic subscription durability as NonDurable in case a Topic does not have the subscription
        durability TV modelled.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="heapifyman" type="fix">
        Fix entity constructor generation when no attributes modelled but operation and associations exist.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="jonnyBgood" type="fix">
        Fix support for abstract super entity (add super to class declaration) even when super entity is not a 
        mapped superclass or specializes another entity. This also cleaned up the constructor implementation in
        the inheriting entity.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        If transaction type specified on the class level and not on the method level, do not generate the
        @TransactionAttribute on the method.  Similarly, if not modelled on the class level, do not generate it there.
        It doesn't make sense to have this annotation at the class level of the parent bean as class level annotations
        are not inherited.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Remove handleDestroy abstract method in SessionBeanBase.  This was not being called correctly by
        Seam.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Session bean base classes now implement a super interface.  Local and remote business interfaces 
        extend this super interface. Session bean implementations now extend the business interface(s).
        This does introduce manual modification when refactoring a session bean's business interface.
        The super interface contains common constants and attribute mutator definitions.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Update persistence.xml descriptor with schema and namespace attributes.
        Added provider org.hibernate.ejb.HibernatePersistence property.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="add">
        Expand on JBoss Seam support.  Move Entity and Session bean Seam component declaration to newly added
        components.xml.
        This means removing @org.jboss.seam.annotations.Name and @org.jboss.seam.annotations.Scope annotations.
        Only specify the @org.hibernate.validator.NotNull annotation on identifier attributes in entity Seam pojos
        if identifer is explicity modelled and explicity defined as not null.
        The ejb-jar.xml descriptor will NOT allow remote business interface declaration where the session bean
        is a Seam component.
        Add interceptors definition to ejb-jar.xml for the SeamInterceptor.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        By default, if a Seam component does not have it's scope type specified, then the default stateless
        scope type is assigned to stateless session beans and a conversation scope type is specified for all
        other types of beans.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Specify the full package path for ScopeType and FlushModeType where the scope  
        or the flushMode parameters are required in Seam annotations.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="fix">
        Fix URLs in howto6.xml for referencing main AndroMDA project.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="Obfuscator" type="update">
        Update the cartridge to reflect the changes for MDB in JBoss 4.0.5.GA.  These changes include rename of
        activation config from durability to subscriptionDurability, the addition of mdb-subscription-id in jboss.xml
        when a topic is durable, removal of minPoolSize activation config and rename of maxPoolSize to maxSession
        activation config.  Reference http://galaxy.andromda.org/forum/viewtopic.php?p=21537#21537.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="khwalk" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-54 - Fix entity level annotations for multiple level single table inheritance hierarchy.  When generating a one
        level hierarchy, the @Table and @DiscriminatorColumn annotations exist on the top level entity.  However,
        when there is a multi-level single table inhiertance hierarchy, these 2 annotations exist on every parent
        entity.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="heapifyman" type="add">
        JIRA EJB-51 - Provide support for Hibernate cascade on association ends by modelling the 
        @andromda.hibernate.cascade tagged value.  This will only work if Hibernate extensions is enabled
        (persistenceProviderExtensions namespace property is set to hibernate). This request was for the
        org.hibernate.annotations.CascadeType.DELETE_ORPHAN cascade type on the one-to-many end, however
        support for this annotations is provided for all association types.  It's up to the user to restrict
        this annotations suitably. i.e. Only specify the DELETE_ORPHAN on the one-to-many end.
        To add more than one cascade property, simply comma separate the types when setting the value of
        the @andromda.hibernate.cascade tagged value.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="khwalk" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-53 - When a modelled entity with a MappedSuperclass stereotype has an association to another
        entity, the association definition in this other entity is incorrectly named.  The resolution is to
        avoid appending Embeddable to the mapped superclass and don't apply a naming pattern when a mapped superclass
        is explicity modelled.  It is fine to apply this naming pattern when this is not explicitly modelled and
        instance scoped operations exist on the entity and a mapped superclass is generated.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="daveangulo" type="add">
        JIRA EJB-50 - Add UUID generic generator support as a Hibernate extension.  This will render the
        @GenericGenerator annotation.  Modified the persistence profile (uml1.4 and 2.0) to support the necessary 
        tagged value.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" type="update">
        Fix naming of the serviceRemoteInterfaceName property to serviceRemoteInterfaceNamePattern.
      </action>
      <action dev="vancek" due-to="dima" type="fix">
        JIRA EJB-55 - Fix optimistic locking - version attribute.  Set the annotation on the getter and change
        modifier on version attribute to public.
      </action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>