<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="wouter@andromda.org">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Spring - Tips</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Tips for using the AndroMDA Spring cartridge">
            <p>
                This section provides you with some pointers that might prove helpful when using AndroMDA with
                the Spring cartridge.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Exceptions">
            <p>
                It's not needed to model exceptions for all the services you model, the Spring cartridge will
                generate them automatically for you. That way you don't need to keep writing
                <code>try/catch</code> blocks in the <code>handleXXX</code> methods in the service implementation
                classes, just throw any error, it will be handled for you.
            </p>
            <p>
                So basically this snippet is a good example of an implementation of a service operation, there is
                no need to catch any exception and rethrow it:
<source language="java"><![CDATA[
protected PersonDetails handleGet(Long id) throws Exception
{
    return (PersonDetails)getPersonDao().load(PersonDao.TRANSFORM_PERSONDETAILS, id);
}
]]></source>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Running without EJBs">
            <p class="highlight">
                If you have told <code>andromdapp:generate</code> to generate a WAR-only project (i.e. for deployment
                in Tomcat) EJBs will be disabled by default and you won't need to worry about this section.
            </p>
            <p>
                With the change of a single line it is possible to enable or disable the usage of stateless session
                EJBs, simply put the <![CDATA[<session-ejbs>]]> outlet in comment, like this
                (this is done in <code>mda/conf/andromda.xml</code>):
<source language="xml"><![CDATA[
<namespace name="spring">
    <properties>
        ...
        <!--
            <property name="session-ejbs">${maven.andromda.core.generated.dir}</property>
        -->
        ...
    </properties>
</namespace>
]]></source>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Beware of lazy loading!">
            <p>
                  Unless an Association is composition-modeled, all associations
                  collections are made <a href="profile.html#@andromda_hibernate_lazy">lazy</a> by
                  default. While this is very nice to avoid retrieving the whole
                  database on each query, you should be aware that each
                  time you invoke a method on a <a href="howto3.html">Spring Service</a>, a Hibernate
                  Session is opened at the beginning and closed at the end of the call.
            </p>
            <p>
                  The consequence of this is that every persistent object that was retrieved in the body
                  of a Service method is unable to retrieve its associations lazily outside this very call.
            </p>
            <p>
                  For example: if the <code>user</code> parameter in the following code was obtained as the result
                  of calling a Spring service method, and that user has a lazy <code>group</code> association,
                  and the following is another Spring Service method,
                  it would raise a <code>net.sf.hibernate.LazyInitializationException</code>:
            </p>
<source language="java"><![CDATA[
protected boolean doSomethingWithUserGroups(User user) throws Exception
{
    ...
    java.util.Collection userGroups = user.getGroups ();
    java.util.Iterator everyUserGroup = userGroups.iterator(); // this call would generate the exception
    ...
}
]]></source>
        </section>
        <section name="Connecting to JBoss with Remote EJBs">
            <p>
                When connecting to a remote EJB wrapped Spring service deployed in JBoss, its possible you'll get
                the following exception:
<source>
org.springframework.beans.factory.BeanCreationException: Error creating bean with name 'transactionManager' defined in c
lass path resource [applicationContext-dataSource.xml]: Initialization of bean failed; nested exception is org.springfra
mework.transaction.TransactionSystemException: JTA UserTransaction is not available at JNDI location [java:comp/UserTran
saction]; nested exception is javax.naming.NameNotFoundException: UserTransaction not bound
org.springframework.transaction.TransactionSystemException: JTA UserTransaction is not available at JNDI location [java:
comp/UserTransaction]; nested exception is javax.naming.NameNotFoundException: UserTransaction not bound
javax.naming.NameNotFoundException: UserTransaction not bound
        at org.jnp.server.NamingServer.getBinding(NamingServer.java:491)
        at org.jnp.server.NamingServer.getBinding(NamingServer.java:499)
        at org.jnp.server.NamingServer.getObject(NamingServer.java:505)
        at org.jnp.server.NamingServer.lookup(NamingServer.java:278)
</source>
                To get around this, place the following 2 properties in your <em>spring</em> namespace:
                <source language="xml"><![CDATA[

<namespace name="spring">
    ...
    <property name="userTransactionName">null</property>
    <property name="transactionManagerName">java:/TransactionManager</property>
    ...
</namespace>
                ]]></source>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Using foreign services">
            <p>
                You can connect to "foreign" spring services, which are not implemented  in your application but in
                another one (e.g. a other ear), as with "normal" services: just draw a dependency to the "foreign"
                service class. The foreign service class has to be defined as any other service but without any method
                or property.
            </p>
            <p>
                To prevent the spring cartridge from generating java code you have to exclude the packages with a
                process="false" statement in the andromda configuration just in your appropriate
                <code>&lt;model&gt;</code> tag:
                <source language="xml"><![CDATA[
<modelPackages>
    <modelPackage process="false">de::my::foreign.package::name</modelPackage>
</modelPackages>
                ]]></source>
                (look at http://team.andromda.org/docs/configuration.html#modelPackage)
                The spring cartridge will generate the dependency code for the source class (property class with
                getter/setter) and the bean-ref tag in the spring application context file. The only thing you now
                have to do is to provide the "foreign" spring bean definition file to your application context (in the
                beanRefFactory file).
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
