<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="chad@andromda.org">Chad Brandon</author>
        <author email="wouter@andromda.org">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA Developer Coding / Patching Conventions</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Foreword">
            <p>
                This document describes a list of coding conventions that are required for
                code submissions to AndroMDA. By default, coding conventions for
                most Open Source Projects should follow the existing coding conventions in
                the file that you are working on. For example, if the bracket is on the
                line after the if statement, then you should write all your code to have
                that convention.
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li><a href="#AndroMDA_Developer_Coding_Conventions">Coding conventions</a></li>
                    <li><a href="#Submitting_Patches">How to submit a patch</a></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="AndroMDA Developer Coding Conventions">
            <p>
                Below is a list of coding conventions that are specific to AndroMDA. 
                Anything else not specifically mentioned here should follow the official 
                <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/html/CodeConvTOC.doc.html">Sun Java Coding Conventions</a>.
            </p>
            <subsection name="General Coding Conventions">
                <p>
                    The following applies to any code, whether it be templates, java files, XML files, etc.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Indentations:</strong> 4 spaces. <strong>NO tabs</strong>. Period.
                            We understand that a lot of you like to use tabs, but the fact of the
                            matter is that in a distributed development environment, when the cvs
                            commit messages get sent to a mailing list, they are almost impossible
                            to read if you use tabs.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            Another requirement is to set the right margin to 120 characters, so lines break
                            if they exceed this limit. A shorter limit is not acceptable since it will break
                            lines sooner and will disrupt the look and feel of the code.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                 </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Java Coding Conventions">
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Brackets:</strong> All brackets (class, method, if, try, etc)
                            must begin and end on a new line. Example :
                        </p>
                      <source language="java">
public class SomeClass
{
    public void someMethod()
    {
        if (xxx)
        {
        }
    }
}
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Whitespace:</strong> Do not add extra whitespace
                            around parenthesis (i.e. "if ( this.isComposition() )") or casts
                            ("(ClassifierFacade) element"), instead they should be written
                            written like the following:
                        </p>
                        <source language="java">
if (this.isComposition()) 
{
}
                        </source>
                        <source language="java">
ClassifierFacade classifier = (ClassifierFacade)element;
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Iterators:</strong> Looping using an iterator, do these in for-loops
                            instead of while loops (because this allows the iterator itself to be scoped
                            into that block). Example:
                       </p>
                       <source language="java">
for (Iterator stereotypeIterator = stereotypes.iterator(); stereotypeIterator.hasNext();)
{
    ModelElement stereotype = (ModelElement)stereotypeIterator.next();
    stereoTypeNames.add(stereotype.getName());
}                        
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Comments:</strong> Javadoc SHOULD exist on all your class members
                            (methods + class variables), including the private ones. Also, if you are
                            working on existing code and there currently isn't a javadoc for that
                            method/class/variable or whatever, then you should contribute and add it.
                            This will improve the project as a whole.  Also add code comments when
                            you think it's necessary (like assumptions), especially when the code
                            is not obvious.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                           <strong>Author References:</strong> If you contribute to a file (code or documentation),
                           add yourself to the top of the file (below the existing authors). For java files
                           the preferred Javadoc format is:
                        </p>
                        <source>
@author FirstName LastName
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Exiting Methods:</strong> There should be only a single
                            point of exit out of a method (i.e. a single return statement).
                        </p>
                        <source language="java">
public int getEntityCount()
{
    // don't do this:
    /*
        if (condition)
        {
           return 6;
        }
        return 0;
    */

    // but do this:
    int entityCount = 0;

    if (condition)
    {
        entityCount = 6;
    }

    return entityCount;
}
                       </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Variable Names:</strong> <em>attr</em> should be written
                            as <code>attribute</code>, <em>collIdents</em> should be
                            <code>identifiers</code> (the type is Collection, don't specify that
                            in the name), <strong>the code should read as plain English</strong>.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <strong>Instance Variables:</strong> Instance variables should not have any
                        prefix and must be referenced using the <em>this</em> object. Example :
                        <source language="java">
public class SomeClass
{
    private String someString;
    ...
    public void someMethod()
    {
        logger.debug("Value = " + this.someString);
    }
}
                       </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <strong>Parameter Names:</strong> Method parameters should not have any
                        prefix. For example :
                        <source language="java">
public void someMethod(String className)
{
}                        
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Strings:</strong> Avoid hardcoding values, Strings as well as
                            numbers, etc should go into a properties file or a class holding constants.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Imports:</strong> Use fully qualified import names when importing classes,
                            this makes it easier for users not familiar with the code base to see where classes
                            are coming from.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Logging:</strong> Do <strong>NOT</strong> use System.out.println()
                            for debugging purposes in your code, instead use a log4j logger.
                        </p>
                        <source language="java">
try
{
   ...
}
catch (Exception ex)
{
    logger.error("Some error has occurred" + ex);
}
                        </source>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            <strong>Exception Recording:</strong> Do <strong>NOT</strong> use ex.printStackTrace()
                            for debugging purposes in your code, instead use the provided ExceptionRecorder class.
                        </p>
                        <source language="java">
try
{
   ...
}
catch (Exception ex)
{
    logger.error("Some error has occurred" + ex);
    ExceptionRecorder.instance().record( ex );
}
                        </source>
						<p>
							This will create a .exc file with the stacktrace and additional
							debugging and environment information:
<pre>
------- AndroMDA Exception Recording -------
Version ........: 3.0-RC2-20050420181638
Error ..........: Error performing ModelProcessor.process with model(s) --> 'jar:file:/home/martin/ews30andromda/workspace/andromda-all/cartridges/andromda-webservice/src/test/uml/WebServiceCartridgeTestModel.xml.zip!/WebServiceCartridgeTestModel.xml'
Build ..........: 2005-04-20 18:16:38
Build System ...: Linux-2.6.11-suspend2
Build JDK ......: Sun Microsystems Inc.-1.4.2_07-b05
Build Builder ..: martin
Run System .....: Linux2.6.11-suspend2
Run JDK ........: Sun Microsystems Inc.1.4.2_07-b05
Main Exception .: Error performing MDRepositoryFacade.readModel
Root Exception .: java.lang.OutOfMemoryError
java.lang.OutOfMemoryError
	
</pre>							
						</p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Template Coding Conventions">
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                           <strong>Referencing properties:</strong> In Velocity (etc) try to do
                           <code>$variable.property</code> instead of <code>$variable.getProperty()</code>,
                           the two calls are equivalent but the former better matches our metamodels
                           (and is less code to write).
                        </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Committing Code into CVS">
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                           As always, make sure to have a clear comment supporting your change in CVS,
                           if something goes wrong others might help to track down the problem by
                           reading the history.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            If you fixed, added, updated or removed a feature then update
                            <code>/documentation/changes.xml</code>.
                            Take a look at previous changes for examples.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Submitting Patches">
            <p>
                As always, use <a href="http://jira.andromda.org/">JIRA</a> to submit feature requests
                and patches.
            </p>
            <p>
                If you have modified your local version by adding a new feature and would like to see in the main
                distribution, then file a new issue in JIRA and attach the patch to it (please do not send it to
                the mailing list).
            </p>
            <p>
                If you want to see your patch quickly applied by committers, you should be able to provide
                the following items:
            </p>
            <ol>
                <li>A CVS diff against the latest CVS version. No, a zip file with all modified sources is *not*
                    okay.</li>
                <li>If appropriate, include one or more JUnit tests related to the new feature.
                    Also, be sure to run all of the existing testcases to verify that you are not breaking existing
                    code.</li>
                <li>Where applicable, update the documentation (namespace/modeling docs, samples, ...).</li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                If all of these requirements are met and you are respecting the coding conventions,
                then it is very likely your patch will be accepted soon.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
