<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="wouter@andromda.org">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - How-to Guides</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="How-to Guides">
            <p>
                A few guides have been written to make it easier to get started using AndroMDA
                on your projects, on this page you will find the links to those guides.
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul class="textList">
                    <li>
                        <a href="starting.html#My_first_AndroMDA_project">Project Generator</a><br/>
                        <strong>This getting started guide is *highly* recommended newbie material.</strong><br/>
                        Explains how to set up a new project template in which you use AndroMDA to generate
                        code from your UML model. The project templates have been specifically designed
                        for J2EE applications.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="andromda-bpm4struts-cartridge/howto.html">Bpm4Struts Cartridge</a><br/>
                        <strong>This howto will teach you how to model your presentation layer.</strong><br/>
                        Bpm4Struts is a cartridge that is able to generate Struts code from activity
                        graphs and use-cases. This guide briefly explains the way you should approach
                        and eventually model your application's architecture.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="andromda-spring-cartridge/howto.html">Spring Cartridge</a><br/>
                        <strong>This howto will teach you how to model your persistence and application layer,
                            also recommended for people using the EJB and/or Hibernate cartridges.
                        </strong><br/>
                        The Spring cartridge is used to generate your application's back end, it generates Spring
                        services (optionally wrapped by Session EJBs) using Hibernate POJOs for persistence.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="andromda-cartridges/manageable-entities/index.html">Manageable Entities</a><br/>
                        <strong>Generate all your CRUD features in a matter of minutes</strong><br/>
                        Explains what is needed to generate CRUD pages, services and DAOs. This feature generates
                        an administration console for your entities that works out-of-the-box, and that will perfectly 
                        integrate with the existing application.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="configuration/server-howto.html">AndroMDA Server</a><br/>
                        <strong>Significantly speedup the code generation process</strong><br/>
                        In this short howto you'll learn what the AndroMDA server can do for you and how to configure
                        and start it.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
