<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="chad@andromda.org">Chad Brandon</author>
        <title>AndroMDA Profiles</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="AndroMDA Profiles">
            <p>
                People sometimes ask: "Can I change the stereotype names?, I really don't like using the capitalized <em><![CDATA[<<Entity>>]]></em>
                to denote an entity, I'd rather use the lowercase <em><![CDATA[<<entity>>]]></em> instead."  Well in order to provide this ability to 
                customize existing AndroMDA profiles (as well as creating your own), AndroMDA has the concept of customizable profile descriptors.  
                This XML configuration file (which must be named <em>andromda-profile.xml</em> and reside in the <em>META-INF</em> directory) 
                allows someone using AndroMDA to map stereotypes, tagged values, and data types to ANY names he or she  wants without having to 
                change <code>ANY</code> code.
            </p>
            <p>
                Lets have a look at the contents of what a typical andromda-profile.xml file might contain (this snippet was taken from
                the UML metafacades <em>andromda-profile.xml</em> file):
                <source language="xml">
<![CDATA[
<mappings name="uml">
    <!-- stereotypes -->
    <mapping>
        <from>CRITERIA</from>
        <to>Criteria</to>
    </mapping>
    <mapping>
        <from>ENTITY</from>
        <to>Entity</to>
    </mapping>
    ...
    <!-- tagged values -->
    <mapping>
        <from>DOCUMENTATION</from>
        <to>documentation</to>
    </mapping>
    <mapping>
        <from>PERSISTENCE_TABLE</from>
        <to>@andromda.persistence.table</to>
    </mapping>
    <mapping>
        <from>PERSISTENCE_COLUMN</from>
        <to>@andromda.persistence.column</to>
    </mapping>
    <mapping>
        <from>PERSISTENCE_COLUMN_LENGTH</from>
        <to>@andromda.persistence.column.length</to>
    </mapping>
    ...
    <!-- datatypes -->
    <mapping>
        <from>COLLECTION_TYPE</from>
        <to>datatype::Collection</to>
    </mapping>
    <mapping>
        <from>LIST_TYPE</from>
        <to>datatype::List</to>
    </mapping>
    <mapping>
        <from>SET_TYPE</from>
        <to>datatype::Set</to>
    </mapping>
    ...
</mappings>              
]]>      
                </source>
            </p>
            <p>
                If you'll familiar with AndroMDA <a href="mappings.html">mappings</a> you'll notice that the above profile is in the same structure: you have the <![CDATA[<from/>]]>
                element which is the profile constant, and the <![CDATA[<to/>]]> element which is to what the constant should be mapped.   These andromda-profile.xml files
                are loaded during AndroMDA startup and made available to the framework. 
            </p>
            <subsection name="Overriding Profile Values">
                <p>
                    In order to customize a specific profile mapping value, one must override that value by creating his/her own
                    profile mapping and letting AndroMDA know its location by using the <em>profileMappingsUri</em> property.  
                    For example, this profile mappings file below would allow us to change the stereotype indentifying an entity to 
                    <![CDATA[<<entity>>]]> instead of the default <![CDATA[<<Entity>>]]>  (the <em>ENTITY</em> profile constant
                    is defined in the andromda-profile.xml of the UML metafacades jar which we saw above).  Once we provide
                    this customized mappings file AndroMDA will now recognize model elements with the stereotype <![CDATA[<<entity>>]]> :
                    <source language="xml">
<![CDATA[
<mappings name="CustomProfile">
    ...
    <mapping>
        <from>ENTITY</from>
        <to>entity</to>
    </mapping>
    ...
</mappings>      
]]>  
                    </source>                                    
                    After writing your profile mappings file (the mappings named "CustomProfile" we wrote above), you'd then define the location of this mappings 
                    file as the namespace property <em>profileMappingsUri</em> (within the mda/project.xml file or your mda/build.xml if using Ant), like
                    we do here (notice that the path must be a URI):
                    <source language="xml">
<![CDATA[
<namespace name="default">
    <properties>
        ...
        <property name="profileMappingsUri">file:${basedir}/mda/conf/mappings/CustomizedProfileMappings.xml</property>
        ...
    </properties>
</dnamespace>
]]>
                    </source>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
