<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="mbohlen@mbohlen.de">Matthias Bohlen</author>
        <title>AndroMDA.com Professional Services: Training</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Training for AndroMDA users">
            <p> While the Open Source model employed by <a 
                href="http://www.andromda.org/">AndroMDA.org</a> makes it very easy for you to get 
                access to AndroMDA software, becoming productive quickly requires special expertise 
                and guidance that can come through the <a 
                href="http://www.andromda.com/">AndroMDA.com</a> training program. Even seasoned 
                professionals will benefit from regular training to remain up-to-date with the 
                latest advanced AndroMDA technologies and techniques. To meet this requirement, <a 
                href="mbohlen@mbohlen.de">Matthias Bohlen</a> has founded <a 
                href="http://www.andromda.com/">AndroMDA.com</a> and has developed a curriculum of 
                courses that are available through both public and private on-site training 
                courses. </p>
            <p>Choose <a href="http://www.andromda.com/">AndroMDA.com</a> Training Services 
                when:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You are new to AndroMDA and need to get up-to-speed quickly</li>
                <li>You are experienced with AndroMDA technology and want a refresher course or to 
                    learn about new capabilities in the latest release</li>
                <li>You would like to better understand new technical directions in the field of 
                    model driven architecture and want to learn about it from the experts leading 
                    the innovation</li>
                <li>You need to train multiple people from your organization at your location 
                    (on-site training)</li>
                <li>You wish to customize the training module to better meet the specific needs of 
                    your staff (on-site training)</li>
            </ul>
            <p><a href="http://www.andromda.com/">AndroMDA.com</a> offers a number of different 
                public training courses that take place in major business cities in Germany. The 
                number of participants is purposely kept to max. 10 students per course in order to 
                maximize the experience of the attendees.</p>
            <p>Private hands-on training courses enable you to train a team of developers at one 
                time at your own site. There is also some flexibility in the course curricula 
                allowing you to tailor the training course to meet your specific needs - both in 
                terms of subject matter and knowledge-level of your staff.</p>
            <p> <a href="http://www.andromda.com/">See the AndroMDA.com website</a> for more 
                information on available training courses. </p>
            <p> I'll be happy to welcome you in one of the courses! </p>
            <p>
                <a href="mbohlen@mbohlen.de">Matthias Bohlen</a>
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>