<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="naresh@andromda.org">Naresh Bhatia</author>
        <title>AndroMDA for Java</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Getting started with AndroMDA for Java">
            <p>
                <strong>Note: This tutorial has been superseded by a new one with several
                enhancements including Maven 2 support and front-end construction.
                Click <a href="http://www.andromda.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=category&amp;sectionid=11&amp;id=42&amp;Itemid=89">here</a> to follow the new tutorial.</strong>
            </p>

            <p>
                Understanding new tools and technologies can be a daunting task. AndroMDA
                is no exception. This tutorial serves as a gentle introduction to the power
                of AndroMDA. We will show you step-by-step how to set up your development
                environment and build your first Java application. Instead of mechanically
                going through a series of steps, we will focus on ideas and concepts. Armed
                with this knowledge you will be ready to take on real world challenges.
                Please set aside half a day of quality uninterrupted time to learn AndroMDA
                as there is lot to learn. Then brew a good cup of coffee and immerse yourself
                in the wonderful world of Model Driven Architecture.
            </p>

            <p>
                Let us start by reviewing some foundational concepts that form the basis
                of most modern enterprise applications. After reviewing these concepts
                we will discuss how AndroMDA implements them in the applications it
                generates.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Application Architecture">
            <p>
                Modern enterprise applications are built using several components connected
                with one another, each providing a specific functionality. Components
                that perform similar types of functions are generally grouped into layers.
                These layers are further organized as a stack in which components in a
                higher layer use the services of components in the layer below. A component
                in a given layer will generally use the functionality of other components
                in its own layer or the layers below it. The diagram below shows a popular
                layer structure for an enterprise application.
                <p>
                    <div align="center">
                        <img src="images/ApplicationArchitecture.jpg"/>
                    </div>
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><strong>Presentation Layer:</strong> The presentation layer
                    contains components needed to interact with the user of the
                    application. Examples of such components are web pages, rich-client
                    forms, user interaction process components etc.</li>

                    <li><strong>Business Layer:</strong> The business layer encapsulates
                    the core business functionality of the application. Simple business
                    functions can be implemented using stateless components whereas complex
                    long running transactions can be implemented using stateful
                    workflows. The business components are generally front-ended
                    by a service interface that acts as a facade to hide the complexity
                    of the business logic. This is commonly known as Service-Oriented
                    Architecture (SOA).</li>

                    <li><strong>Data Access Layer:</strong> The data access layer provides
                    a simple API for accessing and manipulating data. The components
                    in this layer abstract the semantics of the underlying data access
                    technology thus allowing the business layer to focus on business
                    logic. Each component typically provides methods to perform
                    Create, Read, Update, and Delete (CRUD) operations for a specific
                    business entity.</li>

                    <li><strong>Data Stores:</strong> Enterprise applications store their
                    data in one or more data stores. Databases and file systems are two
                    very common types of data stores.</li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            <p>
                Note that layers are simply logical groupings of components that make up
                an application. How these layers are deployed on physical machines can
                vary widely depending on several factors. In the very simplistic scenario
                all the layers can reside on one machine. In a slightly more complex
                scenario, the presentation layer can reside on one machine, the business
                and data access layers on a second machine and the database on a third
                machine. More elaborate scenarios are possible. For example, a high traffic
                web site can deploy the presentation layer on a web farm consisting of
                tens of machines.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Architecture of AndroMDA Generated Applications">
            <p>
                Now that we understand the basic concepts behind modern enterprise
                applications, let's discuss how AndroMDA implements these concepts.
                AndroMDA takes as its input a business model specified in the
                Unified Modeling Language (UML) and generates significant portions
                of the layers needed to build a Java application. AndroMDA's ability to
                automatically translate high-level business specifications into production
                quality code results in significant time savings when implementing
                Java applications. The diagram below maps various application layers
                to Java technologies supported by AndroMDA.
                <p>
                    <div align="center">
                        <img src="images/JavaApplicationArchitecture.jpg"/>
                    </div>
                </p>

                <ul>
                    <li><strong>Presentation Layer:</strong> AndroMDA currently offers
                    two technology options to build web based presentation layers:
                    <a href="http://struts.apache.org/"  target="_blank">Struts</a>
                    and <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/javaserverfaces/download.html"  target="_blank">JSF</a>.
                    It accepts UML activity diagrams as input to specify page flows and
                    generates Web components that conform to the Struts or JSF frameworks.</li>

                    <li><strong>Business Layer:</strong> The business layer generated
                    by AndroMDA consists primarily of services that are configured using
                    the <a href="http://www.springframework.org/"  target="_blank">Spring Framework</a>.
                    AndroMDA creates blank methods in implementation
                    classes where business logic can be added. Generated services can
                    optionally be front-ended with EJBs. In this scenario the services
                    must be deployed inside an EJB container such as
                    <a href="http://www.jboss.org/"  target="_blank">JBoss</a>. Services
                    can also be exposed as Web Services, providing a platform independent
                    way for clients to access their functionality. AndroMDA can also generate
                    business processes and workflows for the
                    <a href="http://www.jboss.com/products/jbpm" target="_blank">jBPM</a>
                    workflow engine (part of the JBoss product line).</li>

                    <li><strong>Data Access Layer:</strong> AndroMDA leverages the
                    popular object-relational mapping tool called
                    <a href="http://www.hibernate.org/"  target="_blank">Hibernate</a>
                    to generate the data access layer for applications. It generates
                    data access objects (DAOs) for entities defined in the UML model.
                    These data access objects use the Hibernate API to convert
                    database records to objects and vice-versa.</li>

                    <li><strong>Data Stores:</strong> Since AndroMDA generated
                    applications use Hibernate to access the data, you can use
                    any of the databases supported by Hibernate.</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Data Propagation Between Layers">
            <p>
                In addition to the concepts discussed above, it is important to understand
                how data propagates between various layers of an application. Let us start
                from the bottom up.
            </p>

            <p>
                As you know, relational databases store data as records in
                tables. The data access layers fetches these records from the database
                and transforms them in to objects that represent entities in the business
                domain. Hence these objects are called business entities.
            </p>

            <p>
                The data access layer passes the business entities to the business layer
                which performs business logic using these entities.
            </p>

            <p>
                The last thing to discuss is the propagation of data between the business
                layer and the presentation layer. There are really two schools of thought
                on this subject. Some people recommend that the presentation layer should
                be given direct access to business entities. Others recommend just the
                opposite, i.e. business entities should be off limits to the presentation
                layer and that the business layer should package necessary information into
                so called "value objects" and transfer these value objects to the
                presentation layer. Let's look at the pros and cons of these two approaches.
            </p>

            <p>
                The first approach (entities only, no value objects) is simpler to implement.
                You do not have to create value objects or write any code to transfer
                information between entities and value objects. In fact, for simple small
                applications where the the presentation layer and the service layer run
                on the same machine this approach will probably work just fine. However for
                larger more complex applications this approach does not scale well. Here's
                why:

                <ul>
                    <li>Business logic is no longer contained in the business layer.
                    It is tempting to freely manipulate entities in the presentation layer
                    and thus spread the business logic in multiple places - definitely a
                    maintenance nightmare. In case there are multiple front-ends to a service,
                    business logic must be duplicated in all these front-ends. In addition,
                    there is no protection against the presentation layer corrupting the
                    entities - intentionally or unintentionally!</li>

                    <li>When the presentation layer is running on a different machine (as
                    in the case of a rich client), it is very inefficient to serialize
                    a whole network of entities and send it across the wire. Take the
                    example of showing a list of orders to the user. In this scenario,
                    you really don't need to transfer the gory details of every order to
                    the client application. All you need is perhaps the order number,
                    order date and total amount for each order. Later if the user wishes
                    to see the details of a specific order, you can always serialize that
                    entire order and send it across the wire.</li>

                    <li>Passing real entities to the client may pose a security risk.
                    Do you want the client application to have access to the salary
                    information inside the Employee object or your profit margins
                    inside the Order object?</li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            <p>
                Value objects provide a solution for all these problems. Yes, they require
                you to write a little extra code, but in return you get a bullet-proof
                business layer that communicates efficiently with the presentation layer.
                You can think of a value objects as a controlled view in to one or more
                entities that is relevant to your client application. Note that AndroMDA
                provides some basic support for translation between entities and value
                objects as you will see in the tutorial.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Services and Hibernate Sessions">
            <p>
                Another key concept about AndroMDA generated applications is the strong
                association between service methods (i.e. operations exposed by a service)
                and Hibernate sessions. But before we introduce this concept we must
                lay out some ground work. The Hibernate session is a runtime object that
                allows an application to create, read, update and delete entities in the
                data store. As long as the session is "open", these entities are attached
                to the session and you can navigate from one entity to another using
                relationships between them. If a related entity is not yet in
                memory Hibernate will automatically pull it in for you (this is called
                "lazy loading"). However as soon you close the Hibernate session,
                the entities that exist in memory are considered to be "detached", i.e.
                Hibernate no longer knows about them. You are free to hold
                references to such entities but Hibernate will no longer pull in
                associated entities if they don't exist in memory already. If you
                accidentally try to access such associated entities you will get a Hibernate
                <code>LazyInitializationException</code>.
            </p>

            <p>
                Now that we understand this background material, let us discuss the
                relationship between a service method and a Hibernate session. When a client
                application calls a service method a new Hibernate session is opened
                automatically. You do not have to write any code to do this. Similarly,
                when the service method exits the associated Hibernate session is closed automatically.
                In other words, the lifespan of a Hibernate session is bounded by the
                beginning and ending of a service method call. Consequently, entities
                are attached to Hibernate session for the entire duration of the service
                call, but are detached from this session as soon as the service call ends.
                As a result, if your service method returns raw entities, the client must
                be extra careful not to access related entities that are not in memory already.
                Anyway, you can avoid all this by following the recommendation in the
                earlier section, i.e. transfer all relevant information into value
                objects while the session is still open and pass these value objects back
                to your caller as a return value. In other words, think of a service method
                as a logical transactional boundary - do everything you need to do within
                the method and then return the results as value objects.
            </p>

            <p>
                Another implication of the strong association between a service method
                and a Hibernate session is that client applications should not try to
                bypass the service layer and interact directly with the lower layers.
                You may be able to brute force your way into one data access object,
                but sooner or later you will get into trouble!
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="What's Next?">
            <p>
                Now that you understand the basic tenets of AndroMDA, let's describe
                the sample application we will implement in this tutorial.
                Click <a href="sample-application.html">here</a> to get started.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
