<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - The Animal Quiz sample application</title>
        <gennews>no</gennews>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="The Animal Quiz sample application">
            The animal quiz sample application is part of a set of samples showing what you can do
            with AndroMDA. In order to get the sources for this sample you are required to download
            an AndroMDA 3.x distribution.
            <p class="std">
                This sample consists of a single use case generated using the following cartridges:
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Tier</th>
                        <th>Technology</th>
                        <th>Cartridge</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Persistence (Hibernate) and Business (Stateless Session EJBs)</td>
                        <td>Hibernate 2.x.y and EJB 2.0 (Stateless Session EJBs)</td>
                        <td>andromda-hibernate-cartridge</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Presentation</td>
                        <td>Struts 1.2 (dev)</td>
                        <td>andromda-bpm4struts-cartridge</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                When playing the game the server will ask you to keep an animal in mind, he will try to guess
                it until he runs out of guesses.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                The server will either try to guess your animal or ask a question so it can narrow down the list
                of possible animals. You will need to answer the question honestly (no cheating! :-) ).
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                There are two scenarios to a game-over. Either the server guessed your animal correctly, either
                it failed in doing so. In the latter case the server will be curious and will want to know your animal.
                It will propose you to enter the animal followed by a question that will distinguishes this animal
                from the last one guessed, this way it is able to use this animal in future games..
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                This application has been generated from a UML model modeled using
                <a href="http://www.magicdraw.com">MagicDraw 7.5</a>, you can find the model
                <a href="resources/AnimalQuiz.xml.zip">here</a>, this file contains a zipped XMI 1.4.
            </p>
            <p class="std">
                A running instance of this sample has been put online for everybody to test, check it out here:
                <a href="http://team.andromda.org:8080/AnimalQuiz">http://team.andromda.org:8080/AnimalQuiz</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
