<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <author email="cwbrandon@users.sourceforge.net">Chad Brandon</author>
        <author email="amartinwest@users.sourceforge.net">Martin West</author>
        <title>Recent AndroMDA changes</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <release version="3.0M3-SNAPSHOT" date="2004-12-19" description="The most recent CVS snapshot for version 3, milestone 3">
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add" issue="CORE-33">
                The ability to filter (or select) the cartridges you want 
                to perform model processing has been introduced.  Please see 
                <a href="maven-andromda-plugin/properties.html#maven.andromda.cartridgeFilter">maven.andromda.cartridgeFilter</a> 
                for more information on how to use this new featuire with the maven plugin, or
                <a href="anttask.html#cartridgeFilter">cartridgeFilter</a> for more information
                on how to use it directly with the AndroMDA Ant task.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add" issue="CORE-23">
                Merge support has been enabled: A new namespace property named 
                <code>mergeMappingsUri</code> has been introduced which allows you 
                to defined mapping files for merging.  These files behave just like the
                other mapping files (i.e. languageMappings, sqlMappings, etc) and can be
                used within each namespace or within the default namespace. Please see
                <a href="andromda-cartridges/index.html#mergeMappingsUri">mergeMappingsUri</a> 
                for more information.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add" issue="OCL-5">
                Translation of OCL to Hibernate QL has been improved to use named (instead
                of unnamed) parameters, please see the issue for more detailed information.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                The Spring cartridge DAO business operations are now able to lazily load relationships
                between entites, they also have required parameter checks generated (just like all Spring
                service operations).
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="SPRING-9">
                The Spring cartridge has a new feature: <![CDATA[<<Entity>>]]> operations can now be toggled
                to <code>classifier</code> or <code>instance</code> scope; the former will put the
                operation on the entity's DAO, while the latter will simply put the operation into
                the entity implementation class. Most UML tools allow this feature on an operation by
                selecting the desired state in the operation's properties dialog.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="BPM-114">
                The bpm4struts-cartridge now generates more styles in the CSS files that are created for each
                <![CDATA[<<FrontEndView>>]]>, by default these styles are empty but it is very easy to
                customize them to fine-tune the layout for your pages.
                <ol>
                    <li>form labels and fields</li>
                    <li>form buttons (submit and reset)</li>
                    <li>displaytag:table headers</li>
                    <li>displaytag:table columns</li>
                </ol>
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="fix">
                In bpm4struts it is now possible to send parameters from one action state to another, and this
                in the scope of an action; it is therefore not needed anymore to have parameters entering or exiting
                a page, any action state will do. These parameters will also be recorded in the corresponding action
                form.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="fix" issue="BPM-102">
                Bpm4Struts internal plumbing has significantly improved, this will be most
                noticeable in the performance. This fix is the first part of a series of
                improvements in order to support large and complex models which would yield
                JVM overflow errors.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="fix">
                In bpm4struts you must now draw dependencies from the
                <![CDATA[<<FrontEndController>>]]> to the associated
                <![CDATA[<<FrontEndSessionObject>>]]> classes instead of simply using
                associations.
            </action>
            <action dev="amwest" type="add">
                The <a href="andromda-hibernate-cartridge/modeling.html">AndroMDA
                Hibernate</a> cartridge supports hibernate's Three Inheritance
                Strategies and allows root entities to be generated as
                interfaces. 
                </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                The <a href="andromda-spring-cartridge/modeling.html">AndroMDA Spring</a> 
                cartridge can now model (and have generated) full role 
                based security for the optional Session EJB wrappers.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                The ModelElementFacades association to DependencyFacade has been renamed from
                <code>dependencies</code> to <code>targetDependencies</code>.
                This was necessary due to the fact the dependencies returned were 
                target dependencies only and did not include source dependencies.  
                A new association was added to DependencyFacade called 
                <code>sourceDependencies</code> which can retrieve all source dependencies 
                for a model element.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                The <a href="andromda-webservice-cartridge/modeling.html">AndroMDA Web Service</a> 
                cartridge can now have web services secured through modeling.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                The bpm4struts generated <code>web.xml</code> file now contains some merge points, similar to
                <a href="http://xdoclet.sourceforge.net/xdoclet/merge.html">XDoclet</a>. If you want
                you can completely ignore them because they are commented out. But for some people it might be useful
                to insert fragments into the web.xml without
                <a href="andromda-cartridges/index.html#mergeLocation">overriding the template</a>.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                Added support for lazily loaded relationships collections in
                <a href="andromda-hibernate-cartridge/modeling.html#@andromda.hibernate.lazy">Hibernate</a> and
                <a href="andromda-spring-cartridge/modeling.html#@andromda.hibernate.lazy">Spring</a>, it is sufficient
                to use the aggregation kind of an association end (composite is not lazy, the other kinds are lazy)
                but you can always override the default values using the newly define
                <code>@andromda.hibernate.lazy</code> tagged value.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                Bpm4Struts now supports file uploads, just use the pre-defined
                <code>datatype.File</code> from the profile (or create it yourself)
                on an action parameter.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                Added new tagged value to BPM4Struts called <code>@andromda.struts.view.field.reset</code>
                which allows one to specify specific fields that should be reset on a transition.  This
                is useful when you want certain fields to be reset after action execution but you don't
                want the entire form to be reset.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                BPM4Struts can now extract resource message keys from exceptions thrown from the business
                tier.  For example, if an operation in your service throws an exception with
                the message " {some.message.key} an exception occurred!", BPM4Struts will
                extract the <em>some.message.key</em> from the exception, and add it to the
                request as a struts action error.  You then place this new key in your custom
                message resources with a corresponding message, and next time the error occurs
                this new message will be displayed (instead of the exception).
                The exception handling pattern and a few other related properties are configurable, 
                you can learn more about them on <a href="andromda-bpm4struts-cartridge/namespace.html">BPM4Struts Namespace Properties</a>.
                <strong>NOTE:</strong> if the pattern can not be found in an exception processing
                continues as normal and the exception will be displayed.  
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                Table and action now have their own dedicated CSS style, per
                generated JSP another CSS file will be generate by bpm4struts;
                in this file you can locally override any defined styles.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="fix">
                The 'validwhen' validation feature has finally been implemented. It is now possible with bpm4struts
                to additionally validate a specific field check for certain runtime conditions. This feature is mostly
                used to confirm passwords; this example has been added to the online-store.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                Specific generated pieces of JSP code has its own style, a stylesheet is generated for each page.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                The bpm4struts cartridge now overwrites all jsps pages and stylesheets upon regeneration.
                This is very important for users of earlier versions.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                Updated the <a href="starting.html">getting started</a> guide.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update" issue="BPM-83">
                This update is the last one that will impact the way users model their Struts application.
                A change was needed due to a missing feature: "multibox". In order to properly fix it
                some other changes were required too.
                <ol>
                    <li>You can now put any widget in a table, you can do that by simply linking an action
                        parameter using the <code>@andromda.struts.view.field.tablelink</code>
                        tagged value to an incoming table collection. You must of course link to an existing
                        table column.
                    </li>
                    <li>Previously performing this step would simply create a hyperlink, now you would need to
                        set the action parameter's <code>@andromda.struts.view.field.type</code>
                        tagged value to 'link' in order to achieve that.
                    </li>
                    <li>Due to HTML limitations you can only make links to the same table from a single
                        action. The reason is that there can be only one form around the table. If you still
                        want to have multiple actions working on the same table you will need to patch in
                        manually using JavaScript (setting the target action URL).
                    </li>
                    <li>If you want to use the
                        <a href="http://struts.apache.org/userGuide/struts-html.html#multibox">multibox</a>
                        feature you need first to model a collection or
                        array page-variable that contains the values against which to match. Next you create
                        a table link, thereby selecting the table column. Finally you set the field type of the
                        action parameter to something like this (assuming the multibox collection is
                        called 'myValues')
                        <code>@andromda.struts.view.field.type = multibox:myValues</code>
                    </li>
                    <li>The online store has been extended with an example of this, just open the model
                        and check out the 'buy this item' action. The 'test' and 'available' parameters
                        are rendered as widgets in the table, the 'available' column is a multibox.
                        Please also note how the multibox collection (called 'availableItems') is preloaded
                        by the 'loadItems' controller operations.
                    </li>
                </ol>
                <p class="highlight">
                    I strongly recommend not relying too much on the widgets-in-table feature
                    yet, it is experimental and is likely to change in the future. The reason it has
                    been put in is to see whether or not it is usable. A restriction currently
                    is that you will not have any way to submit the changes you make in the table,
                    for that to work we would need to apply some updates to the rendered rows so a submit button
                    could properly trigger the sending of the form.
                </p>
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                The AndroMDApp Maven plugin has been improved to include Spring
                and the WebService cartridges as options when generating an AndroMDA
                powered Maven application.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="fix">
                AndroMDA now automatically assigns a suitable name to association ends with a
                'many' cardinality and an empty name. Before only the name of the target classifier
                was taken into account, now it is analyzed and a proper (English) name is constructed
                (word:words, key:keys, property:properties).
                If your code relies on such unlabeled association ends it might be possible that an
                AndroMDA run on your UMl model will result in code that is uncompilable in combination
                with your existing implementation classes, a simple rename will be sufficient.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update" issue="UMLMETA-3">
                The metafacades now have their properties no longer modeled as operations but as attributes,
                wherever possible. This has no effect on code already generated. In addition boolean accessor
                methods now have their names properly rendered according to the Java Bean specification
                (getXXX becomes isXXX).
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                The Xdoclet dependency, WebDoclet to be exact, has been removed from the bpm4struts-cartridge;
                now the
                <code>struts-config.xml</code> and
                <code>validation.xml</code> files are generated
                directly by AndroMDA. The Ant-tool and the maven plugins, used to generate a default AndroMDA
                project, have also been updated to reflect this change.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                The AndroMDA Spring cartridge (a cartridge based on the
                <a href="http://www.springframework.org">Spring Framework</a>)
                has moved from the contrib module to the main andromda codebase.  To learn how to use this new cartridge,
                please see the the documentation
                <a href="andromda-spring-cartridge/index.html">here</a>
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update" issue="BPM-72">
                The latest major update has been improved: it is now no longer needed to
                add tagged values onto controller operation arguments. The cartridge will
                auto-detect the appropriate value. In addition more validation constraints
                have been added to inform the user of any cartridge modeling errors.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update" issue="BPM-71">
                The latest major bpm4struts update did not prove to be a very elegant solution,
                this led us to revise
                the implementation and come up with an alternative one. Here's a list of what has changed:
                <ol>
                    <li>parameters with the same name and in the same use-case are required to also
                        be of the same type</li>
                    <li>form fields do no longer have their name prefixed with the name of the action</li>
                    <li>forms now implement an interface for each controller operation they defer to</li>
                    <li>it is now needed to put arguments in the controller operations, these arguments
                        will be available in the form interface that is accessible programmatically</li>
                    <li>these arguments will need to have the
                        <code>
                        @andromda.struts.view.field.type</code> tagged value set to 'select' in case
                        you want to prepopulate a list of entries (see samples)
                    </li>
                    <li>currently it is also needed to specify the table columns (just as you
                        would on a collection-type page variable) in case the argument
                        maps onto an action parameter which is displayed in tabular format, but this
                        will be solved soon</li>
                </ol>
                <p class="highlight">
                    All of this means this will break the compilation of your current
                    codebase using one of the previous AndroMDA versions.
                </p>
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update" issue="BPM-32">
                Overloaded a controller method for accessing the session objects, the new
                method allows to choose whether or not to create the session in case it does
                not exist yet (default is
                <code>true</code>). Also implemented some
                improvements in handling the session objects and the session itself.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                The andromda task and maven plugin, now support an attribute called
                <code>failOnModelValidationErrors</code> which allows us to
                turn on/off whether or not model processing should fail/stop
                if
                <strong>ANY</strong> model validation errors occur.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="update">
                The hibernate cartridge now generates its own hibernate.cfg.xml which
                means the jboss-service.xml generated by xdoclet is no longer needed.
                With this change, multiple new namespace properties were added
                for configuring this configuration file.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="BPM-69">
                Just like you can use success messages on action transitions we now have
                the possibility to use warning messages, simply add the tagged value
                <code>@andromda.struts.action.warning.message</code> to the action
                transition and set its value to the message you want to have displayed (will be i18n'ed).
                Warning messages will be rendered in yellowish.
                In addition all messages are now supported on
                <strong>any</strong> transition, and you may have
                more than one message on such a transition (unlimited).
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update" issue="BPM-32">
                The controllers associated to session objects have different methods to
                access those objects. The 'clearXXX' method has been renamed to 'removeXXX'.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                A new namespace property 'versionProperty' has been added, it is used
                to determine which property/attribute name to use for versioning entities.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                There is a new link in the download section (menu), it is called 'resources' and it
                will contain resources on AndroMDA such as tutorials and slides.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                A new namespace property is available to set a default date format to use for
                date fields in your bpm4struts, not specifying this value will use dd/MM/yyyy as the default
                date format.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="fix">
                This change fixes some issues with the most recent updates for bpm4struts:
                <ol>
                    <li>We no longer have the controller operation interfaces the forms were implementing</li>
                    <li>Instead we have a controller operation for each different action that defers to them,
                        this means you sometimes have the same operation more than once with only a different
                        argument type for the form. This seems to be the most optimal and realistic
                        implementation, forms cannot be shared using interfaces aggregating the fields
                        because field names carry the action name as a prefix and this cannot be changed
                        because in that case validation rules would be impossible to determine for fields
                        that have the same name and type over different page actions.
                    </li>
                    <li>It should now be possible to easily send parameters between use-cases</li>
                </ol>
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                Controllers and their implementation have changed names. The abstract parent
                classes now no longer have the 'Interface' suffix, the descendants have
                the 'Impl' suffix. This has been done for consistency with other cartridges
                and because it is cleaner not to have any suffix on the interface or
                abstract parents.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update" issue="BPM-44">
                It is now possible to specify labels and values differently
                for selectable parameters such as in comboboxes and lists.
                The form containing such a parameter will have two new properties:
                'valueList' and 'labelList'. If you do not specify the 'labelList'
                property it will assume the values of the 'valueList'.
                The backing list has been made readonly
                because it will construct a special array to be handled by the Struts tags.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                Controller implementation do not get form types passed in the argument, instead
                there is an interface aggregating common form properties, this way forms
                of several different types implementing this interface can be passed in.
                This elegantly allows a single controller operation to be called from different
                actions (which each have their own form).
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                A major change has been incorporated into the cartridge, you will have to
                be very careful when migrating to a version after this date.
                ActionForms are back into the request scope so their properties will not be
                persisted into the session as was the case before. Bpm4Struts now is
                intelligent enough to determine which properties should be available in which
                ActionForm (even in ambiguous cases such as cyclic processes or when
                multiple actions target multiple pages without a 1-to-1 mapping.
                The reason for this drastic change was a possible bug in the server-side
                validation framework. It would happen that forms were not properly recognized on
                the server while the client could parse them fine.
                In order to properly migrate you should at least need to fix the controller
                implementations (you will have compilation errors otherwise), unfortunately
                you will need to update all JSP pages. The changes are minimal so you might
                consider looking at the differences manually (we are back at using the Struts HTML
                tag library instead of the plain old HTML tags directly).
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="update">
                The
                <code>validating</code> flag has been renamed to the more
                appropriate
                <code>xmlValidation</code>.  At the same time a new
                <code>modelValidation</code> flag has been added that allows us
                to turn on/off model validation during processing.   By default
                model validation occurs, however its sometimes nice to turn it
                off for performance reasons (i.e. you have a really big model).
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="BPM-32">
                We now have session objects, these instances can be handled
                through protected controller methods. Controller interfaces
                are abstract classes now, so make sure you use 'extends'
                instead of 'implements' when using the cartridge after
                this date.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update" issue="BPM-36">
                The namespace property 'breadCrumbs' (boolean) has been replaced by the property
                'maxBreadCrumbs' (integer). To disable breadcrumbs specify zero.
                Additionally the tabledecorator has been removed, it was only used to render
                specific HTML code but a more elegant solution has been put in place.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="update">
                A new namespace property has been added that can be used for
                <em>any</em> cartridge, its called
                <code>mergeLocation</code>, for
                more information see
                <a href="andromda-cartridges/index.html#mergeLocation">Overriding cartridge resources</a>.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="BPM-48">
                For those who want it online help will be generated
                for your application, by default it is enabled. You can
                override this by setting the 'onlineHelp' property to
                'false' in your bpm4struts namespace.
                It currently supports documentation on use-cases, action
                transitions, action parameters and pages.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                Tooltips are now handled in JavaScript. We had to remove
                the doctypes for that to work properly in Firefox and Mozilla.
                It will be improved in the future.
                The reason we have these JS tooltips is that now it can also
                support images and text of arbitrary length.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                Pattern masks for input field validation must not include
                the leading '^' and trailing '$' anymore. Some CASE tools
                such as MagicDraw don't handle them well.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                The table link tagged value changed name:
                <code>@andromda.struts.action.tablelink</code> is now
                <code>@andromda.struts.view.field.tablelink</code>, the reason is that
                the location for this tagged value is the parameter and not the
                transition (as in the very beginning).
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                Form bean fields now have the name of their action prepended to their
                name (only for action parameters, page variables are unchanged).
                Using bpm4struts after this date will require you to update
                your controller implementations or a compilation error
                will occur.
                This change was needed in order to allow action parameters to
                have the same names in a single use-case. Without this feature
                the form would contain the same field name more than once, and that
                is not allowed in Java.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                A new namespace property has been added: 'dummyData'. You can either
                give it a 'true' or 'false' value. The default is 'true'. If the
                value is 'true' a 'dummy data' will be rendered in places like the
                controller, if set to 'false' this dummy data will not be generated.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="update">
                toJavaClassName and toJavaMethodName in StringUtilsHelper have been
                renamed to more language generic "upperCamelCaseName"
                and "lowerCamelCaseName".
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                A new namespace property has been added: 'tableNamePrefix'.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="BPM-36">
                A new namespace property has been added: 'breadCrumbs'. You can either
                give it a 'true' or 'false' value. The default is 'true'. If the
                value is 'true' a 'history' is rendered at the top of each page,
                also known as breadcrumbs: it allows you to navigate back and forth
                between the pages already visited. The scope of the breadcrumbs is
                restricted to the context use-case.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="BPM-39">
                Required fields now have an asterisk rendered next to their
                label. (Only if validation has been enabled)
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="BPM-45">
                Added the following tagged value:
                <code>@andromda.struts.view.field.tablelink</code>.
                You can use it to create hyperlinks to actions in the columns of a table.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="BPM-23">
                Date input field now have a popup calendar to choose the date from
                and have it automaitcally rendered into the appropriate format.
            </action>
        </release>
        <release version="3.0M2" date="2004-08-09" description="A stable development release for version 3, milestone 2">
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                Cartridges now allow generation based on metafacade
                type (and optionally its properties), in addition to stereotypes.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add" issue="BPM-14">
                It is now possible to create a hyperlink from a final state to a use-case
                and have the cartridge interpret it as the next use-case to navigate to.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="update">
                The maven build has been changed
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        All artifacts now reside in the 'andromda' groupId of the maven
                        repository.  This means for those using Maven for their projects,
                        they'll need to specify 'andromda' as the groupId (for dependencies)
                        instead of the old 'andromda-cartridges' for cartridges and
                        'andromda-translation-libraries' for translation-libraries.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                       Bootstrap dependencies are now stored in CVS. They are renamed
                       to the current version and copied to the remote repository during the build (
                       they used to be stored remotely).
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="update">
                The <![CDATA[<andromda/>]]> Ant task was changed to
                allow multiple models to be specified using a URL.
                This included adding a new <![CDATA[<model/>]]> element
                and eliminating the modelURL attribute from the <![CDATA[<andromda/>]]>
                task.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                Enabled support for tools that do not allow putting graphs inside use-cases. It is now
                sufficient to put the
                <code>@andromda.struts.usecase.activity</code>
                tagged value on the use-case and assign it the name of an activity graph.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                Enabled support for tools that do not allow assigning model elements to classifiers.
                It is now possible to put a
                <code>@andromda.struts.controller.usecase</code> tagged value
                on the controller and assigning it the name of a use-case.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                Tagged value prefix of "@andromda" was added back to
                all tagged values.  It was causing naming conflicts
                with XDoclet tags when it was just "@".
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                Added new resource element to the andromda-cartridge.xml
                that allows non template resources (like images, jars, etc)
                to be included and output from a cartridge.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="update">
                All JSPs have been updated to render XHTML 1.0 compatible content,
                the content-type declaration has been updated and any HTML
                comment has been changed to comply to the XHTML standard.
                You will need an XHTML compatible browser to properly
                view the pages.
                By default bpm4struts generates HTML 4.0 compliant JSPs but
                by setting the 'xhtml' namespace property to 'true' it will
                render XHTML.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="update">
                The 'sheet' attribute in the template element has been
                renamed to 'path'.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                In bpm4struts there is a new namespace property: xhtml. The property
                'securityEnabled' has been renamed to 'security'.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="update">
                The 'overWrite' attribute in the template element has been
                renamed to 'overwrite'.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                A new feature has been added that will allow users to import legacy database
                schemas and have an XMI file generated from them. This will make it easier to port
                development of legacy systems to AndroMDA.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                A new cartridge is available for publishing services
                as web-services, this cartridge is to be used in
                combination with either the EJB, Hibernate,
                or Java cartridge.
            </action>
            <action dev="draftdog" type="add">
                Tabular data can now automatically be displayed using paging,
                sorting and exporting features, the displaytag tag-library is
                used.
            </action>
            <action dev="cwbrandon" type="add">
                OCL support provides the following features:
                <ul>
                    <li>Metamodels will now have their constraints
                        validated during code generation.</li>
                    <li>Finder queries for persisted entities
                        can now be expressed using OCL.</li>
                </ul>
            </action>
        </release>
    </body>
</document>
