<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="mbohlen@mbohlen.de">Matthias Bohlen</author>
    <title>Consulting</title>
    <gennews>no</gennews>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Consulting for Architecture, Object and Component Technologie">

      <p class="std">
          I am an independent consultant for software architecture,
          OO analysis, design and implementation of business systems.
          I have written AndroMDA just to show my clients how easy and
          effective it can be to use a model-driven approach for large
          scale software development projects.
      </p>
      <p class="std">
          If you run a software development project and you should have the
          need for some independent view and vendor-neutral expertise, it may make
          sense to ask me for contract work.
      </p>

      <p class="std">
        <b>What I do</b>
      </p>
      <p class="std">
         I work as a peer for my clients' software development teams during day to day
         development work. Conference talks and the writing of books and magazine articles
         goes hand-in-hand with the other activities. Main subjects of my work are:
      </p>
      <ul>
         <li class="std">OO analysis</li>
         <li class="std">OO design</li>
         <li class="std">component architectures</li>
         <li class="std">development tools</li>
         <li class="std">agile development processes</li>
         <li class="std">making development interesting and enjoyable</li>
      </ul>

      <p class="std">
        <b>How I work</b>
      </p>
      <p class="std">
         Each project is different. How a project looks like, depends on
         three variables: culture, architecture and process. They form
         a triangle - when you change one of them, the rest will change, too.
         Therefore, I try to see a project as a whole.
      </p>
      <p class="std">
         Consulting, coaching,
         training, mentoring - all these are ways to influence people to go
         into the direction "they always wanted to go but could not". In one
         project I use one way, in another project I use another. It depends
         on how the three variables are configured in that particular company.
      </p>

      <p class="std">
        <b>Stop philosophy - kneel down and get your hands dirty!</b>
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        If you don't like the abstract talk above :-), here are some of
        the areas where I have particular expertise:
      </p>
      <ul>
         <li class="std">Object orientation (OOA, OOD, UML, CASE-tools)</li>
         <li class="std">Component development</li>
         <li class="std">System architecture</li>
         <li class="std">J2EE, especially Enterprise JavaBeans</li>
         <li class="std">Java programming</li>
         <li class="std">Best practices for development (eXtreme Programming)</li>
         <li class="std">Highly efficient development tools (Eclipse, Ant, JUnit, etc.)</li>
         <li class="std">Optimizing the way to work in high-speed, high-risk projects</li>
      </ul>

      <p class="std">
        <b>More info and contact</b>
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        You want to know more about me and my clients? You want to contact me?
        Maybe, you want to see what model-driven architecture can do for your project?
      </p>
      <p class="std">
        Visit my website at <a href="http://www.mbohlen.de/">http://www.mbohlen.de/</a>
        - there you will find all the
        info you need. Most of the website is in German because I mainly work
        in Germany. However, you will
        find a link "English pages" on the upper left side to get an English overview.
      </p>

    </section>

  </body>
</document>
