<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document> 
  <properties>
    <author email="mbohlen@mbohlen.de">Matthias Bohlen</author>
    <author email="chdbrandon@yahoo.com">Chad Brandon</author>
    <title>Modeling for AndroMDA</title>
    <gennews>yes</gennews>
  </properties>
  	<body> 
		<section name="Modeling for AndroMDA">
			<title>Modeling</title>
			<p> AndroMDA is an automatic tool with a medium amount of 
				intelligence built into it. Such a tool always has to rely upon 
				some clearly defined preconditions; in the case of AndroMDA, 
				these preconditions are <b>modeling conventions</b>. This means 
				that a UML model for use with AndroMDA cannot be structured 
				arbitrarily but has to adhere to a certain structure that can 
				be interpreted by AndroMDA. 
		    </p>
			<p> On the other hand, not too many constraints should 
				be imposed on the modeler - after all, a model should represent 
				the conceptual reality of the customer's requirements and the 
				structure of the application domain. 
		    </p>
			<p> To sum up it all up, we've tried to keep the number of 
				rules low in order to keep your freedom of modeling high.
				Keep in mind: modeling standards/requirements will 
				ultimately be dependantant on the implementation(s) of the cartridge(s) 
				you employ at build time.  Each cartridge has required properties and modeling
				conventions that must be followed.  See 
			    <a href="../andromda-cartridges/index.html">Cartridges</a> for 
				more information. In general, there rules to follow (seen below) when you start 
				sketching a design model and you want AndroMDA to generate your 
				components smoothly. 
			</p>
			<subsection name="General Modeling Rules">
				<p>
					<strong>Stereotypes drive code generation!</strong>: 
					UML Stereotypes are a kind of "label" that you 
					attach to modeling elements in order to classify them. 
				</p>
				<p> <b>Example:</b> You tag a CustomerService class 
					with a <code><![CDATA[<<Service>>]]></code> stereotype. 
					AndroMDA sees this stereotype, looks into its internal 
					dictionary of available code generation components (called 
					"cartridges") and finds the EJB cartridge. In the EJB
					cartridge, two templates correspond to the <code><![CDATA[<<Service>>]]></code>
					stereotype: 
					SessionBean.vsl and SessionBeanImpl.vsl. AndroMDA uses the
					internal representation of CustomerService loaded from the model, 
					calls the processing engine twice, and two output files are generated:
					CustomerServiceBean.java and CustomerServiceBeanImpl.java. 
				</p>
				<p>
					A small model, containing an element tagged with the 
					<code><![CDATA[<<Service>>]]></code> stereotype,
					can be seen in this picture:
				</p>
				<img src="images/CarRentalCustomers.gif" width="624" height="590" />
				<p> Even though modeling will depend primarily on how the 
					cartridge is implemented. There are some standard ways of 
					modeling which <strong>MUST</strong> be followed to ensure 
					the model is <em>syntantically and semantically 
					complete</em>, meaning the cartridge performing generation 
					has enough information on which to generate from. 
			    </p>
				<p> These are listed here. 
					<ul> 
						<li> 
							<strong>Names:</strong> 
							the general rule for all the names is to capitalize the 
							first letter of each concatenated word (i.e 
							exampleOfCapitalizationOfConcatenatedWords). This applies 
							to all model element names (methods, operations, 
							attributes, associations, association ends, etc.). 
						</li> 
						<li> 
							<strong> Specify the type of ALL attributes and operation 
							parameters. </strong> Some tools with allow you to 
							specify an attribute or operation without making you 
							specify it's type, but make sure you specify this, as a 
							cartridge performing generation will expect this 
							information. </li> <li> <strong>Specify the multiplicities 
							of both ends of ALL associations</strong>. Cartridges use 
							and require all multiplicity information. 
						</li> 
						<li> 
							<strong> Make sure names of association ends making up an 
							association are UNIQUE within the association. </strong> 
							If more than one association end of the same association is 
							the same name, there will be conflicts from the generated 
							output. 
						</li> 
						<li> 
							<strong>
								Do not leave unused elements <em>dangling</em> in your model.
							</strong> 
							One of the biggest causes of syntatic incompleteness is 
							the existence in the model of partially defined elements that are 
							undetected by the modeler because they do not reside in any 
							model diagram. Its easy to make the mistake of deleting the 
							element from the diagram but then forgetting to delete it 
							from the model as well. 
						</li> 
						<li> 
							<strong> If an element CANNOT exist without another element, define the 
							association end of the owning element as <code>composite 
							aggregation</code>.</strong> An association between a <em>house</em> 
							and a <em>room</em> is a good example of <code>composite 
							aggregation</code>. Destruction of the <em>house</em> implies 
							destruction of all <em>rooms</em> that the <em>house</em> contains. 
							Therefore the association end of the <em>house</em> to a 
							<em>room</em> would be defined as <code>composite 
							aggregation</code> (i.e. a black diamond). 
						</li> 
						<li> 
							<strong>Specify ordering where ordering matters.</strong> 
							When using multivalued attributes and association ends you 
							should be able to specify whether or not these are ordered in 
							the modeling tool. Make sure you specify this if ordering does matter 
					        for these multivalued properties since cartridges need to 
							be able to take advantage of this specification. For 
							example, if an association end was defined as ordered, a 
							cartridge generating to Java may specify the type as a 
							<code>java.util.Set</code> instead of a 
							<code>java.util.Collection</code> (if it was left 
							unspecified or defined as unordered). 
						</li> 
						<li> <strong>Do NOT add getter and setter operations for attributes.</strong> The cartridge will generate any 
							required accessor and mutator operations needed at 
							generation time. 
						</li> 
						<li> 
							<strong>Do NOT add getter and setter methods for association ends.</strong> The cartridge 
							will generate any required accessor and mutator operations 
							needed at generation time. 
						</li> 
						<li> 
							<strong>Define and use <code>Datatypes</code> for simple types.</strong> Use 
							UML <code>Datatypes</code> for simple types such as String, 
							Collection, Set, etc. instead of using the language 
							specific types which the tool may implement by default 
							(i.e. java.lang.String). You want to keep the model as 
							language independant as possible. Cartridges use mapping 
							files at generation time to map Datatypes to specific 
							language types (i.e. for Java, these could be: Collection <![CDATA[-->]]>
					        java.util.Collection, Blob <![CDATA[-->]]> java.sql.Blob, etc.) 
					    </li> 
		            </ul> 
			    </p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
