<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="chad@andromda.org">Chad Brandon</author>
        <title>AndroMDA Namespace</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="AndroMDA Namespace">
            <p>
                AndroMDA namespace components are described through a single XML descriptor, the namespace.xml file.  
                You'll find this file in a cartridge, translation-library or metafacades jar (basically any component that 
                can reside with a <em>namespace</em>) located in the <em>/META-INF/andromda</em> directory of that jar.
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                In order for a namespace component to be <em>"discovered"</em> by AndroMDA, it <strong>MUST</strong> be registered within this descriptor.
            </p>
            <p>
                <ol>
                    There are several purposes of the namespace descriptor:
                    <li>Allowing discovery of the namespace by AndroMDA when placed on the classpath</li>
                    <li>Providing registration all components for the namespace</li>
                    <li>Defining any properties that are used to configure the namespace</li>
                </ol>
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                Each namespace descriptor must adhere to this <a href="namespace/schema.html">XML Schema</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Let's take a look at how a typlical namespace descriptor is structured.  
                You'll notice from this example below that both the cartridge and metafacades components are defined
                for the <em>webservice</em> namespace.  What this means, is that when AndroMDA <em>"discovers"</em> this namepsace,
                it will know that it needs to register both a cartridge and a set of metafacades under the namespace of <em>webservice</em> 
                (the descriptors for both the cartridge and metafacades will be need to be present in the webservice cartridge jar).
                <source language="xml">
<![CDATA[<namespace name="webservice">
    <components>
        <component name="cartridge"/>
        <component name="metafacades"/>
    </components>
    <properties>
        <propertyGroup name="Outlets">
            <documentation>
                Defines the locations to which output is generated.
            </documentation>
            <property name="wsdls">
                <documentation>
                    Specifies the directory to which generated WSDL's will be placed.
                </documentation>
            </property>
            <property name="java-types">
                <documentation>
                    The directory to which any non implementation Java files will be generated.
                </documentation>
            </property>
            <property name="axis-configuration">
                <documentation>
                    The directory to which any AXIS specific configuration files
                    are generated (such as the WSDD files, etc).
                </documentation>
            </property>
            <property name="axis-tests" required="false">
                <documentation>
                    The directory to which AXIS specific test classes are generated.
                </documentation>
            </property>
            <property name="axis-test-impls" required="false">
                <documentation>
                    The directory to which the AXIS specific test implementation classes are generated.
                </documentation>
            </property>
            <property name="wss4j-configuration" required="false">
                <documentation>
                    The directory to which any <a href="http://ws.apache.org/ws-fx/wss4j/index.html">WSS4J</a>
                    specific configuration files are generated.
                </documentation>
            </property>
        </propertyGroup>
        <propertyGroup name="Other">
            <property name="namespacePrefix">
                <default>impl</default>
                <documentation>
                    Defines the prefix to give to the default namespace.
                </documentation>
            </property>
            <property name="qualifiedNameLocalPartPattern">
                <default>{0}</default>
                <documentation>
                    The pattern to use when a qualified name local part is created.
                    <em>{0}</em> represents the name of the classifier (i.e.
                    <em>WS{0}</em> would give all your types and services a prefix
                    of <em>WS</em>).
                </documentation>
            </property>
            <property name="namespacePattern">
                <default>http://{0}</default>
                <documentation>
                    The pattern to use when a namespace is created.
                    <em>{0}</em> represents the package name of the classifier (i.e.
                    <em>ws.{0}</em> would prefix all your type and service
                    namespaces with <em>ws.</em>).
                </documentation>
            </property>
            ...
        </propertyGroup>
        ...
    </properties>
</namespace>]]>                   
                </source>
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
