<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="cwbrandon@users.sourceforge.net">Chad Brandon</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Samples</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="AndroMDA Samples">
            <p>
                AndroMDA would be very difficult to grasp without at least one
                sample application.  Therefore, the distribution
                includes several:
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <a href="animal-quiz.html">Animal Quiz</a>
                    </li>
                    <!--
                    <li>
                        <a href="car-rental-system.html">Car Rental System</a>
                    </li>
                    -->
                    <li>
                        <!--
                        use this instead when the page is present: <a href="online-store.html">Online Store</a>
                        -->
                        <a href="andromda-bpm4struts-cartridge/samples.html#online-store">Online Store</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="andromda-cartridges/manageable-entities/index.html">CRUD Sample (Manageable Entities)</a>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <subsection name="Where can I find the samples?">
                <p>
                    The models and source code of each sample are located within the
                    <code>samples</code> directory of the AndroMDA binary and source distributions.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="How are the samples structured?">
                <p>
                    The
                    <code>src</code> directory of each module described below (excluding
                    the
                    <strong>mda</strong> module which is a special case) contains the sources
                    that have been hand coded, most of them were generated by AndroMDA the first run
                    and then they had business or custom logic hand-coded in.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Each sample is made up  of the modules explained here:
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            /mda
                            <p class="highlight">
                                This is the
                                <strong>most important</strong> module, as it contains the
                                project's model.  This module is used by AndroMDA to generate code
                                into all other modules.
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                What happens within this module is this:
                                <ol>
                                    <li>
                                        maven calls the
                                        <strong>andromda:run</strong> goal of the
                                        <a href="maven-andromda-plugin/index.html">AndroMDA maven plugin</a>
                                    </li>
                                    <li>
                                        The plugin tells AndroMDA to load the model located in the
                                        <code>mda/src/uml</code>.
                                    </li>
                                    <li>
                                        The AndroMDA plugins (cartridges, and translation-libraries)
                                        defined within the mda/project.xml file let AndroMDA know exactly
                                        what stuff it needs to generate when processing the model.
                                    </li>
                                    <li>
                                        AndroMDA runs and the files/resources are generated to the locations
                                        defined by the namespace properties within the plugin dependencies.
                                    </li>
                                </ol>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            /app
                            <p>
                                Contains files required to create the
                                <strong>ear</strong> bundle.
                                Typically you will find application deployment descriptors in this
                                directory, as well as DDL scripts to initialize/drop your schema 
                                (if you're using hibernate/spring).
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            /common
                            <p>
                                Contains common sources that can be shared between the different
                                modules in the project. Typically you will find utility classes
                                in this directory.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            /core
                            <p>
                                Contains the persistence and business/transaction management layer.
                                This contains generated source from either the hibernate, spring,
                                or ejb cartridges.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            /web
                            <p>
                                Contains sources required to build the presentation layer.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            /webservice
                            <p>
                                Contains any source, descriptors, or other necessary files
                                required for webservice support.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="How do I build the samples?">
                <p>
                    Its very easy to build all samples or just one at a time.  First of all you
                    <strong>MUST</strong> install
                    <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</a>.
                    To build all, just change to the samples directory, and type
                    <em>maven</em>.
                    To build a single sample (i.e. animal-quiz), just change to the samples/animal-quiz
                    directory and again type
                    <em>maven</em>.  That's all there is too it!
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    After the build of a sample completes, you'll notice each module contains
                    a target directory, this target directory contains all generated source,
                    any class files, any generated descriptors, etc. (i.e. anything that has
                    been generated/created during the build process which will NOT be checked into
                    source control).
                </p>
                <p>
                    Once built, you'll find each deployable
                    <strong>ear</strong> file located in the
                    /app/target directory. Each ear can deployed by dropping it in the deploy directory
                    of a
                    <a href="http://www.jboss.org">JBoss</a> application server instance.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Need more help?">
                <p>
                    In case of difficulties, please subscribe to the
                    <a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/andromda-user">andromda-user</a> mailing list
                    and post your questions there.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>