<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="draftdog@users.sourceforge.net">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <author email="cwbrandon@users.sourceforge.new">Chad Brandon</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Installation</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Getting started with AndroMDA">
            <h3>Maven</h3>
            <p>
                Make sure you have both <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</a> and the
                <a href="maven-andromdapp-plugin/download.html">AndroMDApp Maven Plugin</a>
                installed.
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                It is very important your Maven installation knows how to download dependencies and its own plugins,
                in order to achieve that you should create a file called <code>build.properties</code>
                in your home directory (for example <code>C:\Documents and Settings\Wouter</code> on Windows),
                this file should be a plain text file and should contain this line:
                <source>
maven.repo.remote=http://www.ibiblio.org/maven,http://team.andromda.org/maven
                </source>
                Once you have done that you will be able to succesfully execute the following command that will
                install the AndroMDA Maven plugin to generate AndroMDA projects:
                <source>
maven plugin:download -DgroupId=andromda -DartifactId=maven-andromdapp-plugin -Dversion=3.0M3-SNAPSHOT
                </source>
                For more information you can also read the
                <a href="http://maven.apache.org/reference/user-guide.html#Properties_Processing">Maven user guide</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Go into a directory in which you want to create your working directory.
                For example, suppose you want to work in C:\development\java\my-project, then
                simply go into C:\development\java\
            </p>
            <p>
                At the console type:
                <source>
C:\development\java> maven andromdapp:generate
                </source>
            </p>
            <p>
                Answer the questions you are prompted to answer
            </p>
            <p>
                Giving your project the id 'my-project' will create a subdirectory
                with the same name, so you'll have C:\development\java\my-project.
            </p>
            <p>
                C:\development\java\my-project\mda\src\uml will contain an empty XMI
                document, you can use it to get started modeling your application
            </p>
            <p>
                Simply typing 'maven' in C:\development\java\my-project will build your
                application and it will put all the binaries into your local
                Maven repository (by default, this is the .maven directory in your 
                user home, i.e. $HOME for linux/unix, %USERPROFILE% for windows).
            </p>
            <p>
                Optionally you can go into a subdirectory to build it separately from
                the others, this is much quicker and it will make it easy to focus on
                only a part of your application.
            </p>
            <p>
                If your application 'my-project' has been built succesfully you can find
                the binaries here: %USERPROFILE%\.maven\repository\my-project\
                (for *nix users: $USER_HOME\.maven\repository\my-project\)
            </p>
            <p>
                By default the application will generate an EJB backend (optionally with a
                Hibernate persistence layer) and a Struts front-end.
            </p>
            <a name="starting-with-ant"/>
            <h3>Ant</h3>
            <p>
                Make sure you have <a href="http://ant.apache.org">Ant</a> installed.
                Download the AndroMDA 3.x binary distribution from the AndroMDA Sourceforge
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=73047&amp;package_id=117392" target="_blank">site</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Unzip into any location and go into the 'ant' subdirectory. Type 'ant' there to invoke
                the Ant build process. (You will need to have Ant installed of course)
            </p>
            <p>
                Answer the questions, a little later you will have your environment
                setup for you. It consists of a hierarchy of build.xml files and
                corresponding property files.  In addition, it will create a directory 
				called 'lib' containing all necessary dependencies for your newly generated application.			
            </p>
            <p>
				To successfully build your new application, you must do two things:
                <ol>
                    <li>
						Copy the resulting lib directory to the directory of your newly generated application.
                    </li>
                    <li>
				        Change to your newly generated application directory and type 'ant' and you'll
                        see your AndroMDA powered Ant application application being built!
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>