<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>
            Create UserVO
        </title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Create UserVO">

            <p>
                This page provides directions to create the
                <tt>UserVO</tt>
                using RSM.
            </p>

            <p>
                Let's take a look at the initial content of the freshly generated model.
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Start RSM.</li>
                <li>The AndroMDApp generated model is not meant to be edited directly: we have to import it into RSM.
                    Since AndroMDA will use only the exported file, you have the choice on which project you want to store the .emx model.
                    <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                        <li>An independant project in your RSM workspace</li>
                        <li>The Java project containing your Andromda project</li>
                    </ol>
                    For this tutorial, we'll choose the first option. Click on
                    <i>File &gt; New... &gt; Project</i>. Choose
                    <i>Simple &gt; Project</i>
                    and click on<i>Next</i>. Type in
                    <tt>TimeTracker</tt>
                    as the name and click<i>OK</i>.
                </li>
                <li>Select<i>File &gt; Import...</i>. Choose
                    <i>UML2 Model</i>
                    and then click on<i>Next</i>. Click on the upper
                    <i>Browse...</i>
                    and traverse to<tt>C:\timetracker\mda\src\main\uml</tt>.
                    Click
                    <i>Open</i>
                    to open this file. Then click on the second
                    <i>Browse...</i>
                    and choose the
                    <tt>TimeTracker</tt>
                    project.
                    Check the box
                    <i>Open imported models</i>
                    and click on
                    <i>Done</i>
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                On the left of the window, there is the model explorer. It displays the objects
                that make, together, the model. AndroMDA sees the model like it is displayed here (and not
                through the several diagrams). By making sure that the content of your model is matching the pictures
                shown during this tutorial, you'll avoid a lot of errors.
            </p>
            <p>
                As you can see, the model is not empty. Some of work has already be done for you. Let's review the initial
                content of the model.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <tt>UML2</tt>: This module contains the standard datatypes for UML2.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <tt>Basic, Intermediate, Complete, Default, Deployement</tt>: These modules are the standard profiles applied to a UML2 model.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <tt>AndroMDA Datatypes</tt>: This package contains some platform independent datatypes
                    that have be used in your UML model. AndroMDA will map then to platform specific datatypes.
                    <i>Important</i>: A common source of errors is to use UML's datatypes instead of these.
                    When specifying datatypes, make sure that they come from this package. Example: use
                    <tt>datatype::String</tt>
                    instead of<tt>String</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <tt>AndroMDA Profile</tt>: This collection of profiles define all the stereotypes and
                    tag values that will be used by AndroMDA for generating code.
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                Note: all this content is not
                <i>included</i>
                in the .uml2 file. They're only
                <i>references</i>
                to
                files located into your maven 2 repository.
            </p>
            <p>
                We have to rename the model to<tt>timetracker</tt>. Otherwise, the exported file won't be called
                <tt>timetracker.uml2</tt>.
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>In the model explorer on the left, open the
                    <tt>timetracker.emx</tt>
                    and select the model called<tt>model</tt>. Press F2 and type in
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    as the name of this model.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                As said previously, AndroMDA can't read RSM models directly. You have to export it
                to another file format: EMF-UML2.
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Save your
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model by double-clicking on
                    <tt>timetracker.emx</tt>
                    and clicking on
                    <i>File &gt; Save</i>
                    (<i>Ctrl + S</i>).
                </li>
                <li>
                    Select<i>File &gt; Export...</i>. Choose
                    <i>UML2 Model</i>
                    and then click on<i>Next</i>.
                    As
                    <i>source</i>
                    select
                    <tt>/TimeTracker/timetracker.emx</tt>
                    and as
                    <i>destination</i>
                    browse to<tt>C:\timetracker\mda\src\main\uml</tt>.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <blockquote>
                <b>Important</b>: Always use the
                <i>timetracker.emx</i>
                file for editing. After edition, don't forget to export the model
                to EMF/UML2. AndroMDA won't take your changes into account if you don't export your model.
            </blockquote>
            <p>
                Let's start the 'real' work. We will create
                <tt>UserVO</tt>
                and
                <tt>UserVO[]</tt>
                in a package named
                <tt>org.andromda.timetracker.vo</tt>. When finished, the model explorer in
                RSM will look like the screen shot on the bottom of this page.
            </p>

            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Now right-click on the
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model and select<i>Add UML Entity
                        &gt; Package</i>. A new package will be created under the
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model element with
                    an edit box to its side. Type in
                    <tt>org.andromda.timetracker</tt>
                    as the name
                    of the package. AndroMDA will map this package to a Java package with the same name.
                    Note: Make sure the package name is exactly<tt>org.andromda.timetracker</tt>,
                    with no leading or trailing spaces. We have found that some browsers introduce a
                    leading space in the package name if you copy it from this page!
                </li>
                <li>Now create a package called
                    <tt>vo</tt>
                    under<tt>org.andromda.timetracker</tt>.
                    We will create our value objects in this package. Note that AndroMDA does not require
                    this package structure. We are doing it simply to separate our value objects from
                    other type of objects such as business entities, services etc.
                </li>
                <li>In the model explorer on the left, right-click on the
                    <tt>vo</tt>
                    package
                    and select<i>Add Diagram &gt; Class Diagram</i>. The diagram is created and opened in a new window.
                    You can see that the diagram's name is being edited. Type in
                    <tt>Value Objects</tt>
                    as the name of
                    this diagram and press Enter.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Note: Depending on your configuration, RSM add automatically a diagram
                    to created package. Simply delete them or use them. It is up to you.
                </li>
                <li>In the toolbar on the left of the class diagram click on the
                    <i>Class icon</i>
                    (2nd icon
                    from the class diagram group). Now click anywhere inside the diagram. A new class will be created.
                    Click on
                    <tt>Class1</tt>
                    to make RSM display an editing box for the name of the class. Now
                    type the word
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    and press Enter.
                </li>
                <li>Let's add some documentation for the
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class. It is always a good
                    idea to document your model. Documentation added to model elements such as classes,
                    attributes and methods is carried over to the code as comments. Select
                    the
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class. In the
                    <i>Properties</i>
                    tab, click on<i>Documentation</i>.
                    Enter the following words in the field:
                    <tt>This class represents
                        a value object that carries information about a TimeTracker user.
                    </tt>
                </li>
                <li>Now add the stereotype
                    <tt>ValueObject</tt>
                    to class<tt>UserVO</tt>. To
                    do this, select the class and in the
                    <i>Properties</i>
                    tab, click on<i>Stereotype</i>.
                    In this sub-panel, click on<i>Add Stereotypes...</i>. A popup dialog will appear,
                    check
                    <tt>ValueObject</tt>
                    and click<i>OK</i>. The
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class will now have the
                    <tt>ValueObject</tt>
                    stereotype.
                    <blockquote>
                        <b>Tips &amp; Tricks</b>: AndroMDA profiles define a lot of stereotypes and tag values.
                        Some of them are not needed during this tutorial:<tt>Meta</tt>,<tt>Process</tt>,
                        <tt>Webservice</tt>
                        and<tt>Xml</tt>. You may remove them: it will make the selection of
                        stereotypes easier (since a lot of them won't be displayed anymore).
                        <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                            <li>
                                Select the
                                <tt>timetracker</tt>
                                model. On the
                                <i>Properties</i>
                                tab, activate
                                the
                                <i>Profiles</i>
                                sub-panel.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Select the
                                <tt>Meta</tt>
                                profile and click on<i>Delete Profil</i>. Do the same
                                for<tt>Process</tt>,
                                <tt>Webservice</tt>
                                and
                                <tt>Xml</tt>
                                profiles.
                            </li>
                        </ol>
                    </blockquote>
                </li>
                <li>Let's add
                    <tt>id</tt>
                    as an attribute of<tt>UserVO</tt>. Place your mouse on the
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class and wait until a 'tooltip' appears above it. Click
                    on the little red square. A new attribute is inserted with the
                    specification<tt>&lt;&lt;&gt;&gt;Attribute1</tt>. Write over this specification with this new one:
                    <tt>+id</tt>
                    and press Enter. The red square become a green circle, meaning the attribute is 'public'.
                    Note that attributes are always
                    generated as private members of a class. However the visibilities of the associated
                    getter and setter are determined by the visibility of the attribute specification.
                    In this case we have specified public visibility (by using the plus sign) and hence
                    the getter and setter for the
                    <tt>id</tt>
                    attribute will be public.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Select the attribute<i>id</i>, and in the
                    <i>Properties</i>
                    tab, click on<i>General</i>.
                    In this sub-panel, click on<i>Select Type...</i>. A popup dialog will appear,
                    select
                    <tt>AndroMDA Datatypes::datatype::Long</tt>
                    and click<i>OK</i>.
                </li>
                <li>Now add three more public attributes called<tt>username</tt>,
                    <tt>firstName</tt>
                    and
                    <tt>lastName</tt>
                    to the
                    <tt>UserVO</tt>
                    class. Make them
                    <tt>String</tt>
                    type. In your model two different types called String are available (see above).
                    Use the one from<tt>AndroMDA Datatypes::datatype</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Add a new class to the diagram and name it<tt>UserVO[]</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Make sure your class diagram matches the one shown on the right exactly. (It is okay if
                    your class shows an empty operation compartment. This can be hidden very easily).
                </li>
                <li>Make sure that the RSM model explorer the screen shot shown below.</li>
                <li>Save your
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    model by double-clicking on
                    <tt>timetracker.emx</tt>
                    and clicking on
                    <i>File &gt; Save</i>
                    (<i>Ctrl + S</i>).
                </li>
                <li>
                    Select<i>File &gt; Export...</i>. Choose
                    <i>UML2 Model</i>
                    and then click on<i>Next</i>.
                    As
                    <i>source</i>
                    select
                    <tt>/TimeTracker/timetracker.emx</tt>
                    and as
                    <i>destination</i>
                    browse to<tt>C:\timetracker\mda\src\main\uml</tt>.
                </li>
            </ol>

            <p>
                Congratulations! You have now specified the
                <tt>UserVO</tt>
                value object of
                the
                <tt>TimeTracker</tt>
                application. We are now ready to generate some code.
                Please go back to the main tutorial page and continue from where you left off.
            </p>

        </section>
    </body>
</document>
