<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="naresh@andromda.org">Naresh Bhatia</author>
        <title>Create PersonVO using MagicDraw</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Create PersonVO using MagicDraw">
            <p>
                This page provides directions to create the PersonVO using MagicDraw. The model is
                shown below for your reference.
            </p>

            <p>
                <div align="center">
                    <img src="../../../images/magicdraw/PersonVO.jpg"/>
                </div>
            </p>

            <p>
              <ol>
                <li>In the TimeTracker model create a package called <code>vo</code> under
                    <code>org.andromda.timetracker</code>. We will create our value objects in this package.</li>
                <li>In the Containment Tree on the left, right-click on the <code>vo</code> package and select
                    New Diagram > Class Diagram. Type in Value Objects as the name of this diagram
                    and click OK. The diagram is created and opened in a new window.</li>
                <li>From the Containment Tree on the left, drag the <code>Person</code> class on to the diagram.
                    Warning: It is important to bring in the existing <code>Person</code> class from the <code>domain</code>
                    package into this diagram. DO NOT create a new <code>Person</code> class in this diagram.
                    Doing so will create a new class in the <code>vo</code> package
                    - this is not our intention. All we need is a reference to the existing <code>Person</code>
                    class in the <code>domain</code> package.</li>
                <li>Add a new class to the diagram and name it <code>PersonVO</code>.</li>
                <li>Add the stereotype called ValueObject to <code>PersonVO</code>.</li>
                <li>Add four attributes to <code>PersonVO</code> as shown above.</li>
                <li>Select the dependency relationship from the toolbar. Now left-click the mouse on the
                    <code>Person</code> class, drag it to the <code>PersonVO</code> class and release
                    the mouse. A dependency relationship is added between the two classes.</li>
                <li>Add a new class to the diagram and name it <code>PersonVO[]</code>.</li>
                <li>Make sure your class diagram matches the one shown above.</li>
                <li>Save the model by selecting File > Save Project.</li>
              </ol>
            </p>

            <p>
              We are now ready to generate code for the <code>PersonVO</code> value object. Please go back to the main
              tutorial page and continue from where you left off.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
