<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="wouter@andromda.org">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA Server Howto</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
  		<section name="AndroMDA Server Howto">
			<p>
                In order to get the best performance out of AndroMDA some improvements have
                been implemented that will significantly speed-up the generation process,
                one of these improvements is the AndroMDA server.
  			</p>
            <p>
                The server has been designed to (re)load the UML model in the background thereby
                minimizing the resources needed to keep track of the latest changes. There are
                at least two advantages:
            </p>
            <p>
                <ol>
                    <li>Since the model is kept in memory all the time, the initialization routines
                        required to load it need only to be executed once. Especially in the
                        case where you're regenerating multiple times per day the performance gain
                        is tremendous.</li>
                    <li>Changes to the model are loaded in the background, in a seperate process,
                        and this is done automatically when the server detects the model has been
                        changed. That way the new model will already have been reloaded by the
                        time you want to generate code from it.</li>
                </ol>
            </p>
            <subsection name="Configuration">
                <p>
                    In order to properly launch the server you'll need to configure it
                    in the <code>andromda.xml</code> configuration file. Assuming you have
                    generated your project using <code>andromdapp:generate</code> this file
                    will be located in <code>/mda/conf/andromda.xml</code>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Since AndroMDA 3.2 the server will be configured by default, to fine-tune
                    please see <a href="../configuration.html">Configuring AndroMDA</a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Just make sure the server is listening on a port which isn't in use.
                    Typically the configuration will look like this:
<source language="xml"><![CDATA[
    <server>
        <host>localhost</host>
        <port>4446</port>
    </server>
]]></source>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Starting/Stopping the server">
                <p>
                    So you know how to configure the server, but you're wondering how to launch it.
                    It's very easy if you have generated your project using
                    <code>andromdapp:generate</code>, just type <code>maven start-andromda-server</code>
                    in the root of your project. Mind you, this will block the console so you'll need
                    to open another one to call your project's maven goals. Call
                    <code>maven stop-andromda-server</code> to stop the server process.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Starting and stopping the server has been included in the Maven
                    <code>andromda</code> plugin, please see the corresponding
                    <a href="../../andromda-maven-plugins/andromda-maven-plugin/goals.html">goals documentation</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Example">
                <p>
                    Here is a step-by-step example on how to make sure things are properly working,
                    we'll assume you have generated your project using at least AndroMDA version 3.2
                    as described in the
                    <a href="../starting.html#My_first_AndroMDA_project">Getting Started</a> page.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ol>
                        <li>Open a console and go to the root of your project</li>
                        <li>Open another console and go to the root of your project</li>
                        <li>In the first console type <code>maven start-andromda-server</code></li>
                        <li>Watch the server initializing and loading the model</li>
                        <li>In the second console type <code>maven mda</code> to generate code
                            from the model (most of the time you'll want to build the entire
                            project by simply typing <code>maven</code>, in this example
                            we're performing the code generation part only)</li>
                        <li>Open the UML model with your favorite UML editor, apply a change and
                            save it</li>
                        <li>Watch the server instance in the first console reloading the model</li>
                        <li>Regenerate the code</li>
                        <li>You can keep doing this until you are done modeling...</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    Don't forget Maven allows the <code>-o</code> flag which will instruct it not
                    to download any dependencies, you should use it once you are certain all
                    dependencies have been downloaded into your local Maven repository.
                </p>
            </subsection>
  		</section>
    </body>
</document>
