<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="wouter@andromda.org">Wouter Zoons</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - Bpm4Struts - HowTo - Tables</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Tables">
            <p>
                It's possible to have the cartridge render tables for you from certain parameters
                modeled in UML. These tables use the <a href="http://www.displaytag.org/">displaytag</a>
                tag-library behind the scenes.
            </p>
            <p>
                In order to have these tables rendered for you you will need to model a
                <a href="howto2.html#Page_Variables">page variable</a> that maps onto a descendant of
                <code>java.util.Collection</code> (for example <code>datatype::Collection</code>) or use
                an array of a custom type.
            </p>
            <p>
                Using arrays is interesting when you
                are using dates in columns and you want to specify a custom format, in this case you'll just need to add
                a tagged value to the corresponding attribute of the array's type. This feature elegantly integrates
                with the use of value objects and POJO entities such as found in Hibernate.
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                Do not specify type <code>java.util.Collection</code> directly, but use
                <code>datatype::Collection</code> instead. When specifying an array you must not use an array
                of datatypes, but define your own class instead, add attributes to it
                and model another class representing the array by adding the array suffix to its name, eg.
                <code>[]</code> (see the <a href="samples.html#online-store">online store</a> for an example).
            </p>
            <p>
                Next you will simply need
                to model one or more tagged values onto that parameter. (If you choose to specify more than
                one property per value you can also separate them using commas, nevertheless, it is
                recommended to specify a value per property)
            </p>
<source><![CDATA[
@andromda.presentation.view.table.columns=property1,property2,...,propertyN
]]></source>
            <p>
                Just make sure that each property listed has corresponding accessor methods for each element
                in the collection parameter. This requirement cannot be checked during development so failing
                to conform to it will result in a runtime error.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Hyperlinks">
                <p>
                    It's very common that users want to click on a row in the table and continue to the next page,
                    possibly showing the item in more detail. It's possible to have this feature generated by
                    associating one of the table columns to one of the events exiting that same page.
                </p>
                <p>
                    First of all you will need to model an event with one or more parameters (if you are not sure how to
                    do that then re-read <a href="howto2.html#Event_Parameters">this previous section</a>), make sure
                    this event transition is going <em>out</em> of the page containing the table page-variable.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Second, you will need to make sure the event will be rendered as an hyperlink and not as a regular
                    form post, you can do that by using the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.type=hyperlink</code>
                    tagged value on the transition itself.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Finally link this event to the table page-variable and specify the column in which the hyperlink is
                    to be rendered, this is particularly important since there
                    might be more than a single table from which to choose. In order to achieve this we will be using
                    the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.tablelink=myTable.myColumn</code> tagged value on the transition
                    (replace <code>myTable</code> with the name of your table, and notice how to dot separates both
                    fields).
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    If you don't specify a column name then the hyperlink will be rendered in its own column, the
                    link will show the name of your event, rather than the cell value.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Submitting a row">
                <p>
                    Not only hyperlinks can be modeled this way, also events that work on individual rows. This is
                    very similar to the modeling of hyperlink events, except that here the tagged value should not be
                    set to <code>hyperlink</code>, but to <code>form</code>, like this:
                    <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.type=form</code> (which is the default value
                    if it has not been specified, so you don't actually need to set it).
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    Please note that it is not possible to use a hyperlink when submitting a row. It would be possible
                    only when none of the row values are updateable, but in order to not overly complicate the usage
                    of the bpm4struts cartridge by adding more/complex modeling constraints we prefer to simply
                    restrict sending a row's value using the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.type=form</code> tagged
                    value.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Model an event going out of the page showing the table, add one or more parameters to this
                    event. Every one of these parameters will now be rendered in a widget, and next to each
                    row there will be a button to apply this action on it. Clicking the button will invoke a JavaScript
                    function that will sumbit a form to the target action; browsers not supporting JavaScript or having
                    JavaScript disabled will not be able to use this functionality.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Don't forget to add the tagged value, but it's not needed to specify any column this time:
                    <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.tablelink=myTable</code> No need to specify a column name in this
                    tagged value as these buttons will always be put in their own column.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Any widget is allowed, but if you still prefer to have plain text rendered instead of a widget
                    then simply use the <code>plaintext</code> field type, like this:
<source><![CDATA[
    @andromda.presentation.web.view.field.type=plaintext
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    If there are many events linked to the same table, and the same parameter is repeated across
                    different events, then the hyperlink events with take priority, meaning you will never see any
                    input widget for those parameters in an hyperlink event.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It's possible to have an image instead of an hyperlink or button, for this you'll have to
                    use the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.type=image</code> tagged value on the event transition.
                    An entry in the resource bundle will be generated for the image, and the value will be resolved
                    against the current contextPath (much like the struts tags taking a <code>page</code> attribute).
                </p>
                <p>
                    This has the advantage that the image can be i18n'ed, allowing you to display a different image
                    per language or locale.
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    By default the image will be missing from the generated application, you will have to add it
                    manually to your source directory and have it copied into the war bundle. You can use the
                    <a href="tips.html">copy-over</a> feature to achieve this.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Submitting selected rows">
                <p>
                    In addition to the submittal of a specific row it is also possible to select a couple of rows
                    and submit them, mind you, this mechanism works a little different than one might expect.
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    This feature is only able to submit <em>one single value</em> per row, it is <em>not</em> possible
                    to submit all column values for all selected rows.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In order to achieve this we use the table link and action type tagged values as before,
                    only this time the value is of the action type is <code>table</code>, like this:
<source><![CDATA[
    @andromda.presentation.web.action.tablelink=myTable
    @andromda.presentation.web.action.type=table
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Let's list the things to do in order to successfully make use of this feature:
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ol>
                        <li>make sure you have a table page-variable</li>
                        <li>have an action with a single event parameter, make sure this parameter carries the same
                            name as one of the table columns, it will be that column's value that will be sent when the
                            checkbox for the row is checked</li>
                        <li>add the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.tablelink</code> tagged value on
                            the action transition</li>
                        <li>add the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.type=table</code> tagged value on
                            the action transition</li>
                    </ol>
                </p>
                <p>
                    In summary: this will result in the cartridge having generated code that will place a checkbox in
                    front of each row, the checkbox carries the value of the table column with the same name as the
                    <em>event parameter</em> modeled on the transition. Each such action will have a button and there's
                    also a button to select or deselect all rows. When a checkbox is selected its corresponding value
                    will be sent to the server when one of the action buttons is clicked.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Multibox">
                <p>
                    One very special type of widget, which is a little more complicated to understand at first, is
                    the <code>multibox</code> widget. Basically it allows you to render checkboxes whose
                    <code>checked</code> statuses need to be controlled by another property.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Let's say you want to render a checkbox for each row, but the value behind is not of a
                    <code>boolean</code> type but a <code>String</code>; in that case you can setup a page-variable
                    which holds an <code>array</code> or a <code>Collection</code> of <code>String</code> instances,
                    when a value for a specific row matches at least one of the elements the checkbox will be checked.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The <code>available</code> column of the table in the example image below has the following
                    tagged values:
                </p>
<source><![CDATA[
@andromda.presentation.web.view.field.tablelink=itemList
@andromda.presentation.web.view.field.type=multibox
@andromda.struts.view.field.multibox=availableItems
]]></source>
                <p>
                    In this example the <code>availableItems</code> page-variable is used to match the
                    <code>available</code> property against.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Example">
            <p>
                This example is taken from the
                <a href="samples.html#online-store">Online Store</a> sample.
                It is showing two hyperlink events, on the <code>id</code> and <code>publisher</code> columns
                respectively, and one form event that will submit the <code>id</code>, <code>edition</code> and
                <code>available</code> fields (see the
                <a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/*checkout*/andromda/samples/online-store/mda/src/uml/online-store.xml.zip">
                UML model</a>, opens in MagicDraw only).
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="howto/org/andromda/test/online-store-table.gif"/>
            </p>
            <subsection name="The 'id' hyperlink">
                <p>
                    In the <code>id</code> column you can see an hyperlink for each row. This has been achieved by
                    modeling the following things:
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>model an event going out of the page</li>
                        <li>add a parameter to this event's trigger, give it the name <code>id</code></li>
                        <li>add the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.tablelink</code> tag to the event,
                            the value should be the name of the table separated from the column name using a dot, ie.
                            <code>itemList.id</code>. Not specifying the column name will make put this link in
                            a separate column on the right.
                        </li>
                        <li>add the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.type=hyperlink</code> tag to the event,
                            this denotes this action to be rendered as an hyperlink pointing to the target
                            Struts action.
                        </li>
                        <li>add the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.view.field.type=link</code> tagged
                            value to the 'id' event trigger parameter. Unless you do this the
                            field will be rendered using the default widget which will be a text-input field.
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    This feature is interesting when you want to see the details of a specific item in the list.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="The 'publisher' hyperlink">
                <p>
                    Equivalent to the <code>id</code> hyperlink, except that this time we add two parameters to this
                    event: <code>id</code> and <code>publisher</code>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Make sure to have the hyperlink point to the <code>publisher</code> column, like this:
                    <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.tablelink=itemList.publisher</code>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    This feature is interesting when you want to see information on a related property, in this case
                    the homepage of the company or person that has published this item.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="The 'edition', 'available' and 'buy' widgets">
                <p>
                    All these elements make up a specific event, which has been modeled like this:
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>model an event going out of the page, call it <code>buy</code></li>
                        <li>for each field model a parameter, specify the appropriate widget for each of these
                            parameters (go <a href="howto2.html#Event_Parameters">here</a> if you don't remember
                            how to do that), in this example <code>edition</code> is a 'select' and
                            <code>available</code> is a 'multibox'
                        </li>
                        <li>add the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.action.tablelink</code> tag to the event, the value should
                            be the name of the table
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    If you wish to include the <code>title</code> parameter but you don't want to have it rendered
                    as an input field, then simply use the <code>@andromda.presentation.web.view.field.type=plaintext</code>
                    tagged value on that parameter.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                Next up is the <a href="howto9.html">Other Content</a> section.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
