<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>
            Create UserService
        </title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Create UserService">

            <p>
                This page provides directions to create the
                <tt>UserService</tt>
                using ArgoUML.
                The model is shown below for your reference.
            </p>

            <div align="center">
                <img src="images/UserService.png" alt="UserService"/>
            </div>
            <p>

                <img src="images/ServicePackage.png" alt="Containment Tree"/>
            </p>
            <p>
                We will create
                <tt>UserService</tt>
                in a package named<tt>org.andromda.timetracker.service</tt>.
                When finished, the containment tree in ArgoUML will look like the screen shot
                on the right.
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>In the TimeTracker model create a package called
                    <tt>service</tt>
                    under<tt>
                        org.andromda.timetracker</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>In the Containment Tree on the left, right-click on the
                    <tt>service</tt>
                    package
                    and select Create DiagramNew Class Diagram. Select the new unnamed diagram
                    and type in Services as its name on the property panel.
                    The diagram is created and opened in a new window.
                </li>
                <li>Add a new class to the diagram and name it<tt>UserService</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Add the stereotype called Service to<tt>UserService</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Let's add the
                    <tt>getAllUsers()</tt>
                    method to<tt>UserService</tt>. Double-click
                    on the operations compartment (the bottom one) of the
                    <tt>UserService</tt>
                    class
                    to create a new operation. A new operation is inserted with the specification
                    &quot;+newOperation() : void&quot;. Write over this specification with this new one:
                    &quot;+getAllUsers() : UserVO[]&quot;.
                </li>
                <li>Similar to creating new attributes, you can also create new operations from
                    the property panel if that fits your work style better. Click on the
                    New Attribute Tool
                    <img src="images/ToolNewAttribute.png" alt="New Attribute Tool"/>
                    and fill in the name, visibility, and return type on the Operation property panel
                    for the newly created operation. The property panel provides more explicit
                    guidance, but typing a specification on the diagram tends to be faster for
                    experienced users.
                </li>
                <li>Make sure your class diagram matches the one shown above.</li>
                <li>Make sure that the ArgoUML explorer pane matches the screen shot shown above.</li>
                <li>Save the model by selecting FileSave Project (or just type keyboard
                    accelerator Ctrl/S).
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                We are now ready to generate code for the<tt>UserService</tt>. Please go back
                to the main tutorial page and continue from where you left off.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
