<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="naresh@andromda.org">Naresh Bhatia</author>
        <title>The Sample Application</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="The Sample Application - TimeTracker">
            <p>
                Northwind Corporation uses a paper based system to track the time
                of their employees. This process is highly inefficient and hence
                the CIO of Northwind has tasked you to create an online time
                tracking system called TimeTracker. Unfortunately, he wants the
                system delivered by next week and if you can't meet this deadline
                he will give away the job to someone else. Suddenly you remember
                a conversation with your friend the other day where he was raving
                about how AndroMDA can generate large portions of an application
                from business level specifications. You say to yourself "If this
                is really true, it will help me meet my deadline. Let's give AndroMDA
                a try." So you accept the CIO's offer and get to work.
            </p>

            <p>
                Your first stop is at the office of the Director of Human Resources.
                You ask her to describe the current time tracking process. She says
                "At the beginning of every week, each person picks up a new timecard
                from the supply room. As they work on different tasks, they record
                their start and stop times on this timecard. Every task has a task id
                which they look up from the employee handbook. At the end of the
                week people submit their timecards to their managers for approval.
                A manager can either approve or reject the timecard. If rejected, they
                must put a comment on the timecard stating the reason for rejection.
                The submitter of the timecard must then make necessary corrections
                and resubmit the timecard for approval." You politely ask the director
                for a copy of a typical timecard. Here's what she gives you.
                <p>
                    <div align="center">
                        <img src="images/SampleTimecard.jpg"/>
                    </div>
                </p>
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="What's Next?">
            <p>
                Armed with this knowledge you are eager to get started. You rush
                back to your office. It is time to install the necessary development
                tools and software. Click <a href="env-setup.html">here</a> to get
                started.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
