<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>
            TimeTracker Tour
        </title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="TimeTracker Tour">

            <p>
                Before we start building TimeTracker from scratch, let's take a test drive of the
                finished application. This will give you a good feel for what you are about to embark
                on and also give you some direction in case you get stuck. You will also get hands
                on experience with various development procedures, such as administering MySQL and
                JBoss. These will be helpful when you start building your application from scratch.
            </p>

            <p>
                Follow these steps to build and run TimeTracker:
            </p>
            <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                <li>Download the source for the
                    <a href="timetracker-completed.zip">
                        finished application
                    </a>
                    and unzip it at <tt>C:\</tt>. You will get a directory
                    called<tt>C:\timetracker-completed</tt>.
                    <i>Note: If you decide to unzip the tutorial
                        at a different location, make sure there are no spaces in your pathname - otherwise
                        Maven will run into build problems.
                    </i>
                </li>
                <li>If you downloaded a version of MySql driver other than 5.0.4, then you must edit
                    the file<tt>C:\timetracker-completed\pom.xml</tt>. Look for the two instances
                    of
                    <tt>5.0.4</tt>
                    and change them to the version of your MySQL driver.
                </li>
                <li>Open a Command Prompt in the directory <tt>C:\timetracker-completed</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Execute the command
                    <tt>mvn install</tt>
                    to build the application. This step
                    downloads all the libraries needed to build the TimeTracker application from remote
                    Maven repositories. These libraries have been specified in the various
                    <tt>pom.xml</tt>
                    files under the TimeTracker source tree. Due to the sheer number and size of these
                    libraries, this step will take a significant amount of time. However, be assured
                    that your next build will be much faster because all the necessary dependencies
                    will be available locally. Note that sometimes due to bad Internet connectivity
                    or server load, Maven may not be able to download all dependencies in one go. If
                    your build fails due to this reason, try to issue the command again until you get
                    a successful build.
                </li>
                <li>Let this Command Prompt remain open for subsequent steps.</li>
                <li>Now that we have built the application, let us create a database schema to store
                    its data. We will create a schema called
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    and a user called
                    <tt>timetracker</tt>
                    who has full access to this schema.
                    <ul>
                        <li>Open MySQL Administrator. Login in as root.</li>
                        <li>Click
                            <tt>Catalogs</tt>
                            in the left navigation bar.
                        </li>
                        <li>Right click in the lower left panel (called Schemata) and select
                            <tt>Create NewSchema</tt>.
                        </li>
                        <li>Enter the schema name as
                            <tt>timetracker</tt>
                            and click OK.
                        </li>
                        <li>Click
                            <tt>User Administration</tt>
                            in the left navigation bar.
                        </li>
                        <li>Click
                            <tt>New User</tt>
                            and add a new user called timetracker with password
                            timetracker.
                        </li>
                        <li>Select the
                            <tt>Schema Privileges</tt>
                            tab and then click the timetracker schema.
                        </li>
                        <li>Click the
                            <tt>&lt;&lt;</tt>
                            button to assign all privileges to the timetracker
                            user and click<tt>Apply Changes</tt>.
                        </li>
                        <li>Close MySQL Administrator.</li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Now let's populate the timetracker schema with the tables required by the application.
                    To do this run the following command in the Command Prompt opened earlier:
                    <br/>
                    <tt>mvn -f core/pom.xml andromdapp:schema -Dtasks=create</tt>
                </li>
                <li>Now that the tables have been created we need to populate the tables with some sample
                    data. Follow the steps below to do this:
                    <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
                        <li>Open MySQL Query Browser. Login as timetracker.</li>
                        <li>Select File &gt; OpenScript and open the following script file:
                            <tt>C:\timetracker-completed\app\src\main\sql\static-data-insert.sql</tt>.
                            Click the Execute button to on the top right to execute the script and populate
                            static data in the database (users and tasks).
                        </li>
                        <li>Now open the script file
                            <tt>test-data-insert.sql</tt>
                            in the same directory
                            and execute it. This will insert test data in the database (timecards and time allocations).
                        </li>
                        <li>Close MySQL Query Browser.</li>
                    </ol>
                </li>
                <li>Let's start the JBoss server so we can deploy the TimeTracker application to it.
                    To do this, open a second Command Prompt in the JBoss bin directory (<tt>C:\jboss-4.0.4\bin</tt>)
                    and execute the command <tt>run</tt>. JBoss will take some time to start up.
                    Wait for a message similar to this to make sure JBoss has started successfully:
                    <br/>
                    <tt>19:50:01,285 INFO [Server] JBoss (MX MicroKernel) [4.0.4.GA (build: CVSTag=JBoss_4_0_4_GA
                        date=200605151000)] Started in 39s:517ms</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Now we are ready to deploy the finished application to the JBoss server. Go to the
                    previous Command Prompt (in the directory <tt>C:\timetracker-completed</tt>)
                    and execute the command:
                    <br/>
                    <tt>mvn -f app/pom.xml -Ddeploy</tt>
                    <br/>
                    You will notice that the TimeTracker EAR (Executable Archive) file is copied over
                    to the JBoss deploy directory (<tt>C:\jboss-4.0.4\server\default\deploy</tt>)
                    and the JBoss console displays several messages indicating that it is deploying
                    the application. Wait for a message similar to this to make sure TimeTracker has
                    started successfully:
                    <br/>
                    <tt>19:59:53,767 INFO [EARDeployer] Started J2EE application: file:/D:/jboss-4.0.4/server/default/deploy/timetracker-1.0-SNAPSHOT.ear</tt>
                </li>
                <li>Now we are ready to test the application. Open a browser and make it point to http://localhost:8080/timetracker.
                    (If you have changed the JBoss HTTP port, then replace 8080 with the appropriate
                    port number.) The login page should appear.
                </li>
                <li>Enter
                    <tt>nbhatia</tt>
                    as the username and
                    <tt>cooldude</tt>
                    as the password.
                    Click the
                    <i>Login</i>
                    button. The TimeTracker home page should appear with links
                    to various sections of the application.
                </li>
                <li>Click on<i>Search Timecards</i>. The search screen should appear. Try changing
                    the search criteria and click the
                    <i>Search</i>
                    button. The
                    <i>Search Results</i>
                    panel should show appropriate results. Note that the remaining TimeTracker screens
                    are under construction.
                </li>
                <li>When you are satisfied with the TimeTracker tour, you may stop the JBoss Server
                    by typing Control-C in the JBoss Command Prompt.
                </li>
                <li>We can now drop all the tables in the TimeTracker database in preparation of your
                    turn to build the application from scratch. To do this, simply go to the first Command
                    Prompt in the
                    <tt>C:\timetracker-completed</tt>
                    directory and excute the following
                    command:
                    <br/>
                    <tt>mvn -f core/pom.xml andromdapp:schema -Dtasks=drop</tt>
                </li>
            </ol>
            <p>
                Well, now that you have seen the TimeTracker application in action, are you ready
                to recreate it from scratch? I am hearing a resounding yes! Alright, click
                <a href="development-approach.html">here</a> to go ahead.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
