<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="mbohlen@mbohlen.de">Matthias Bohlen</author>
        <author email="cwbrandon@users.sourceforge.net">Chad Brandon</author>
        <title>The Car Rental System sample application</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="The Car Rental System sample application">
            <p>
                The car rental system application is one of multiple samples showing what you can do
                with AndroMDA. In order to get the sources for this sample you are required to download
                an AndroMDA 3.x distribution.
            </p>
            <p>
                The model has been designed using the Poseidon case tool.  You will find
                the model inside this <a href="resources/CarRentalSystem.xml.zip">file</a>. 
                Open and view this model with Magic Draw's community edition, which can 
                be downloaded from <a href="http://www.nomagic.com">No Magic's web site</a>.
                Although Poseidon CE is free, not everybody has installed it. Therefore, we have
                used Poseidon PE to generate an HTML/JPEG representation of the car rental system sample model
                browsable as <a href="../umldoc/index.html">HTML</a>.
            </p>
            <subsection name="The Model">
                <p>
                    The model consists
                    of a package with use cases, explaining what the main actors (users)
                    of the application might be and what they can do with the system.
                    The main actors are an administrator who creates things
                    like cars and types of cars, a customer who reserves cars for certain
                    dates, and a call center who can reserve cars as well as record
                    car accidents. Last, but not least, there are car loan and
                    reception desks who do what their names imply. :-)
                    Each use case has an activity diagram attached to it which explains
                    the message flow of that particular use case.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The rest of the model contains all the design level packages with the
                    class diagrams inside. The design level packages are
                    <code>admins</code>,
                    <code>contracts</code>,
                    <code>customers</code> and
                    <code>inventory</code>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="The Implementation">
                <p>
                     This sample was generated using the following cartridges:
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Tier</th>
                            <th>Technology</th>
                            <th>Cartridge</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Persistence (Entity Beans) and Business (Stateless Session EJBs)</td>
                            <td>EJB 2.0 (Stateless Session and Entity EJBs)</td>
                            <td>andromda-ejb-cartridge</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Presentation</td>
                            <td>Struts 1.2.4</td>
                            <td>andromda-bpm4struts-cartridge</td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Building and Deploying">
                <p>
                    To build the car rental system, just cd to the andromda distribution's 
                    <em>samples/car-rental-system</em> directory and type <em>maven</em>, 
                    this will build both EJB and Hibernate versions of the application.  
                    You will find the deployable ear file located in 
                    <em>samples/car-rental-system/app/target</em>. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    This ear files can be deployed within a JBoss application server instance 
                    (like any typical J2EE application) by dropping
                    the ear files within your <em>$JBOSS_HOME/server/default/deploy</em> directory.  
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    Because the application uses the HypersonicSql Database bundled with JBoss,
                    you'll need to make sure you have JBoss running before attempting to deploy
                    the application.
                </p>           
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Using">
            <p>
                Once the car rental system has been successfully deployed within JBoss (i.e.
                no exceptions), point your browser
                to <a href="http://localhost:8080/car-rental-system">http://localhost:8080/car-rental-system</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                You may now begin to explore the application:
                <ol>
                    <li>
                        Login as an administrator
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Create things such as car types, cars and customers
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Logout
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Login as a customer and reserve the cars created from
                        step 2 car(s) for certain date(s).
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Finally, you may start a JDBC browser to have a look at the 
                        database tables with their beautiful CMR relationships in 
                        the disguise of foreign keys
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </p>
            <p class="highlight">
                When you log in as administrator for the first time, the system will prompt
                you for a new username and password.  Please memorize these for the next
                time you log in.
            </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
