<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>AndroMDA - News</title>
        <author email="michail@andromda.org">Michail Plushnikov</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="UML2 2.x is now the default supported by 3.4-SNAPSHOT">
            <p>Wednesday, 17 February 2010</p>

            <p>The default EMF UML2 repository implementation was changed from UML2 1.x to UML2 2.x, in order to support
                the most current versions of the MagicDraw and Rational tools. Due to conflicting dependencies in the
                uml libraries, both implementations could not be supported at the same time.
            </p>

            <p>Have a look at
                <a href="http://forum.andromda.org/viewtopic.php?t=6724">here</a>
                and
                <a href="http://forum.andromda.org/viewtopic.php?t=6526">here</a>
                for more information.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Andromda hosted at Sonatype repository">
            <p>Friday, 01 January 2010</p>

            <p>Andromda maven2 repository is now hosted on the Sonatype repository.
                You can access all artifacts on <a href="http://oss.sonatype.org/content/groups/public/org/andromda">Sonatype</a>
            </p>

            <p>The old Andromda maven2 repository under <a href="http://www.andromda.org/maven2">http://www.andromda.org/maven2</a> was configurated to redirect all
                requests going to "org.andromda" group to the new repository.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Andromda has moved to a new server...">
            <p>Tuesday, 01 December 2009</p>
            <p>Andromda has moved to a new server. Thank you for waiting.</p>

            <p>We have updated our forum to a new version of phpBB (v.2.0.x ->v.3.0.x)
                We have updated our Jira to a new version (v.3.X ->v.4.x)
            </p>

            <p>We apologize for any inconvenience and downtime in the last few days.</p>
        </section>

        <section name="Maven 2.2.1 compatibility">
            <p>Monday, 12 October 2009</p>

            <p>The current Snapshot of Andromda is now fully compatible with maven 2.2.1 version.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="Andromda goes SVN">
            <p>Sunday, 28 June 2009</p>

            <p>The andromda source repository has been migrated to SVN.</p>

            <p>The V3_x_HEAD branch has been moved to trunk.</p>

            <p>You can access new repository <a href="http://andromda.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/andromda">here</a></p>
        </section>
        <section name="Site Recovery">
            <p>Sunday, 28 June 2009</p>

            <p>The site suffered a hard drive failure. The site is now partially restored. There are some missing links.
                Please bare with us while we complete the restoration of the site. The forum is now back up.
                The maven repositories are working.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="UML2 2.x and RSM 7.x support added to andromda">
            <p>Friday, 05 June 2009</p>

            <p>Unfortunately, the UML2 1.x EMF dependencies are not compatible with the UML2 2.x dependencies,
                both cannot be loaded by andromda at the same time. Since the maven andromda-plugins loads and validates
                all repositories when loading, and there is no way (that I know of) to change the plugin dependencies
                dynamically, the dependencies must be changed manually before running. Any suggestions would be welcome.
                Perhaps we can deprecate UML2 1.x support when everything has been thoroughly tested.
            </p>

            <p>
                <a href="http://forum.andromda.org/viewtopic.php?t=6526">Read more</a>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Codegeneration 2009">
            <p>Thursday, 14 May 2009</p>

            <p>
                <a href="http://www.codegeneration.net/cg2009/">Codegeneration 2009</a>
            </p>

            <p>CG2009 is for people who want to successfully apply or learn more about the following topics:</p>

            <ul>
                <li>Code Generation !</li>
                <li>Domain-Specific Languages</li>
                <li>Model-Driven Development (MDD), Model-Driven Architecture (MDA)</li>
                <li>Eclipse Modelling Tools, openArchitectureWare (oAW), Xtext etc.</li>
                <li>Executable UML</li>
                <li>Model-Driven Software Development (MDSD)</li>
                <li>Domain-Specific Modelling</li>
                <li>Software Factories and Software Product Lines</li>
                <li>Generative Software Development and other similar approaches.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="AndroMDA 3.3 Final is released and available for download!">
            <p>Tuesday, 22 April 2008</p>

            <p>The AndroMDA committers team is proud to announce release 3.3 of the Model Driven Architecture framework AndroMDA.
                This release primarily contains bug fixes and smaller enhancements such as:
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>Better support for latest versions of Maven (tested with Maven 2.0.8)</li>
                <li>Ability to read *.emx files from RSA directly without the need to convert them to *.uml2.
                    AndroMDA also checks for the IBM-specific metamodels for graphical elements in UML diagrams.
                    If it finds them on the classpath, it registers them with the EMF package factory registry.
                </li>
            </ul>

            <p>You can download the new version using Maven 2 or directly from SF.net.
                Have fun and enhance your productivity with AndroMDA!
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="AndroMDA 3.2 Final is released and available for download!">
            <p>Friday, 10 November 2006</p>

            <p>The AndroMDA committers team is proud to announce release 3.2 of the Model Driven Architecture framework AndroMDA.
                Highlights in this release are:
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>Support for UML 2.0 and Eclipse EMF-based tools (MagicDraw 11.6, RSM, etc.)</li>
                <li>Now integrates with Maven 2</li>
                <li>Code generation for PSM metamodel classes</li>
                <li>Support for the Freemarker template engine</li>
                <li>Code generation for Java generics</li>
                <li>Enhanced documentation, lots of tutorials</li>
                <li>Bug fixes and smaller enhancements</li>
            </ul>

            <p>You can download the new version using Maven 2 or directly from SF.net.</p>

            <p>Have fun and enhance your productivity with AndroMDA!</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
