<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="vancek@users.sourceforge.net">Vance Karimi</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - EJB3 - TestNG with JBoss Embeddable EJB3 Microcontainer</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="TestNG with JBoss Embeddable EJB3 Microcontainer">
            <p>
                As a developer, you are always tempted to get by with smallest amount of unit testing...some
                even avoid the subject all together.  With the introduction of EJB 3.0, it was intended to make
                things easier, including testing.  Setting up the right test environment was always a difficult,
                especially when you don't always have the luxury of time to get it right!
            </p>
            <p>
                The EJB3 cartridge now provides a basic test framework for your session beans.  You can now
                use the popular TestNG framework, along with JBoss Embeddable EJB3 Microcontainer to perform
                your tests outside of the application server.
            </p>
            <p>
                Read up on the <a href="http://docs.jboss.org/ejb3/embedded/embedded.html">JBoss Embedded container</a>.
                Read about the <a href="http://www.testng.org/">TestNG framework</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                The example widely available on the internet uses JUnit in combination with TestNG.  The EJB3 cartridge
                only uses TestNG with Maven2.  It is currently using TestNG version 4.7-jdk15 and JBoss Embeddable
                ALPHA_9.
            </p>
            <a name="Setup"/>
            <subsection name="Setup">
                <p>
                    You do not need to download any of the tools mentioned above.  The cartridge will generate
                    all the required configuration necessary for the JBoss Embeddable container.  All the
                    required artifacts are also available from the AndroMDA repository.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Because we consider testing such a key component of a project, there is no option to enable or
                    disable the test framework with an EJB3 project.  Everything is generated whether you want it
                    or not.  However, all the tests will finish successfully (as there is not implementation for them).
                </p>
                <p>
                    All you need to do is follow the <a href="project.html">project howto</a> to generate your
                    EJB3 project.  Make sure you are running the latest AndroMDA since the test framework is only
                    available from AndroMDA version 3.3-SNAPSHOT onwards.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The test framework will be generated as long as you have at least 1 session bean modeled
                    in your project.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Configuration"/>
            <subsection name="Configuration">
                <p>
                    The following are typical testing configuration files generated for an <i>ejb3</i> project.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ul>
                        <li class="gen">Auto-generated source that does not need manual editing</li>
                        <li class="impl">Auto-generated source that should be edited manually</li>
                        <li class="changed">File that is affected by the modifications applied in this section</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <ul>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/default.persistence.properties"><code>default.persistence.properties</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/ejb3-interceptors-aop.xml"><code>ejb3-interceptors-aop.xml</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/embedded-jboss-beans.xml"><code>embedded-jboss-beans.xml</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/jboss-jms-beans.xml"><code>jboss-jms-beans.xml</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/jndi.properties"><code>jndi.properties</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/log4j.xml"><code>log4j.xml</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/login-config.xml"><code>login-config.xml</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/security-beans.xml"><code>security-beans.xml</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/roles.properties"><code>roles.properties</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/users.properties"><code>users.properties</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/testng.xml"><code>testng.xml</code></a></li>
                        <li class="impl"><a class="changed" href="howto/org/andromda/test/testjms.xml"><code>testjms.xml</code></a></li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    When you first run <i>mvn</i> over your project, the cartridge will generate all the
                    JBoss Embeddable container configuration files in <code>core/src/test/resources</code>.
                    All these files are generated ONCE ONLY and will NOT be over-written.  You can safely make
                    any modifications to any of these files.
                </p>
                <p>
                    There is one exception to the latter.  The <code>testng.xml</code> configuration file is also
                    generated in <code>core/src/test/resource</code>, however, this is over-written on every
                    run over your model.  This is because when you add a new session bean, the trigger to
                    run the tests for this new bean is inserted into the <code>testng.xml</code> file.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Once of the most interesting configuration files generated is the <code>embedded-jboss-beans.xml</code>.
                    Take a look at your project's file and notice that the EJB3 cartridge has added 
                    your datasource to this file, along with the existing <code>DefaultDS</code> datasource, which
                    is used by the JMS provider.  You are free to modify the connection settings so that
                    you point this to your development database server.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The <code>log4j.xml</code> file in this directory sets the <i>Threshold</i> to <code>WARN</code>
                    by default.  If you want to see more detailed log information to the console while the tests
                    are running, change this to something like <code>DEBUG</code>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The <code>login-config.xml</code> sets up the JAAS environment for your tests.  If you had
                    enabled security before running maven over your project the first time, everything will be
                    generated for you and you don't need to worry about the following.
                    If you had not
                    enable security for your project on the first run, a relevant security context will not be
                    generated for you in this file.  Say that you want to enable security at a later point, then
                    by simply following <a href="howto8.html">the security howto</a>, you uncomment the
                    <code>securityRealm</code> property in the <b>ejb3</b> and the web framework namespaces.  You 
                    must then copy the last <code>application-policy</code> section of the <code>login-config.xml</code>
                    and change the name property to your <code>application.id</code>.  If your project application id
                    name is <b>howtomodel</b>, the <code>login-config.xml</code> should contain the following:
<source language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <application-policy name="howtomodel">
    <authentication>
      <login-module code="org.jboss.security.auth.spi.UsersRolesLoginModule"
        flag="required"/>
    </authentication>
  </application-policy>
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The cartridge will also generate a <code>roles.properties</code> and <code>users.properties</code>
                    which will help provide basic JAAS authentication for users/roles.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Session_Tests"/>
            <subsection name="Session Tests">
                <p>
                    Now take a look in your source folder <code>core/src/test/java</code>.  You should have a file
                    named <code>EJB3Container.java</code> in one of the packages here.  This file starts and
                    shuts down the embeddable container before and after running any tests respectively.  It also
                    provides helper static methods to get the <code>InitialContext</code> so you can retrieve
                    the stub for the session bean (local or remote interface) from JNDI.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It is important to note that if you want to propagate security credentials (principal and password)
                    because you have enable security and secured your session beans by modeling actors to the class
                    or operations, you must use the overloaded <code>getInitialContext</code> methods with signature 
                    that allows you to provide a username and password.  The generated tests actually provide a basic
                    template that shows you how to do this.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In case you did not enable security on the first generation run, and find you need it later,
                    apart from following the instructions above to modify the <code>login-config.xml</code>,
                    you must also modify the <code>EJB3Container.java</code> to uncomment the following section
                    in the <i>startup</i> method:
<source><![CDATA[
            logger.info("==>Deploying security-beans");
            EJB3StandaloneBootstrap.deployXmlResource("security-beans.xml");
            logger.info("==>Deployed security-beans");
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Now open up any of the test classes.  These are generated to the <code>core/src/test/java</code>
                    source folder in the corresponding package.  You will notice the EJB3 cartridge just creates
                    one test case per session bean business operation.  The the test source files will NOT be
                    over-written, so if you add or delete business operations from your model, you must make the
                    changes to these files manually.
                </p>
                <p>
                    You may have noticed how simple these test sources really are and you may be wondering how
                    we start and stop the embeddable microcontainer and deploy our archives which contain the EJB 3
                    beans.  Take a look at your <code>testng.xml</code> in <code>core/src/test/resources</code>.
                    The first class listed to run is the <code>EJB3Container</code>.  This will call the
                    annotated methods to start and shutdown the embeddable container before and after your tests
                    respectively.
                </p>
                <p>
                    You can now open the tests and add your implementation before running maven over the <i>core</i>
                    project or running the tests.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <a name="Message_Driven_Bean_Tests"/>
            <subsection name="Message Driven Tests">
                <p>
                    If you have one or more message driven beans, you must make sure the 
                    <code>EJB3Container.java</code> contains the following section
                    in the <i>startup</i> method:
<source><![CDATA[
            logger.info("==>Deploying jboss-jms-beans - init JBoss MQ core services");
            EJB3StandaloneBootstrap.deployXmlResource("jboss-jms-beans.xml");
            logger.info("==>Deployed jboss-jms-beans");
            
            logger.info("==>Configure test queue and topic");
            EJB3StandaloneBootstrap.deployXmlResource("testjms.xml");
            logger.info("==>Configured test queues and topics");
]]></source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The cartridge will generate one test class with one test case per message driven bean to 
                    the <code>core/src/test/java</code> source folder in the corresponding package.  
                    The the test source files will NOT be
                    over-written, so if you wish, you can add further cases.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Take a look at your <code>testng.xml</code> in <code>core/src/test/resources</code>.
                    Apart from the other session test classes, you also have a message driven test class
                    reference.  This is how message driven tests are triggered.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Finally, take a look at <code>testjms.xml</code>.  This file contains the necessary
                    configuration to create the queue/topics within the embedded container before the
                    MDB's are deployed and tests are run.  This file will be automatically re-generated on
                    every run, so when you add another MDB, this file will be updated to reflect the
                    addition of another queue or topic.
                </p>
                <p class="highlight">
                    For your message driven test framework to work, you need to make sure the <code>jms-ra.rar</code>
                    and <code>jcainflow.rar</code> RAR files exist in your project <code>src/test/resources</code> 
                    folder.  These are from JBoss Embeddable Microcontainer <code>lib</code>.  When you run
                    your model generation phase, these libs will be automatically copied to your resources
                    folder.  We are forced to do this until Eclipse (perhaps other IDE's don't have this issue) can
                    include .rar files in the project classpath.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
