<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="vancek@users.sourceforge.net">Vance Karimi</author>
        <title>AndroMDA - EJB3 - Installation &amp; Configuration</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Installation">
            <p>
                Since the EJB3 cartridge is not part of the base AndroMDA package, you need to know a
                few things to get started with the cartridge.  This installation and configuration
                guide should provide enough information to get you started.
            </p>
            <a name="Requirements"/>
            <subsection name="Requirements">
	            <p>
	                You must have the latest Maven (currently 2.0.4) installed and configured.
	                You can install Maven 
	                <a href="http://maven.apache.org/download.html#Installation">here</a>.
	            </p>
	            <p class="highlight">
	                If you want to build the site docs, you need to download the latest Maven 2.0.x source
	                from https://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/maven/components/branches/maven-2.0.x and follow
	                the instructions to build, assemble and set your M2_HOME and PATH variables.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                You need to have an instance of AndroMDA 3.2.  At the time of writing this, 3.2 RC1
	                was released but the latest 3.2-SNAPSHOT from CVS contains updates to the project generator
	                and site plugin, and is more suitable to use with the EJB3 cartridge.  Follow the anonymous
	                CVS access at <a href="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=73047">AndroMDA project</a> to
	                checkout the latest <b>andromda-all</b>.
	            </p>
	        </subsection>
            <a name="Getting_the_Cartridge"/>
            <subsection name="Getting the Cartridge">
	            <p>
	                The first thing you need to do is checkout the latest EJB3 cartridge from
	                CVS.  Follow the anonymous CVS access at
	                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=154568">andromdaplugins project</a>
	                on SourceForge to checkout the latest <b>andromda-ejb</b> module.
	            </p>
	        </subsection>
            <a name="Building_the_Cartridge"/>
            <subsection name="Building the Cartridge">
	            <p>
	                Once you have checked out the andromda-ejb3 cartridge, you can simply build it by
	                going to the root folder of the project and running <i>mvn</i>.
	            </p>
	        </subsection>
            <a name="Building_Reports"/>
            <subsection name="Building Reports">
	            <p>
	                To build the EJB3 cartridge site documentation requires a few extra Maven 2 plugins
	                to be downloaded from the Maven 2 sandbox in SVN.  The
	                <a href="http://maven.apache.org/guides/development/guide-building-m2.html">Maven build</a>
	                documentation will give you some information on how to access their SVN.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                You will need to check out the following plugins from Maven <b>sandbox</b>.
	                <ul>
	                    <li><p>maven-changes-plugin</p></li>
	                    <li><p>maven-changelog-plugin</p></li>
	                </ul>
	                Once you have built them (mvn install), these plugins will reside in your local repo.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                In adopting the existing AndroMDA site format for the documentation, the Maven Doxia
	                plugin needs a patch to be applied.  You can check out <b>doxia-1.0-alpha-8</b>
	                from Maven SVN and apply the patch <a href="http://jira.codehaus.org/browse/MNG-545">here</a>.
	                It is not critical to apply this patch, but if it's not applied, the generated XHTML will
	                not be formated correctly but still acceptable.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                All other require plugins will be downloaded to your local repo if they don't already
	                exist.
	            </p>
	            <p>
	                You can download the source examples used in the howto for all sections
	                <a href="HowToModel-src.zip">here</a> and extract to the target/site folder of the
	                andromda-ejb3 plugin.
	            </p>
	        </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Next">
            <p>
                Before starting with the EJB3 howtos, find out how to generate your
                <a href="project.html">EJB 3.0 project</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
